. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE
AND WELCOME TO THE OCTOBER 28TH 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN PRESENT MANDEL MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SUTTER
SUTTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERALD PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT.
MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAW MATERIALS WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAHMATULLAH COLONY HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBLE PARTIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
ROMITA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I'D LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY SUE ENOS WHO
RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATION? >> US?
YES, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON
TODAY IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER IN ROOM 250
WITHIN CITY HALL ON THE SECOND FLOOR.
IF YOU ARE UNABLE TO MAKE IT IN PERSON YOU'RE ABLE TO WATCH
THE LIVESTREAM ON S.F. O VTV.ORG OR ON CHANNEL TWO X.
>> YOU CAN SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING BY EITHER
SENDING AN EMAIL TO B O S AT S.F. GOV BORG OR USE THE U.S.
POSTAL SERVICE JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
941082. IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A FUTURE
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION OR IF YOU NEED THIS LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO
BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH EIGHT ITEMS
ONE THROUGH EIGHT ARE ON CONSENT IF THESE ITEMS ARE
CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE. BUT IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM
MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH EIGHT
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR CARTER SUTTER I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EITHER ARI LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION MR. PRESIDENT
MY APOLOGIES THERE ARE TEN EYES WITH TEN EYES AND WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS.
PLEASE CALL ITEMS NINE AND TEN TOGETHER HERE WE HAVE ITEMS TWO
ORDINANCES THAT AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE FOR AFFORDABLE AND LOW INCOME HOUSING AND THE
COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX EXEMPTION ITEM NINE THIS
ORDINANCE AMENDS THE BUILDING AND PLANNING CODES TO COMPLY
WITH CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE SECTION 66007 BY POSTPONING THE
COLLECTION OF DEVELOPMENT IMPACT FEES FOR DESIGNATED
RESIDENTIAL DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS TO THE DATE OF THE
FIRST CERTIFICATE OF OCCUPANCY OR FIRST TEMPORARY CERTIFICATE
OF OCCUPANCY WHICHEVER OCCURS FIRST TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM TEN IF YOU RECALL THIS ITEM REQUIRES EIGHT VOTES OF
THE MEMBERSHIP ITEM TEN THIS ORDINANCE EXCLUDES FROM GROSS
RECEIPTS TAX THE GROSS RECEIPTS OF LOW INCOME HOUSING
PARTNERSHIP RECEIVED FROM THE LEASE OF RESIDENTIAL REAL
ESTATE BEGINNING WITH THE 2026 TAX YEAR SUSPENDS THE BUSINESS
REGISTRATION CERTIFICATE AND FEE REQUIREMENT FOR THOSE
PARTNERSHIPS BEGINNING WITH THE REGISTRATION YEAR COMMENCING
APRIL 1ST 2026 EXEMPTS FROM EXEMPTS THE CITY FROM THE
COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX RETROACTIVE TO JANUARY FIRST
2025 AND EXEMPT PERSONS HOLDING PROPERTY TO BE USED FOR CITY
SPONSORED AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECTS FROM THE COMMERCIAL
VACANCY TAX RETROACTIVE TO JANUARY FIRST, 2022 AND REFUNDS
THE COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX PAID BY EXEMPT PERSONS.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS NINE AND TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
ALL RIGHT RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 11 AND 12 TOGETHER ITEMS 11
AND 12 ARE TWO ITEMS THAT PERTAIN TO THE TREASURE ISLAND
I RFD THAT'S THE INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE
APPROXIMATELY 5.8 MILLION TO FUND AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROJECTS TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT AND PLACING THESE FUNDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE
PENDING THE SALE OF THE TAX INCREMENT REVENUE BONDS AND THE
RECEIPT OF PROCEEDS IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026.
ITEM 12 THIS RESOLUTION SUPPLEMENTS RESOLUTION NUMBER
SEVEN DASH 17 AND AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF SAN
FRANCISCO INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE OF ONE OR MORE SERIES OF BONDS IN AN
AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF 31 MILLION IT APPROVES THE
OFFICIAL STATEMENT FOR ONE OR MORE SUPPLEMENTS TO INDENTURES
OF TRUST IN THE CONTINUING DISCLOSURE CERTIFICATE ONE OR
MORE BOND TO PURCHASE AGREEMENTS WITH A JOINT
EXERCISE OF POWERS AUTHORITY AND THE BOND UNDERWRITER
AND OTHER RELATED DOCUMENTS AS DEFINED HERE IN AND MAKES OTHER
RELATED DETERMINATIONS AS DEFINED HERE IN CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THESE ITEMS ON ITEMS 11 AND 12 SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
MANDOLIN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 13 ITEM 13 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RETRO ACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE FIRE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND APPROXIMATELY $2.3 MILLION IN GRANT FUNDS FROM THE
FEDERAL EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT AGENCY ASSISTANCE TO
FIREFIGHTERS GRANT PROGRAM TO PURCHASE PERSONNEL
AND PROTECTION OF PROTECTIVE EQUIPMENT SEPTEMBER 12TH, 2023
THROUGH SEPTEMBER 11TH, 2025. >> AND WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
14 AND 15 TOGETHER. ITEMS 14 AND 15 ARE TWO
RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE COOPERATIVE AGREEMENTS WITH THE
CALIFORNIA STATE DEPARTMENT OF FORESTRY AND FIRE PROTECTION.
ITEM 14 AUTHORIZES THE FIRE DEPARTMENT TO ENTER INTO A
COOPERATIVE AGREEMENT FOR THE FIREFIGHTER PROPERTY PROGRAM
WITH CALIFORNIA STATE DEPARTMENT FORESTRY AND FIRE
PROTECTION UNDER WHICH THE DEPARTMENT MAY RECEIVE
TEMPORARY LOANS OF PROPERTY IN PROVIDING FIRE AND EMERGENCY
MEDICAL SERVICES TO INCLUDE DISASTER RELIEF ACTIVITIES FOR
A THREE YEAR TERM EFFECTIVE UPON EXECUTION OF THE
COOPERATIVE AGREEMENT FOR ITEM 15.
THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE FEDERAL EXCESS PERSONNEL
PROPERTY PROGRAM TO TO ENTER INTO A COOPERATIVE AGREEMENT
WITH SAN FRANCISCO AND THE CALIFORNIA STATE DEPARTMENT OF
FORESTRY AND FIRE PROTECTION UNDER WHICH THE DEPARTMENT
RECEIVES TEMPORARY LOANS OF EQUIPMENT FOR FIRE SUPPRESSION
AND PRICE SUPPRESSION USE FOR AN INITIAL TERM OF FIVE YEARS
EFFECTIVE UPON EXECUTION OF THE COOPERATIVE AGREEMENT.
>> AND WE CAN TAKE THESE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM 16 THIS RESOLUTION
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND IN AN APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF $63,000 A GRANT FROM
THE CALIFORNIA GOVERNOR'S OFFICE OF EMERGENCY SERVICES
FOR THE PAUL COVERDELL FORENSIC SCIENCE IMPROVEMENT PROGRAM TO
TRAIN AND PROCURE EQUIPMENT FOR THE CRIMINOLOGY LABORATORY
APRIL 1ST, 2025 THROUGH MARCH 31ST, 2026 AND SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 17. >> ITEM 17 THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES AN AWARD OF PROFESSIONAL SERVICES AGREEMENT
FOR AIRPORT CONTRACT FOR OPERATION AND MAINTENANCE OF
THE AIRPORT BAGGAGE HANDLING SYSTEMS BETWEEN BOEING YOUR
LIFECYCLE MANAGEMENT LLC AND THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR 30
MILLION A THREE YEAR TERM NOVEMBER 1ST 2025 THROUGH
OCTOBER 31ST 2028 WITH A SINGLE OPTION TO EXTEND FOR TWO
ADDITIONAL YEARS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 18.
>> ITEM 18 THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT APPROVES A FOURTH
AMENDMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND UNIVERSAL PROTECTION
SERVICES L.P. DOING BUSINESS HAS ALLIED UNIVERSAL SECURITY
SERVICES FOR UNARMED SECURITY GUARD SERVICES AT SAN FRANCISCO
GENERAL HOSPITAL. TO EXTEND THE CONTRACT BY FIVE
MONTHS FOR A TOTAL TERM OF FEBRUARY 15TH 2023 THROUGH JUNE
14TH 2026 AND INCREASES THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 2.2 MILLION
FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 12.18 MILLION AND WE CAN TAKE THIS
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 19. >> ITEM 19.
THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT AUTHORIZES THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE THE
STANDARD AGREEMENTS WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT UNDER THE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND SUSTAINABLE COMMUNITIES
PROGRAM FOR A TOTAL AWARD OF 46 MILLION TO INCLUDE 33 MILLION
DISBURSED BY CD AS A LOAN TO THE BALBOA GATEWAY LP FOR 100%
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT AT 11 FRIDA KAHLO WAY AND 12.7
MILLION TO BE DISBURSED AS A GRANT TO THE CITY FOR PUBLIC
TRANSPORTATION IMPROVEMENTS NEAR 11 FRIDA KAHLO WAY FOR THE
TERM STARTING AT THE EXECUTION DATE OF THE STANDARD AGREEMENT
THROUGH NOVEMBER 30TH 2043. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 20 AND 21 TOGETHER ITEMS 20
AND 21 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO 13 ZERO THREE LARKIN
STREET ITEM 20. THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE
EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF MULTIFAMILY HOUSING REVENUE
NOTES IN ONE OR MORE SERIES IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL
AMOUNT OF 19 MILLION FOR THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING FINANCING
FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF A 68 UNIT MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING
PROJECT LOCATED AT 13 ZERO THREE LARKIN STREET KNOWN AS 13
ZERO THREE LARKIN STREET. ITEM 21 THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE
DOCUMENTS RELATED TO A LOAN WITH 13 ZERO THREE LARKIN
STREET LP FOR AN AGGREGATE LOAN AMOUNT OF 18.5 MILLION TO
FINANCE THE ACQUISITION REHABILITATION AND PERMANENT
FINANCING OF A 100% AFFORDABLE 68 MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT FOR LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS LOCATED AT 13 ZERO
THREE LARKIN STREET AND AFFIRMS THE SEQUENT DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND WE CAN DO THESE
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
22. ITEM 22 THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE MAYOR AND THE DIRECTOR OF THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
EXECUTE LOAN DOCUMENTS RELATED TO A LOAN WITH TO PROCEED AS
SMALL PROJECTS LLC IN A TOTAL AMOUNT OF NOT TO EXCEED 38
MILLION TO FINANCE THE ACQUISITION, REHABILITATION
AND PERMANENT FINANCING OF 15 MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING
BUILDINGS FOR LOW TO MODERATE INCOME HOUSEHOLDS CONSISTS OF A
TOTAL OF 89 RESIDENTIAL RENTAL UNITS AND NINE ANCILLARY
COMMERCIAL UNITS LOCATED AT 3329 THROUGH 3333 20TH STREET
3182 THROUGH 3198 24TH STREET 3353 26TH STREET 15 CORTLAND
AVENUE 35 FAIR AVENUE 3840 FOLSOM STREET 642 THROUGH 646
GUERRERO STREET 63 THROUGH 67 LEPAGE STREET 2217 THROUGH 2221
MISSION STREET 3800 MISSION STREET 19 THROUGH 23 PROCEED TO
AVENUE 3443348 PROCEED TO AVENUE 269 THROUGH TO 71
RICHLAND AVENUE 380 SAN JOSE AVENUE AND 1015 SHOTWELL STREET
PURSUANT TO THE SMALL SITES PROGRAM TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND WE CAN
TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
23 AND 24 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 23.
>> THANK YOU. THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT
AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND DELIVERY OF MULTIFAMILY
HOUSING REVENUE BONDS IN ONE OR MORE SERIES IN AN AGGREGATE
PRINCIPAL AMOUNT 60 MILLION FOR THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING
FINANCING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF A 136 UNIT MULTIFAMILY
RENTAL HOUSING PROJECT LOCATED AT 2970 16TH STREET KNOWN AS
THE 2970 16TH STREET ITEM 24. THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE
APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY AND THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
ENTER INTO A GROUND LEASE FOR REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY
AND LOCATED AT 2970 16TH STREET WITH 1979 MISSION STREET PCH
ASSOCIATES LP FOR A LEASE TERM OF 75 YEARS AND 124 YEAR OPTION
TO EXTEND AND AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF $1 IN ORDER TO
CONSTRUCT 100% AFFORDABLE 136 UNIT MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT AS PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR FORMERLY
HOMELESS HOUSEHOLDS OR HOUSEHOLDS AT RISK OF
HOMELESSNESS TO APPROVE AN AUTHORIZED AND AMENDED
AND RESTATED LOAN AGREEMENT IN THE AMOUNT OF 61 MILLION
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 25 ITEM
25 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODE TO
REVISE THE HEALTHY AIRPORT ORDINANCE TO REQUIRE BEGINNING
ON JANUARY 1ST, 2027 THE CONTRACTING PARTIES EMPLOYING
CERTAIN AIRPORT WORKERS MAKE IRREVOCABLE HEALTH CARE
EXPENDITURES ON BEHALF OF THEIR EMPLOYEES AT TIERED RATES
REFLECTING THE EMPLOYEES HOUSEHOLD SIZE.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THIS ITEM HAS BEEN KICKING
AROUND FOR A WHILE. SUPERVISOR WALTON AND I
INTRODUCED IT BACK IN MARCH. >> IT MADE ITS WAY TO GAO A
COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO ON OCTOBER 16TH, 2025.
NONETHELESS, WE HAVE RECEIVED REQUESTS TO CONTINUE IT.
I AM INCLINED TO I SEE THERE SPEAKERS IN THE QUEUE SO I WILL
ALLOW THEM TO SPEAK BUT I AM INCLINED TO THINK THAT IT IS
APPROPRIATE TO GIVE A ONE WEEK EXTENSION.
I DON'T THINK WE SHOULD DO MORE THAN THAT.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELA AND I WOULD
MOVE TO CONTINUE THIS ITEM FOR ONE WEEK TO NOVEMBER 4TH.
IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT SUPERVISOR CHERYL ALL RIGHT.
>> THIS MOTION TO CONTINUE ONE WEEK TO NOVEMBER 4TH HAS BEEN
MADE BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR
CHERYL AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION, MADAM
CLERK ALL RIGHT. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
PASSES AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS 26 AND 27 TOGETHER.
>> ITEMS 26 AND 20 SEVEN ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS AUTHORIZING
BEHEST ID PAYMENTS FOR VARIOUS DEPARTMENTS.
ITEM 26 AUTHORIZES A SIX MONTH WAIVER OF THE CITY'S BE HOSTED
PAYMENTS ORDINANCE FOR THE MAYOR AND DESIGNATED MEMBERS OF
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO SOLICIT DONATIONS OR TO SUPPORT CORE
INITIATIVES FOR ITEM 26. THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE
OFFICE OF THE MAYOR THE OFFICE OF THE CITY ATTORNEY OF THE
CITY ADMINISTRATOR AND THE HEAD OF EACH DIVISION, OFFICE
AND DEPARTMENT UNDER THE SUPERVISION OF THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM VARIOUS PRIVATE,
NONPROFIT, PHILANTHROPIC AND OTHER ENTITIES TO SUPPORT
THE URGENT PROVISION OF LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO THE
CREATION AND ENFORCEMENT OF IMMIGRATION LAWS.
REGULATION AND POLICIES INCLUDING LITIGATION
AND REGULATORY REFORM EFFORTS AT THE LOCAL, STATE AND FEDERAL
LEVEL AND NON LEGAL SERVICES AND TO SUPPORT THE CITY'S
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES FOR GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL
SERVICES RELATED TO DEFENDING AND SUPPORTING LGBTQ RIGHTS,
GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO
DEFENDING AND SUPPORTING REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS, GOODS
AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL SERVICES RELATING TO DEFENDING
ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION LAWS AND PROMOTING ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION EFFORTS. GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING
LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO RACIAL EQUITY INITIATIVES ALL
NOTWITHSTANDING THE BEHEST ID PAYMENT ORDINANCE.
>> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE TWO ITEMS SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ED AND TATE ITEM 28 THIS
RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE ASSESSOR RECORDER, THE DEPUTY
ASSESSORS AND DIRECTORS OF POLICY AND GOVERNMENT AFFAIRS
IN THE ASSESSOR RECORDER'S OFFICE TO SOLICIT DONATIONS
FROM VARIOUS PRIVATE NONPROFIT, PHILANTHROPIC AND OTHER
ENTITIES TO SUPPORT THE URGENT PROVISION OF LEGAL SERVICES
RELATED TO THE CREATION AND ENFORCEMENT OF IMMIGRATION
LAWS, REGULATIONS AND POLICIES TO INCLUDE LITIGATION
AND REGULATORY REFORM EFFORTS AT THE LOCAL, STATE AND FEDERAL
LEVEL AND NON LEGAL SERVICES AND SUPPORT FOR THE CITY'S
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES, GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL
SERVICES RELATING TO DEFENDING AND SUPPORTING LGBTQ RIGHTS,
GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO
DEFENDING AND SUPPORTING REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS, GOODS
AND SERVICES INCLUDING LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO DEFENDING
ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION LAWS AND PROMOTING ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION EFFORTS. ALSO GOODS AND SERVICES
INCLUDING LEGAL SERVICES RELATED TO RACIAL EQUITY
INITIATIVES ALL NOTWITHSTANDING THE BEHEST OF PAYMENT ORDINANCE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT AND COLLEAGUES.
IN 2022 VOTERS PASSED PROP E THE HAZARD PAYMENTS ORDINANCE
WHICH FUNCTIONS AS A CHECK AGAINST GOVERNMENTAL CONFLICTS
OF INTEREST AND SERVES TO BUILD TRUST BETWEEN THE CITY AND ITS
RESIDENTS. THE ORDINANCE ALLOWS FOR
WAIVERS APPROVED BY THIS BOARD WHICH IS WHAT WE'RE VOTING ON
NOW. I THINK IT'S BEEN LOST ON SOME
PEOPLE THAT WE HAVE THE ABILITY TO FUNDRAISE FROM NON
INTERESTED PARTIES AND THERE ARE THOUSANDS IF NOT MILLIONS
OF THOSE KINDS OF ENTITIES IN THE BAY AREA AS WELL.
WE DON'T NEED A FUND A WAIVER TO FUNDRAISE IF CITY OFFICIALS
ARE MAKING WHAT'S CALLED A QUOTE PUBLIC APPEAL, A PUBLIC
APPEAL CAN BE A MESSAGE ON TELEVISION, RADIO, BILLBOARD
AND ONLINE PLATFORM THE DISTRIBUTION OF 200 OR MORE
IDENTICAL PIECES OF PRINTED MATERIAL THE DISTRIBUTION OF A
SINGLE EMAIL TO TWO HUNDRED OR MORE RECIPIENTS OR SPEECH TO A
GROUP OF 20 OR MORE INDIVIDUALS AS LONG AS THEY ABIDE BY
DISCLOSURE REQUIREMENTS UNDER STATE LAW, ANY WAIVER APPROVED
BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MUST ALSO INCLUDE A FINDING
THAT THE WAIVER WOULD NOT CREATE AN APPEARANCE OF
IMPROPRIETY AND WOULD BE IN THE PUBLIC INTEREST BY VOTING TO
SUPPORT THESE WAIVERS. WE ARE ENDORSING THAT FINDING
MOST OF THE WAIVERS WE ARE VOTING ON TODAY ARE RENEWALS OF
SIX MONTH WAIVERS. IN ORDER FOR ME TO FEEL
COMFORTABLE ENDORSING THE FINDING THAT THE RENEWAL
WAIVERS WOULD IN FACT BE IN THE PUBLIC INTEREST AS CHAIR OF THE
GOVERNMENT ON AN OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE, I ASKED EVERY
DEPARTMENT TO REPORT BACK TO THE COMMITTEE WHAT AMOUNT OF
FUNDING THEY HAVE DIRECTED TO THE CITY AND I'M WEIGHING THAT
CONSIDERATION WITH THE REQUESTING OFFICES POTENTIAL
NUMBER OF INTERESTED PARTIES THAT THEY ARE EXPOSED TO
IN THEIR DAY TO DAY DECISION MAKING.
>> THE ASSESSOR RECORDER'S OFFICE MAKES DECISIONS ON
ASSESSED PROPERTY VALUES WHICH TO ME EXPOSES THE OFFICE TO
HUNDREDS IF NOT THOUSANDS OF POTENTIALLY INTERESTED PARTIES
. >> THE SAME GOES FOR US AND THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHICH WE MAKE HUNDREDS OF DECISIONS
EVERY YEAR AND THAT OPENS US UP TO HUNDREDS IF NOT THOUSANDS OF
INTERESTED PARTIES WHICH IS WHY EVEN THOUGH I KNOW WELL WE
DESPERATELY NEED FUNDING I AM NOT FOR HAVING EVEN SUPERVISORS
BE ELIGIBLE FOR WAIVERS. I APPRECIATE THE WORK OF OUR
ASSESSOR RECORDER TO MAKE CONNECTIONS BETWEEN THE CITY
AND FUNDERS ESPECIALLY FOR IMMIGRANTS RIGHTS WORK TO SET
UP THE BARRY EMERGENCY FUND AND WHILE PART OF THAT WORK IS
DONE NO MONEY HAS COME DIRECTLY TO THE CITY UNDER THIS WAIVER
AND THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR AND OFFICE OF CIVIC ENGAGEMENT
AND IMMIGRATION AFFAIRS WHOSE WORK INVOLVES SUPPORTING
IMMIGRANTS ALREADY HAVE A WAIVER FOR SOLICITING THESE
SORTS OF FUNDS AND I BELIEVE CAN CONTINUE THAT WORK FOR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES AS A RESULT.
I DON'T THINK THIS PARTICULAR WAIVER IS NECESSARY AND IS NOT
WORTH THE RISK OF THE EXPOSURE. THAT SAID, I AM WATCHING THE
OTHER WAIVERS THAT WE HAVE APPROVES FOR RENEWAL TODAY
AND WILL NOT BE INCLINED TO SUPPORT THEIR RENEWAL EITHER IF
THEY DO NOT MATERIALLY BENEFIT THE PUBLIC INTEREST OR CREATE
AN APPEARANCE OF IMPROPRIETY. >> THAT'S ALL.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER I DO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR FORWARDING THIS
ITEM TO THE FULL BOARD FOR CONSIDERATION EVEN WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION. SO THANK YOU FOR DOING THAT.
IF NO ONE ELSE HAS ANYTHING TO SAY I WILL SAY THAT I DO
SUPPORT THIS WAIVER FOR THE ASSESSOR RECORDER.
I THINK THE THE VERY BREADTH OF THE DEFINITION OF INTERESTED
PARTIES AND THE FACT THAT THERE ARE SO MANY POTENTIALLY FOR
EITHER THE ASSESSOR RECORDER OR FOR US FRANKLY MEANS THAT IF WE
ARE GOING TO FEEL SAFE FUNDRAISING AND BE SURE THAT WE
ARE WITHIN THE BOUNDS OF THE LAW THEN WE NEED MORE.
IN THIS CASE HE NEEDS THE COVERAGE OF THIS WAIVER NOT TO
ENGAGE IN IN CORRUPT FUNDRAISING.
IT WILL BE DISCLOSED REGULARLY AND HE ASKS THAT HE MAKES THAT
THAT RESULTS IN CONTRIBUTIONS THAT WILL BE PUBLIC HEAVILY
AVAILABLE. PEOPLE WILL SEE THAT THAT WILL
ACT AS A DETERRENT TO BAD ACTION.
BUT BECAUSE OF THE VERY LARGE NUMBER OF POTENTIAL INTERESTED
PARTIES AND THE DIFFICULTY OF THE OF THE ASSESSOR RECORDER
HIMSELF FIGURING OUT IF HE MAY BE INADVERTENTLY RUNNING AFOUL
OF THAT, I THINK HE DOES NEED THIS UMBRELLA OF PROTECTION IF
HE IS TO BE DOING FUNDRAISING FOR THESE CAUSES WHICH I THINK
HE CAN DO AND IT IS IMPORTANT TO ALLOW HIM TO DO SO THAT'S
WHY I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS ITEM WHICH I HAVE ALSO
INTRODUCED TODAY. >> WITH THAT MADAM CLERK, COULD
YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM AN ITEM 28 SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND TWO
NOS WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 29 ITEM
20 NINE THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT HANDS HOW COULD BRETT
CONE TILLIS RESIDENCY RESIDENCY REQUIREMENT WAIVED LAURA
PADILLA ADOBO TRAY ORA RESIDENCY REQUIREMENT WAIVED
TERMS ENDING JUNE 6TH, 2026 AND ASEEL FARRAH MARIO PAZ
RESIDENCY REQUIREMENT WAIVED CELINE KENNELLY YOU PUNK NG OR
JOSE NG SARAH SOUZA AND LUCIA OBREGON LEARN A TERMS ENDING
JUNE 6TH, 2027 TO THE IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION AND PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE SIDE OF MADAM CLERK ON ITEM
TWENTY-NINTHS SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN OH HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EITHER ARE ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE
CALL ITEM 30. >> ITEM 30 WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON THURSDAY OCTOBER 23RD
AND ITEM 30 WAS FORWARDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT A RESOLUTION
THAT AUTHORIZES THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY AND THE DISTRICT
ATTORNEY'S CHIEF OF STAFF TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FOR
PROSECUTORIAL PROSECUTOR EXCUSE ME PROSECUTORIAL OPERATION
AND TECHNOLOGY NEEDS AND TO SUPPORT PUBLIC SAFETY
PREVENTION AND INTERVENTION INITIATIVES FOR SIX MONTHS
NOTWITHSTANDING THE BE HAS PAYMENT ORDINANCE AND I BELIEVE
WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED AND IT IS STILL 229
MADAM CLERK SO PLEASE CALL ITEM 31 ITEM 31 WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON MONDAY OCTOBER 27TH. THIS ITEM WAS REFERRED WITHOUT
RECOMMENDING MOTION AS AMENDED BUT WITH THE SAME TITLE ITEM 31
THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO ELIMINATE THE
NORTH BEACH SPECIAL USE DISTRICT AND CONSOLIDATE
CERTAIN CONTROLS INTO THE NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
DISTRICT EXPAND ALLOWABLE USES AND INCREASES USE SIZE LIMITS
IN THE NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT AFFIRMS THE
SPEAKER DETERMINATION AND MAKES THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES THIS LEGISLATION WILL HELP FILL EMPTY
STOREFRONTS ALLOW EXISTING SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS TO GROW
AND BRING REFORM TO COMPLEX, CONFUSING AND INEQUITABLE
PLANNING CODES ACROSS DISTRICT THREE NEIGHBORHOODS.
>> DISTRICT THREE IS REPUTATION AS THE HARDEST DISTRICT IN SAN
FRANCISCO TO START OR RUN A SMALL BUSINESS IS NOT SOMETHING
ANYONE SHOULD BE PROUD OF AND I THINK THIS LEGISLATION WILL GO
A LONG WAY TOWARDS CHANGING THAT.
A FEW HIGHLIGHTS OF WHAT OUR LEGISLATION DOES IT WILL ALLOW
FASTER VIEWS FOR SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS WHO WANT TO OPEN BY
ADDING NORTH BEACH INTO THE CITY'S PRIORITY PERMITTING
PROCESSING PROGRAM THIS ALLOWS MORE CERTAINTY AND LESS WASTED
RENT BY GUARANTEEING A PERMIT REVIEW WITHIN 90 DAYS AND IT
DOES SO WHILE KEEPING PUBLIC NOTICE.
>> IT REMOVES BANS ON USES THAT CURRENTLY EXIST ACROSS DISTRICT
THREE FOR EXAMPLE YOU ARE CURRENTLY NOT ALLOWED TO OPEN
FLEXIBLE RETAIL IN NORTH BEACH OR PARTS OF RUSSIAN HILL AND
HILL. SO FOR EXAMPLE IF YOU WANTED TO
OPEN A BOOKSTORE AND HAVE A FELLOW BUSINESS OWNER RUN A
COFFEE SHOP IN THE SAME SPACE YOU WOULD NOT BE ALLOWED TO
TODAY AND YOU ALSO ARE CURRENTLY NOT ALLOWED TO EVEN
HAVE A PATHWAY TO SMALL STOREFRONT MERGERS IN NORTH
BEACH OR POLK STREET. >> THIS PROHIBITION HAS LED TO
ONE OFF SPECIAL LEGISLATION IN THE PAST.
INSTEAD WE'RE CREATING A TRANSPARENT PATHWAY THAT ALLOWS
PUBLIC NOTICE OF STOREFRONT MERGERS.
ARTS ACTIVITIES ON HILL ARE CURRENTLY NOT ALLOWED MEANING
YOU WOULDN'T BE ABLE TO OPEN A CERAMICS STUDIO OR A DANCE
STUDIO IN THE AREA. >> WE'RE GOING TO CHANGE THAT.
FINALLY IT CONSOLIDATES TWO SEPARATE LAYERS OF RULES
IN NORTH BEACH FROM A SPECIAL USE DISTRICT AND NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICT INTO ONE INSTEAD THE NORTH BEACH
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT.
I BELIEVE SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS SHOULD BE ABLE TO LOOK IN ONE
PLACE FOR A FULL SET OF RULES. WE HAVE DEVELOPED THIS
LEGISLATION IN COLLABORATION WITH THE OFFICE OF SMALL
BUSINESS PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS
ACROSS THE DISTRICT AFTER HEARING ABOUT THE IMPACTS THAT
CURRENT EXCLUSIONARY RULES HAVE ON SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS WHO
ARE TRYING TO OPEN OR GROW IN DISTRICT THREE WE HAVE BEEN
WORKING WITH COMMUNITY GROUPS TO REFINE OUR LEGISLATION SINCE
JUNE. WE HAVE MADE A NUMBER OF
AMENDMENTS IN RESPONSE TO FEEDBACK AND WE ARE PROUD TO
HAVE EARNED SUPPORT FROM A WIDE RANGE OF SMALL BUSINESSES
AND ORGANIZATIONS INCLUDING JACKSON SQUARE MERCHANTS
ASSOCIATION, GOLDEN GATE RESTAURANT ASSOCIATION, THE SAN
FRANCISCO CHAMBER OF COMMERCE, HILL ASSOCIATION, DISCOVER
POLK, NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORS, THE CHINESE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE
AND RUSSIAN HILL NEIGHBORS. SOMETIMES WE CRAFT LEGISLATION
IN THESE CHAMBERS IN HOPES OF FUTURE USAGE BUT IN THIS CASE
WE LITERALLY HAVE SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS THAT ARE
WAITING ON THIS LEGISLATION TO PASS TO GROW THEIR BUSINESS, TO
SIGN LEASES AND TO FILL EMPTY STOREFRONTS.
EXAMPLES OF THIS INCLUDE MILANA ROM AND HER HUSBAND HIMANSHU
WHO WANT TO OPEN A CAFE ON LOMBARD STREET TO SERVE THEIR
FAMILY'S COFFEE FROM INDIA. THIS WOULD FILL A STOREFRONT
THAT HAS BEEN EMPTY FOR SEVEN YEARS.
SHADY A BELOVED MERCHANT IN NORTH BEACH WHO WANTS TO
EXPAND HIS SMALL MARKET AND GROCERY STORE INTO A SPACE
NEXT DOOR THAT HAS BEEN VACANT SINCE 2018.
A GELATO SHOP RUN BY ITALIAN IMMIGRANTS WHO WANT TO OPEN
THEIR SECOND LOCATION IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THEY WOULD FILL A
STOREFRONT THAT HAS BEEN EMPTY FOR EIGHT YEARS.
ONE WOMAN FOOD TRUCK WHO NOW WANTS TO OPEN HER FIRST BRICK
AND MORTAR BUT IS NERVOUS ABOUT PERMITTING DELAYS WITH OUR
LEGISLATION. HER APPLICATION WOULD NOW BE
GUARANTEED TO BE REVIEWED IN 90 DAYS.
A BARBER WHO WANTS TO MERGE WITH AN EMPTY STOREFRONT NEXT
DOOR SO THEY CAN ADD AN ADDITIONAL CHAIR TO GROW THEIR
BUSINESS. BUTTER AND CRUMBLE A POPULAR
BAKERY WHO WANTS TO GROW BUT STAY IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD BY
OPENING A NEW STORE FOR THEIR CAKES IN A SPACE THAT'S BEEN
EMPTY FOR FOUR YEARS. ALL OF THESE EXAMPLES OF REAL
SMALL BUSINESSES THAT WANT TO OPEN OR GROW WOULD LITERALLY BE
ILLEGAL UNLESS THIS LEGISLATION PASSES.
THAT IS THE REALITY OF WHAT THIS LEGISLATION DOES.
THIS LEGISLATION ONLY MAKES CHANGES TO THE PLANNING CODE
IN DISTRICT THREE. IN OTHER WORDS, COLLEAGUES, IT
DOES NOT MAKE ANY CHANGES TO ANY OF YOUR DISTRICTS.
YOU HAVE A CHANCE WITH TODAY'S VOTE TO PASS LEGISLATION THAT
WILL FILL EMPTY STOREFRONTS AND MAKE LIFE EASIER FOR SMALL
BUSINESS OWNERS. >> I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT. >> I DO WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR SOUDER FOR HIS EFFORT IN REALLY WORKING WITH
THE MERCHANTS AND TRYING TO FIGURE THIS OUT FOR AN
UNPRECEDENTED TIME TO FIGURE OUT WHAT TO DO AND HOW WE CAN
CONTINUE TO SUPPORT OUR MERCHANTS COMING OUT FROM COVID
AND NOW BUT WE ALSO HAVE WITNESSED A ROBUST PUBLIC
COMMENTS AND TWO TO LAND USE COMMITTEE MEETINGS
AND REFLECTED THERE'S A SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF
OPPOSITION LETTERS AND I WANTED TO ARTICULATE WHAT MY APPROACH
AND THINKING IS FOR TODAY BECAUSE IT IS VERY RARE THAT I
AS A COLLEAGUE WOULD CHALLENGE THE WISHES OF THE DISTRICT
SUPERVISOR. I DO HAVE TO ADMIT THAT I DO
HAVE PERSONAL FEELINGS AND ATTACHMENT TO THE
NEIGHBORHOOD THAT I GREW UP IN NORTH BEACH AND CHINATOWN
AND THIS PARTICULARLY IS IMPACTING NORTH BEACH.
AND SO I JUST WANT TO TO ARTICULATE MY CONCERNS ON
BEHALF OF MANY OF THOSE THAT I KNOW ON A PERSONAL LEVEL
BECAUSE HOW I GREW UP AND WHERE I GREW UP THAT I WANT TO POINT
TO A LETTER THAT WE RECEIVED TODAY FROM STEWARD.
>> WHAT'S THE PRESIDENT OF NORTH BEACH BUSINESS
ASSOCIATION. IN THE LETTER ACTUALLY
ARTICULATED THE SUPPORT OF WHAT SUPERVISOR SOUDER IS TRYING TO
ATTEMPT TO DO HERE WITH THE LEGISLATION AND IT'S NOT
PERTAINING TO ANY OF THE AREAS THAT THE SUPERVISOR INDICATED
SUCH AS RUSSIAN HILL, HILL OR POLK STREET OR EVEN LUMBER
STREETS. >> THIS ONE IS SPECIFICALLY
ADDRESSING CONCERNS FOR NORTH BEACH AND JACKSON SQUARE
NEIGHBORHOODS AND THIS SEEMS TO BE THE MOST CONTROVERSIAL PARTS
OF THE ENTIRE LEGISLATION. >> AND SO IT IS UNUSUAL TO
PROPOSE THIS BUT I WANTED TO BE ABLE TO ARTICULATE AGAIN, YOU
KNOW, TO WALK THROUGH THE CONCERNS I ARTICULATED
IN PRESIDENT WATTS LETTER AND THAT IT HAS ARTICULATED
SPECIFIC POINTS OUT THAT HERE IS NUMBER ONE PREVENTING
UNLIMITED RESTAURANTS CONVERSIONS THAT WOULD
OVERSATURATE OUR MARKET. AND I UNDERSTAND THAT I GREW UP
IN NORTH BEACH UNDERSTANDING RESTAURANTS AND BARS,
OVERCROWDING AND COMPETING WITH EACH OTHER AND I THINK THAT'S
THE REASON WHY THERE'S A LONG STANDING RATIO TO MAKE SURE
THAT THERE ARE OTHER SHOPS BAKERY AND LAUNDRY MATS
AND MANY OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD ANGERING BUSINESS CAN REMAIN
BEYOND JUST RESTAURANTS AND BARS.
THE SECOND AMENDMENTS THAT THEY'RE SUGGESTING IS
RESTRICTING STORE FROM MERGER THAT PRICE OUR SMALL
BUSINESSES. IT'S THE SAME CONCERN THAT I
HAVE PREVIOUSLY THINKING ABOUT WHAT THAT MEANS FOR SMALL
BUSINESS AND VERSUS ADVANTAGE THAT FORMULA RETAIL WOULD GAIN
IN SOME NEIGHBORHOODS. AND THIS CASE PARTICULARLY FOR
NORTH BEACH THERE IS STILL REINSTATING THE USE SIZE CAP.
AND AGAIN, I THINK THIS IS A CONCERN ABOUT COMPETITION WITH
FORMULA RETAIL AND CHAIN SHOP THAT'S COMING IN AND USUALLY BE
ABLE TO TAKE UP BIGGER SPACE AND LEAVE BEHIND SMALL BUSINESS
THAT MAY OR MAY NOT BE ABLE TO AFFORD THE KIND OF RENT OR
UTILIZE THE ENTIRE SPACE AND BE ABLE TO START THEIR BUSINESS OR
MAINTAIN THEIR BUSINESS. LAST BUT NOT LEAST IS TO CREATE
PATHWAY FOR VACANT RETAIL SPACES THROUGH A DIFFERENT
SECTIONS WHICH IS SECTIONS 186.4.
THEY'RE VERY SPECIFIC AND I REALLY APPRECIATE THE NORTH
BEACH BUSINESS ASSOCIATION ARTICULATING THOSE.
AND SO WITH THAT COLLEAGUES IT'S I WANTED TO SAY THAT WE DO
HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY TO LISTEN TO SOME OF SAN FRANCISCO MOST
ICONIC RENOWN BUSINESS THAT ACTUALLY ARE OPPOSING
SUPERVISORS FROM DISTRICT THREE'S CHANGES PROPOSED TODAY
THAT'S INCLUDING CITY LIGHTS BOOKSELLERS TONY'S PIZZA SPARKS
AND SO TAMARA WHICH ALL SHOPS AND STORES AND AND RESTAURANTS
I GREW UP WITH SO I HAVE TO SAY I AGREE WITH THEM THAT NORTH
BEACH IS DRIVING AND THIS IS SOMETHING THAT WE OUGHT TO
CONSIDER AND THE MOTION THAT I AM PROPOSING IS TO DIVIDE THE
FILE AND TO FOR US TO CONSIDER THE FOLLOWING SECTIONS
AND REFER THE NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
DISTRICT AND SPECIAL USE DISTRICT AND JACKSON SQUARE
SPECIAL USE DISTRICT TO BACK TO THE COMMITTEE.
>> AND IF I MAY I'M GOING TO READ OUT LOUD THAT MOTION
AND AND SPECIFIC SECTIONS THAT WE'RE TRYING TO DIVIDE FROM THE
FILE WHICH IS SECTION TWO, ARTICLE ONE, SECTIONS 1 OR 2
DEFINITIONS ON PAGE TWO LINES 15 THROUGH PAGE FOUR, LINE
THREE, SECTION THREE, ARTICLE 1.2 SECTIONS 1 TO 1 POINT TO
NONRESIDENTIAL USE SIZE LIMITS ON PAGE FOUR LINES FIVE THROUGH
PAGE FIVE LINES 13 SECTIONS FOR ARTICLE 1.7 SECTIONS 186.
EXEMPTION OF LIMIT TO COMMERCIAL AND INDUSTRIAL NON
CONFORMING USES ON PAGE FIVE LINE 15 THROUGH PAGE SIX LINE
SIX SECTION FIVE ARTICLE TWO SECTIONS 2A1 CLASSES OF USE
DISTRICTS. PAGE SIX LINES EIGHT THROUGH
LINE 19 SECTIONS 2.49.25 JACKSON SQUARE SPECIAL USE
DISTRICT FROM PAGE EIGHT LINES SEVEN THROUGH PAGE TEN LINE 17.
SECTION SIX ARTICLE THREE SECTION THREE O 3.2 C NINE
AND SECTIONS 3 OR 4 PLY PLANNED UNITS DOUBLE DEVELOPMENT PAGE
TEN LINES 19 THROUGH PAGE 11 LINE 24 SECTION SEVEN ARTICLE
SEVEN, SECTION 7 OR 3 NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
DISTRICT REQUIREMENTS AND SECTION SEVEN TWO TO NORTH
BEACH COMMERCIAL DISTRICT. >> PAGE 12 LINE ONE THROUGH
PAGE 19 LINE 17 SECTION 7780 NORTH BEACH SPECIAL USE
DISTRICT REPEALED FROM PAGE 23 LINE FIVE THROUGH PAGE 27 LINE
FIVE I KNOW CLEARLY IN A SECOND FOR THIS MOTION TO IN ORDER FOR
US TO MOVE THIS FORWARD BUT I'M ARTICULATING THE REASON OF WHY
I WOULD MAKE THIS ATTEMPT AND COLLEAGUES I UNDERSTAND
THAT YOU MAY HAVE OTHER QUESTIONS AND THINKING I'M
SIMPLY REPRESENTING THE NEIGHBORS THAT I KNOW, THE
MERCHANTS THAT I KNOW ON A PERSONAL LEVEL AND SPEAKING ON
THEIR BEHALF WHILE NOT AS THEIR DISTRICT SUPERVISOR BUT
CERTAINLY AS A REPRESENTATIVE WHO GREW UP IN THAT
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> THANK YOU.
THROUGH THE PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHAN CAN WE GET A
COPY OF THAT? >> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS MADE A
MOTION. IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
WALTON? >> OKAY.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD COLLEAGUES I WISH TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF
ITEM 31 BY THE SANDERS DISTRICT THREE DRIVES LEGISLATION AND WE
COMMENTING BRIEFLY IN OPPOSITION TO THIS AMENDMENT
FOR A COUPLE OF REASONS. WE'VE BEEN THROUGH TWO LAND USE
COMMITTEE MEETINGS ON THIS ITEM AND OVER THE COURSE OF BOTH OF
THOSE HEARINGS WHICH WERE QUITE THOROUGH AH IT WAS CLEAR THAT
OUR SYSTEM OF RULES AND REGULATIONS DISORIENT WOULD
BE SHOP OWNERS AND RESTAURANT RESTAURANTEURS AND STYMIES THE
GROWTH OF HOMEGROWN FAVORITES ACROSS THE CITY AND THESE RULES
IN DISTRICT THREE COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS HAVE BEEN ESPECIALLY
PROBLEMATIC. THIS LEGISLATION TRIMS BACK THE
SPIDER'S WEB OF RULES THAT HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO STOREFRONT
VACANCIES IN THE VIBRANT NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE
NORTHEASTERN SAN FRANCISCO. IMPROVEMENTS INCLUDE ALLOWING
NORTH BEACH BUSINESSES TO BE ELIGIBLE FOR PRIORITY PERMIT
PROCESSING, ALLOWING FOR ARTS ACTIVITIES ON GROUND FLOORS IN
HILL AND RAISING THE USE THREE USE SIZE THRESHOLDS THAT
TRIGGER THE NEED FOR A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION.
IT ALSO MAKES IT EASIER FOR BARS, RESTAURANTS AND FLEXIBLE
RETAIL USES TO OPEN AND COMBINE DUPLICATIVE SETS OF RULES THAT
CURRENTLY GOVERN BUSINESS USES IN NORTH BEACH.
IMPORTANTLY, THIS LEGISLATION DOES NOT MODIFY FORMULA RETAIL
REQUIREMENTS THAT HELP KEEP REGIONAL AND NATIONAL CLIENT
CHAINS AT BAY. >> THE BENEFICIARIES WILL BE
BUSINESSES LOOKING TO ADD THE UNIQUE CHARACTER OF THE
DISTRICT NOT BIG BOX STORES AS SOME HAVE FEARED.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER AND HIS TEAM HAVE WORKED CLOSELY WITH
THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND BUSINESS GROUPS FROM ACROSS HIS DISTRICT
OVER THE COURSE OF THE YEAR AND HE HAS MADE SEVERAL
ADJUSTMENTS ALREADY IN NORTH BEACH, JACKSON SQUARE, HILL
ELSEWHERE BASED ON FEEDBACK FROM THE COMMUNITY AS RECENTLY
AS YESTERDAY AND IT IS BECAUSE OF THAT COLLABORATION
AND CONSENSUS BUILDING THAT SUPERVISOR SAUTER HAS BRIDGED
COLLABORATION AND ENDORSEMENTS FROM ORGANIZATIONS LIKE THE SAN
FRANCISCO CHAMBER OF COMMERCE AND THE CHINESE CHAMBER OF
COMMERCE AND NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATIONS LIKE THE NORTH
BEACH NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION. THESE FIXES CLEARLY ARE NOT A
SOLUTION LOOKING FOR A PROBLEM AS SOME HAVE SAID IT IS A
SUPERVISOR. SAUTER HAS IDENTIFIED ACTUAL
SMALL BUSINESSES THAT ARE READY TO GO AND ARE AWAITING THESE
CHANGES TO OPEN OR EXPAND THEIR BUSINESSES.
>> WE HEARD IN PUBLIC COMMENT OVER TWO SESSIONS MULTIPLE
HOURS A MAJORITY IF NOT A SUPERMAJORITY OF THE SMALL
BUSINESSES THAT CAME OUT WERE IN SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR SADR'S
LEGISLATION. WE CAN ALWAYS CHERRY PICK
DEFINE OPPOSITION BUT IT TAKES A LOT OF EFFORT FOR A SMALL
BUSINESS TO COME OUT AND SUPPORT AT A LAND USE
COMMITTEE IN THE MIDDLE OF A DAY WHEN THEY HAVE ACTUAL
BUSINESSES TO RUN AND TO COME OUT IN SUPPORT OF A
LEGISLATION. CLEARLY WHEN A SUPERMAJORITY OF
THOSE BUSINESSES ARE COMING OUT IN SUPPORT AT OUR HEARINGS IT
IS BECAUSE THEY KNOW THAT THIS WILL BE A SIGNIFICANT BOON TO
THRIVING IN THIS NEIGHBORHOOD. >> WE HEARD HOW THESE CHANGES
OF THESE RULES WILL BENEFIT FOR THOSE TRYING TO START NEW
BUSINESSES THAT WILL SERVE THIS COMMUNITY, THE CITY AND SUPPORT
RESIDENTS AND BUSINESSES. I THINK ONE OF MY FAVORITE
COMMENTS WAS FROM THE SMALL BUSINESS OWNER OF BUTTER
AND CRUMBLE, WHICH IS AN EXTREMELY SUCCESSFUL LOCAL
BAKERY ALREADY THERE LOOKING TO EXPAND THEIR FOOTPRINT
AND BRING MORE FOOT TRAFFIC TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND YET THEY
ARE UNABLE TO DO SO AND ARE STYMIED BY OUR EXISTING
REGULATIONS. WE SHOULD BE SUPPORTING THE
BEST OF THE BEST OF OUR SMALL BUSINESSES IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND THIS LEGISLATION IS GOING TO ACHIEVE THAT.
THAT IS WHY I AM HAPPY TO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION
AND RESPECT SUPERVISOR SADR'S CONTINUOUS AMENDMENTS THAT HE
HAS MADE IN CONSIDERATION OF THE COMMUNITY.
AND I WOULD ASK AND I'M CURIOUS FROM SUPERVISOR SADR WERE YOU
AWARE OF THE AMENDMENTS THAT WERE JUST COMING TO US TODAY
RIGHT NOW? AND IF NOT, I'M CURIOUS WHY
THESE WERE NOT PRESENTED TO THE LAND USE COMMITTEE IN THE TWO
SESSIONS THAT WE ALREADY HAD AND WITH THESE COMMENTS ALREADY
PROVIDED. BECAUSE THAT SHOULD BE THE
PROCESS THAT WE GO THROUGH. WE HAD TWO MEETINGS ON THIS
ALREADY. WE SHOULD HAVE HEARD THESE
AMENDMENTS BEFORE AND IN LIGHT OF THAT.
I THINK THERE'S BEEN ROBUST DISCUSSION COMMUNITY INPUT
AND THIS LEGISLATION IS READY TO MOVE FORWARD AS IS.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH CHAIR MADAM AND I JUST
WANT TO LEND MY $0.02 AS TO WHY I SUPPORT THE MOTION MADE BY
SUPERVISOR CHIN. I THINK THAT OUT OF RESPECT FOR
COMMUNITY INPUT AROUND ANY CHANGES IN AREAS WITH DISSENT
IN AREAS THAT WOULD HAVE A NEGATIVE IMPACT, IT MAKES SENSE
FOR US TO ALLOW FOR THOSE FURTHER CONVERSATIONS AND THESE
PROPOSED CHANGES IN THE ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE. WE'LL HAVE A LASTING EFFECT ON
ENTIRE COMMUNITIES AND SHOULD BE ONLY POSSIBLE THROUGH A
THOUGHTFUL AND INCLUSIVE PROCESS.
I THINK WE'RE ALL AWARE OF WHAT CAN HAPPEN IF WE IGNORE
COMMUNITY VOICE AND WANT TO LEARN MORE ABOUT WHAT THEY FEEL
IS NECESSARY IN THIS CONVERSATION TO POSSIBLY GAIN
SUPPORT. >> BUSINESSES HAVE REACHED OUT
TO OUR OFFICE. INDIVIDUALS HAVE REACHED OUT TO
OUR OFFICERS IN OUR OFFICES WITH CONCERNS AND I THINK THAT
THEY SHOULD BE HEARD. >> I PERSONALLY SPEND A LOT OF
TIME IN NORTH BEACH AND HAVE HEARD CONCERNS OF
OVERSATURATION PRIOR TO THIS LEGISLATION AND JUST
IN GENERAL. AND SO I DO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR
CHAN'S MOTION ALSO. JUST WANT TO ADD THAT IF OUR
FOCUS IS TO REALLY FILL STOREFRONTS THEN WE SHOULD NOT
BE PROVIDING VACANCY TAX WAIVERS AND USE THE TOOLS THAT
WE HAVE TO SUPPORT OCCUPANCY. AND SO I AGAIN WANT TO LIVE MY
SUPPORT FOR SUPERVISOR CHAN'S MOTION AND REALLY WANT TO ALLOW
COMMUNITY INPUT FROM AREAS THAT ARE NOT EXCITED ABOUT THIS
LEGISLATION. I THINK THAT THE MOTION MADE BY
A SUPERVISOR RESPECTS THE DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISORS
INTENT AND ALLOWS FOR THIS TO MOVE FORWARD AND A GOOD CHUNK
OF WHAT'S BEING PROPOSED BUT ALSO ALLOWS FOR VOICE FROM
COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
AMENDMENT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG.
COLLEAGUES, I BELIEVE THAT OUR CITY ATTORNEY AND OUR CLERK
WOULD ENJOY HAVING A LITTLE BIT OF TIME TO THINK THROUGH HOW TO
DEAL WITH THIS MOTION BEFORE WE VOTE ON IT.
SO WE DO HAVE TWO PEOPLE IN THE QUEUE.
I'M GOING TO CALL ON THEM THEN I THINK WE'LL DO OUR 230
SPECIAL COMMENDATION AND LET LET OUR CLERK AND ATTORNEY WORK
WITH THE MAKER OF THE MOTION ON ON ON IT AND THEN WE CAN TAKE
IT UP AGAIN AFTER THAT 230 SPECIAL SPECIAL ORDER.
>> ALL RIGHT. CHAIRMAN LUGAR, THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. PRESIDENT MANDELL AND I WILL BE
SUPPORTING THE ORDINANCE AS WRITTEN BY THE DISTRICT THREE
SUPERVISOR AND NOT SUPPORTING THE MOTION TO DIVIDE THE FILE
AND SEND IT BACK TO COMMITTEE. WE HAD TWO HEARINGS ON THIS
ORDINANCE AT THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
I JUST WANT TO ADD A COUPLE OF THINGS.
>> FIRST, WHEN YOU SAY COMMUNITY, HE SUPPORTS IT OR
DOESN'T SUPPORT IT. IN THE FIVE YEARS I'VE BEEN ON
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS I CAN THINK OF A HANDFUL OF THINGS
WHERE COMMUNITY ON CONTENTIOUS ISSUES ALL FELL ON THE SAME
SIDE OF THE ISSUE. BY DEFINITION WE ARGUE ABOUT
THINGS IN SAN FRANCISCO WE ARE NOT ALL IN AGREEMENT AS TO
WHERE TO PROCEED BUT WE HAVE A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND WE DO
HAVE DISTRICT REPRESENTATION. SO IN THE LAND USE COMMITTEE WE
IN THE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAVE A LONG
TRADITION OF DEFERRING TO THE DISTRICT SUPERVISOR ON LAND USE
DECISIONS SPECIFICALLY BECAUSE WE TRUST THAT THE DISTRICT
SUPERVISORS KNOW THEIR DISTRICT THE BEST.
I THINK THAT THIS IS A SLIPPERY GOING DOWN THIS PATH WHERE
OTHER DISTRICT SUPERVISORS WANT TO WRITE LEGISLATION FOR A
DIFFERENT DISTRICT PUTS US ON A PATH THAT I FRANKLY DON'T WANT
TO BE ON ON THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
BUT FOR THAT REASON I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING THE MOTION AND I
SUPPORT THE ORDINANCE AS WRITTEN.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER LAST WORD
BEFORE WE GET PRESENT. I KNOW THERE'S A LOT OF AMAZING
HONOREES I WILL BE FAIRLY BRIEF.
I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING THE MOTION OR AMENDMENTS.
YOU KNOW MY COLLEAGUES COMMENTS ARE INTERESTING BUT THEY'RE NOT
ACCURATE TO WHAT IS IN THIS LEGISLATION.
IT DOES NOT ALLOW FOR MORE RESTAURANTS AND BARS.
WE ARE MAINTAINING THE CONTROL FOR NORTH BEACH SAYING THAT
RESTAURANTS CAN ONLY GO INTO A SPACE THAT WAS PREVIOUSLY A
FOOD OR BEVERAGE ESTABLISHMENT. BARS CAN ONLY GO INTO A SPACE
THAT WAS PREVIOUSLY A BAR KEEPING THE CONDITIONAL USE
REQUIREMENT FOR BOTH RESTAURANTS AND BARS.
THE CHANGE IS LIMITED TO LIMITED IS LIMITED TO LIMITED
RESTAURANTS WHICH ARE THE SMALLER SCALE FOOTPRINTS.
IT DOES NOT ALLOW FORMULA RETAIL AS WAS SUGGESTED AND IT
DOES NOT CHANGE A USE SIZE CAP THAT WAS REMOVED IN PREVIOUS
LEGISLATION. IT IS NOT IN THIS LEGISLATION.
SO THE CONCERNS ARE LARGELY INACCURATE.
THERE HAVE BEEN A NUMBER OF AMENDMENTS SPECIFIC TO NORTH
BEACH AND IN JACKSON SQUARE FIVE SEPARATE IN FACT WHICH
HAVE BEEN MADE OVER THE PAST MONTH THERE'S BEEN TWO
EXTENSIONS OR CONTINUANCES. THERE'S BEEN DOZENS OF MEETINGS
WITH NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATIONS AND MERCHANT GROUPS AND A LOT
OF REALLY GOOD PRODUCTIVE BACK AND FORTH AND FEEDBACK.
AND I THINK, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE TO LIVE IN THE REALITY OF WHAT
THIS LEGISLATION IS. I READ OUT A HANDFUL OF THE
SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS THAT THIS WILL ACTUALLY ALLOW TO TO GROW
TO EXPAND, TO COME TO DISTRICT THREE AND THAT'S THE REALITY
AND I WOULD RATHER LIVE IN THE REALITY RATHER THAN GET INTO
INACCURACIES ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION.
SO I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT AGAIN AND I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING A
SUGGESTED AMENDMENT BY THE DISTRICT ONE SUPERVISOR.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER AND WITH THAT WE WILL WE WILL
RETURN TO THIS ITEM AFTER HOUR AFTER HOUR TO 30 SPECIAL ORDER.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL 230 SPECIAL ORDER?
>> YES, THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 IS THE RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> ALL RIGHT.
WE HAVE SOME GREAT ONES TODAY AND WE ARE GOING TO START WITH
SUPERVISOR DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU. PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES IN CELEBRATION OF FILIPINO-AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE A REMARKABLE ORGANIZER THAT HAS
BEEN SHAPING THE GLOBAL STORY OF FILIPINA LEADERSHIP FOR 25
YEARS. THE FOUNDATION FOR FILIPINA
WOMEN'S NETWORK OR F.W. AND FOR A QUARTER CENTURY UN HAS BEEN A
STRONG VOICE FOR EMPOWERMENT AND EQUALITY.
UNDER THE VISIONARY LEADERSHIP OF MERRILEE MONTEIRO.
AFTER UN BUILT A WORLDWIDE SISTERHOOD OF FILIPINA LEADERS
AND AS MERRILEE MERRILEE WHY DON'T YOU COME UP TO THE TO THE
PODIUM SO I CAN SEE YOU WHILE WE'RE INTO UNDER MARILYN'S
VISIONARY LEADERSHIP. AND BUILT A WORLDWIDE
SISTERHOOD OF FILIPINO LEADERS WHO FEARLESSLY SPEAK OUT, WHO
TIRELESSLY UPLIFT ONE ANOTHER AND WHO CONTINUALLY DEMONSTRATE
THAT WHEN FILIPINO WOMEN RISE TOGETHER THEY CHANGE THE WORLD
. SINCE 2003 F.W. PN HAS BEEN
LEADING ONE OF THE NATION'S MOST CELEBRATED AND COURAGEOUS
ANTI-VIOLENCE MOVEMENTS WITH ITS PRODUCTION OF THE
MONOLOGUES ALSO KNOWN AS SUPPING POOKIE IN TAGALOG.
THE AWARD WINNING PERFORMANCE PIECE BY THE CELEBRATED PLAYER
PLAYWRIGHT EVEN ENSLER NOW KNOWN AS VE FROM THE EARLIEST
DAYS OF F.W. NS PERFORMANCE PRODUCTIONS.
THEY WERE CONTROVERSIAL WITH SOME AMONG THOSE EASILY
OFFENDED DISMISSIVELY REFERRING TO MARYLEE AS THAT LADY.
BUT WHAT BECAME WHAT BEGAN AS A PROVOCATIVE PERFORMANCE WOULD
BECOME A TRADITION AND THEN BECOME A MOVEMENT A VISIBILITY
OF HEALING AND OF EMPOWERMENT TURNING STORIES OF TRAUMA INTO
STORIES OF STRENGTH AND SPARKING CONVERSATIONS
ABOUT DOMESTIC VIOLENCE THAT ALL COMMUNITIES DESPERATELY
NEED TO TAKE PART IN. FROM THOSE PERFORMANCES CAME
LOVE BRUNCHES, SAFE SPACES FOR WOMEN.
WOMEN COULD CONNECT SHARE AND HEAL TOGETHER.
FROM THERE GREW A POWERFUL CAMPAIGN FOR JUSTICE, EDUCATION
AND SUPPORT FOR SURVIVORS. WORK BY OFW AND WHICH CONTINUES
TO THIS DAY THROUGH THEIR DISRUPT LEADERSHIP BOOK SERIES
F.W. UN HAS AMPLIFIED THE VOICES OF MORE THAN 160
FILIPINO AUTHORS FROM 16 COUNTRIES TELLING THE STORIES
OF WOMEN WHO OVERCAME POVERTY, DISCRIMINATION AND VIOLENCE TO
BECOME LEADER LEADERS IN A MULTITUDE OF FIELDS.
OVER THE YEARS THE GLOBAL F.W. AND 100 AWARDS HAVE HONORED
FILIPINO TRAIL BLAZERS IN 33 COUNTRIES BUILDING A GLOBAL
NETWORK OF MENTORSHIP AND A COLLABORATION THAT CONTINUES TO
INSPIRE. AND HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WHERE
ONE BEGAN, THEY'VE BEEN AN OUTSTANDING AND TRUSTED PARTNER
TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO WORKING WITH LOCAL
LEADERS TO ADVANCE GENDER EQUITY, TO PROMOTE CIVIC
PARTICIPATION AND TO STRENGTHEN THE VOICE OF OUR ENTIRE
FILIPINO COMMUNITY. HOWEVER FAR BETTER THAN TO
LISTEN TO A MUNICIPAL ELECTED OFFICIAL LIKE MYSELF DESCRIBE
THE MONOLOGUES WOULD BE TO EXPERIENCE THE PERFORMANCE
IN PERSON. SO THOSE INTERESTED ARE URGED
TO SEEK WHAT LIMITED SEATING MAY STILL BE AVAILABLE TO JOIN
F.W. AND TONIGHT 7 P.M. AT THE HERBST THEATER FOR THE 25TH
ANNIVERSARY PERFORMANCE OF THE MONOLOGUES.
LIKE F.W. IN ITSELF THE STAGE PERFORMANCE IS A POWERFUL
HEARTBREAK FELT AND INSPIRING CELEBRATION OF COURAGE,
COMMUNITY AND THE UNSTOPPABLE POWER OF FILIPINO WOMEN MERELY
AS WE BRING OUR ANNUAL CELEBRATION OF
FILIPINO-AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH TO A CLOSE AND ON BEHALF OF A
GRATEFUL CITY AS REPRESENTED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. I PROUDLY PRESENT THIS
COMMENDATION TO THE FOUNDATION FOR FILIPINO WOMEN'S NETWORK
IN CELEBRATION OF 25 YEARS OF LEADERSHIP IN CHANGING LIVES
HERE AT HOME AND AROUND THE WORLD.
>> CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR REMARKABLE MILESTONE AND WE DO
WELCOME ANY WORK BEFORE YOU. WHILE ALL RIGHT NOW YOU'RE
GOING TO GET LOTS OF APPLAUSE AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK, MARILEE,
I WOULD JUST LIKE TO ADD MY MY OWN CONGRATULATIONS.
IT HAS BEEN SUCH A TREAT GETTING TO KNOW YOU THESE LAST
FEW YEARS AND YOU ARE SO IMPRESSIVE AND HAD DONE SUCH
GREAT THINGS SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR DOING
THIS THIS COMMENDATION. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISE YOUR DORSEY AND SUPERVISOR MAN FOR HONORING
US. AS YOU KNOW I BROUGHT OUR
MEMBERS TO COME FROM SIX 12 COUNTRIES.
WE ARE CONVENING OUR ANNUAL FILIPINAS SUMMIT IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND AND THIS IS SUCH A TREAT FOR YOU TO RECOGNIZE
US. I IF I MAY READ MY RESPONSE.
GOOD AFTERNOON, EVERYONE OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ESPECIALLY
PRESIDENT MEN AND MY SUPERVISOR MATT MATT DORSEY.
MY NAME IS MARILEE BANDERA. I'M THE FOUNDER AND CEO OF THIS
FILIPINO WOMEN'S NETWORK. >> THIS BOARD HAS LONG
CHAMPIONED EQUITY, ECONOMIC VITALITY AND COMMUNITY
EMPOWERMENT AND THOSE VALUES PERFECTLY ALIGN WITH F W ITS
MISSION. FOR 25 YEARS WE'VE BEEN
CONNECTING LEADERS CREATING OPERATIVE MESSAGES AND PROVING
THAT WHEN YOU INVEST IN WOMEN'S LEADERSHIP ENTIRE COMMUNITIES
THRIVE. >> 25 YEARS AGO RIGHT HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO W AND WAS BORN FROM A SINGLE BUT BUT POWERFUL
REALIZATION FILIPINO WOMEN STORIES WEREN'T BEING TOLD AT
THAT TIME. >> WHEN I SEARCH THE WORD
FILIPINA ONLINE THE RESULTS WERE DEVASTATING.
WE WERE CALLED MAIL ORDER A MAIL ORDER BRIDES.
WE WERE STARTING TO TYPE TO SUBMISSIVE WIVES EXOTIC AND .
>> AND INVISIBILITY IN LEADERSHIP.
SO WE SET OUT TO DISRUPT THE NARRATIVE.
WE LAUNCHED THE SHAPE THE FILIPINA IMAGE CAMPAIGN TO
AMPLIFY VOICES AND TO ENSURE THAT THE WORLD ALSO SEES
FILIPINA WOMEN WOMEN AS WE TRULY ARE LEADERS, INNOVATORS
AND CHANGEMAKERS. >> DON'T MISUNDERSTAND ME I
HAVE NOTHING ABOUT MAIL ORDER BRIDES.
WE FACT HAVE MEMBERS WHO HAVE NOW BECOME VERY SUCCESSFUL
IN BUSINESS OR IN THEIR CAREERS TO GET OUT OF POVERTY.
THEY WERE ABLE TO MARRY SOME NICE MEANT AND ESTABLISHED
FAMILIES AND CREATED FAMILIES. SAN FRANCISCO GAVE US OUR START
AND WE'VE NEVER FORGOTTEN THAT. >> WE WORK CLOSELY WITH CITY
AGENCIES INCLUDING THE COMMISSION THE STATUS OF WOMEN
,THE MAYOR'S OFFICE COLLABORATIVE AGAINST HUMAN
TRAFFICKING, THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE CONSORTIUM AND I
MYSELF HAVE SERVED THE REDISTRICTING TASK FORCE
AND THE COMMUNITY OCI COMMISSION.
>> THE SUCCESSOR AGENCY OF THE SAN FRANCISCO REDEVELOPMENT
COMMISSION. WE'VE BEEN APPOINTED TO
COMMISSIONS MEMBERS. MANY MEMBERS HAVE BEEN
APPOINTED TO COMMISSIONS BY MAYORS WILLIE BROWN, GAVIN
NEWSOM AND THE LATE ED LEE. THIS CITY SHAPED US AND WE'VE
WORKED TO GIVE BACK IN MEANINGFUL WAYS.
TODAY AFTER WE GAIN HAS GROWN INTO A GLOBAL MOVEMENT OVER A
THOUSAND AWARDEES ACROSS 32 COUNTRIES TODAY WE HAVE
DELEGATES WHO TRAVEL FROM DUBAI, LONDON, SYDNEY, PERTH,
MANILA, CEBU MANY STATES ACROSS AMERICA AND OF COURSE A
DEDICATED LOCAL SAN FRANCISCO BASED MEMBERS.
THESE ARE PROFESSIONALS ENTREPRENEURS, GOVERNMENT
LEADERS, MAYORS, DOCTORS, CEOS AND THEY'RE SHAPING POLICY.
>> WE HAVE SOME ELECTED OFFICIALS HERE A MAYOR FROM
STEVENAGE IN LONDON, A MAYOR OF SAN FERNANDO PAMPANGA IN THE
PHILIPPINES ASCENDED A SAN DIEGO SUPERIOR COURT JUDGE,
BOARD TRUSTEES AND MANY OTHERS THAT I CAN'T.
>> I CAN SEE THEM WHERE THEY ARE AND SUPERVISORS THEY CAME
HERE DESPITE CONCERNS ABOUT ENTERING SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THEY CAME BECAUSE THEY BELIEVE THEY BELIEVE IN THIS
CITY. >> THEY'RE STAYING IN OUR
HOTELS, DINING IN OUR RESTAURANTS, EXPERIENCING OUR
CULTURE, CONTRIBUTING TO THE ECONOMIC RECOVERY.
>> THIS BOARD IS WORKING TO STRENGTHEN.
>> THAT'S THE POWER OF PURPOSE DRIVEN DRIVEN GATHERINGS.
>> OUR ENTIRE CANADA CONTINGENT PURPOSELY BOYCOTTED OUR
CONFERENCE BECAUSE OF WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE IN THE U.S..
>> BUT THERE'S ONE THING THAT I WANT TO ADDRESS THAT CANNOT BE
IGNORED. FILIPINO AND FILIPINO
REPRESENTATION AND IN SAN FRANCISCO'S LEADERSHIP REMAINS
INADEQUATE. THIS BOARD HAS THE POWER TO
CHANGE THAT. >> THE TALENT IS RIGHT HERE.
>> MANY OF US ARE TALENTED. >> JASON CHAN, ONE OF THE OUR
MALE ALLIES FOR THE LAST 25 YEARS FOUNDED THE FILIPINO
AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH WHEN HE WAS WITH MAYOR GAVIN NEWSOM AS
A AAPI COMMUNITY OUTREACH COORDINATOR.
>> AS I UNDERSTAND, HE'S INTERESTED IN BEING APPOINTED A
SUPERVISOR FOR DISTRICT FOUR. AND OF COURSE IT'S MARJAN
FLOWER WHO WAS TRY TO THREE TIMES TO TRY TO OUT SUPERVISOR
KALI CHAN. >> BUT SHE'S STILL TRYING
AND YOU KNOW, WE NEVER STOP RIGHT?
>> WE JUST KEEP GOING. >> THE OPPORTUNITIES THERE
WE'RE INVINCIBLE. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
>> AND THEY KNOW YOU'RE BEING GROOMED FOR SOMETHING ELSE.
>> MAYBE I CAN SUPPORT YOU WITH THAT.
>> MERRILEE UNPLUGGED. SORRY.
I'M SORRY. NOT I DON'T MEAN TO ENDORSE
THAT OR ENDORSE YOU. >> WE ALREADY HAVE FILIPINO
SOME FILIPINOS BREAKING BARRIERS.
JESSICA GALARZA WAS ELECTED LAST YEAR FIRST FILIPINO TO THE
CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY. >> AS MANY OF YOU KNOW, THE
CHIEF JUSTICE OF SUPREME COURT TINY CONTROLS SACAGAWEA SERVED
FOR 13 YEARS. >> WE HAVE MANY OTHERS WHO ARE
RUNNING FOR OFFICE. >> IN 2001 THERE WERE VERY FEW
OR HARDLY ANYONE RUNNING FOR OFFICE OR IN PUBLIC SERVICE.
>> WE'RE NOT ASKING FOR FAVORS TO START JUST STATING A FACT.
EFFECTIVE GOVERNANCE REQUIRES DIVERSE VOICES IN THE ROOMS
WHERE DECISIONS ARE MADE. >> I THINK YOU WILL BENEFIT
FROM A FILIPINO OR FILIPINO WOMAN VOICE.
AND WE ARE LEADERS AND WE'D LIKE TO BE PART THE DECISION
TABLE OTHERWISE WE WILL JUST GO GET A SEAT.
>> SO OUR WORK SPANS TWO CRITICAL AREAS WE HAVE
INTRAPRENEUR SHIP TRAINING. WE WORK WITH GIRLS WHO ARE ONE
TO INFLUENCE THE WORLD. >> WE HAVE THE FILIPINOS
AGAINST VIOLENCE OR WE HAVE RACED OVER ALMOST 500,000 TO
BENEFIT DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AGENCIES.
>> WE HAVE WE WERE FUNDED BY GOOGLE FOR AN AIR TRAINING
AND AT&T HAS US ALSO FOR FINANCIAL LITERACY.
>> SO WHAT WE'RE SAYING IS SAN FRANCISCO BET ON US 25 YEARS
AGO TODAY WE'RE A GLOBAL NETWORK OF WOMEN PROVING THAT
WHAT'S POSSIBLE WHEN WOMEN LEAD.
>> WE'RE HERE TO THANK THE BOARD FOR RECOGNIZING OUR WORK
AND TO REMIND YOU THAT FILIPINO AND FILIPINO COMMUNITY IS READY
TO SERVE AT EVERY LEVEL IN THIS CITY'S GOVERNMENT.
>> AND YES, YOU'RE WELCOME TO COME AND ATTEND THE MONOLOGUES
IS GOING TO BE THE LAST SHOW WE'RE GOING TO HAVE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THEY DON'T HATE US ANYMORE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. HERE WE COULD DO REBOOT OF
MYSELF. OKAY.
I GOT POWER. YOU KNOW I'M POWER.
WHAT I SAID IS WE YOU SAY POWER.
I SAID OUR POWER. >> THANK YOU.
I'M GOING TO HUMBLY SUGGEST THERE MIGHT BE OPPORTUNITIES
FOR PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE WHOLE GROUP OUTSIDE TO REHEARSE.
OKAY. OKAY.
SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU, EVERYONE.
>> THANK YOU. OH, YEAH, YEAH.
YOU YOU GOT LIKE YEAH, YEAH YEAH, I DO.
SEE YOU. YES.
YES. SO SO DORSEY, YOU DON'T WANT
THIS PHOTO ON THE ROAD IN THE ROTUNDA OUTSIDE?
>> YEAH. YEAH.
ALL RIGHT. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN, WE'RE GOING
TO GIVE FOLKS A MINUTE TO COME IN.
>> SO YOU'RE GOING TO BE AN X THAT'S A TOUGH ACT TO FOLLOW
BUT GOOD AND THEN IT STOPS. >> SO IT MIGHT BE SOMETHING
WE'LL SEE. LET'S GIVE IT A TRY HERE.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
YOU INDIVIDUALLY OKAY. >> OKAY.
AND I BELIEVE WE ARE MAKING A LITTLE BIT OF AN ACCOMMODATION
FOR SUPERVISOR CHEN'S HONOREE. >> SO DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR
CHEN. >> YEAH.
THANKS. >> THANK YOU.
PERSON MANAGEMENT MAY I INVITE JOSE?
>> I NEED TO THE PODIUM TEACHER OH, COLLEAGUE TODAY I AM VERY
PROUD TO HONOR SO SANDY FOOTHILL A SECOND GENERATION
FILIPINO-AMERICAN AND A TEACHER AT LONGFELLOW ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL. >> HI.
>> I WAS BORN AND RAISED IN DISTRICT 11 SO SANDY
ATTENDED LONGFELLOW HIMSELF AND AFTER STARTING HIS TEACHING
JOURNEY IN 2009, HIS PASSION AND HEART FOR THE COMMUNITY LED
HIM BACK THERE TO LONGFELLOW. >> HE TEACHES IN THE FILIPINO
ALL LANGUAGE AND ELEMENTARY SCHOOL PROGRAM.
WHAT A TEAM OF DEDICATED TEACHERS MOST WHO ALSO GREW UP
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD. THE PROGRAM TEACHES ETHICS
STUDIES WITH CULTURAL COMPETENCE AND ITS FOCUS ON
BUILDING COMMUNITY FAMILIES ARE ENGAGED AND OFTEN GATHER FOR
CULTURAL CELEBRATIONS. AS A PROUD FILIPINO AMERICAN
TEACHER SO SANDY EMPOWERS YOU TO LEARN ABOUT THEIR CULTURE
AND HISTORY FOSTERING AS SCENES OF COMMUNITY IN STUDENTS EVEN
FOR THOSE WHO ARE NOT FILIPINO .
>> WITH HIS LEADERSHIP, STUDENTS EXPLORE THE VIBRANT
SEA OF FILIPINO CULTURE BUILDING AFFINITY FOR THE
LANGUAGE AND DEVELOP DEEPER UNDERSTANDINGS OF THE DIVERSE
HERITAGE THAT ARE VITAL TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CULTURAL VIBRANCY
AS AN ADVOCATE AND A LEADER DOSANI FIGHTS FOR PROGRAMS LIKE
FILIPINO WORLD SO THIS IS LIKE W L.
>> S W OUR IS TO HELP STUDENTS SECURE SAFE SPACE TO CONNECT
WITH THEIR HERITAGE ROOTS AND UNDERSTAND THE LEGACY OF
RESILIENT RESISTANCE TO FIT THE FILIPINO W L.
>> S PROGRAM AT LONGFELLOW. IT'S ONE OF THE FEW OF ITS KIND
WE ARE LUCKY TO HAVE ETHNIC STUDIES CURRICULUM FOCUSED ON
FILIPINO CULTURE, LANGUAGE AND HISTORY IN OUR ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL IN DISTRICT 11 THAT IMPACT LED BY EDUCATORS LIKE
DOSANI GO FAR BEYOND LEARNING IN CLASSROOM STORY YOUR
DEDICATION, COMPASSION AND HALF HOUR LEADERSHIP TEACHER JORHAT
TEACHER SENIOR PHOTO YOU CONTINUE TO CONNECT STUDENTS TO
THEIR HERITAGE EACH TO THEIR COMMUNITY FOSTERING A MORE
RESILIENT, INCLUSIVE AND THRIVING FUTURE FOR ALL
IMMIGRANT STUDENTS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU TESS. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS I HAPPILY I COULD
DO JUST AS RIGHT I HAPPILY ACCEPT THE AWARD IN BEHALF OF
MY FOR LONGFELLOW ELEMENTARY AND THE FILIPINO WORLD LANGUAGE
ELEMENTARY SCHOOLS PROGRAM. I DON'T KNOW HOW I COULD TOP
THE PREVIOUS PRESIDENT BUT I AS A AS A FIRST GRADE TEACHER, A
PARENT AND A GRADUATE OF LONGFELLOW, I CARRY MY LOVE FOR
THE FILIPINO WORLD LANGUAGE ELEMENTARY SCHOOLS PROGRAM
LITERALLY AROUND MY NECK. >> I WE ARE HUMBLED BY THIS
RECOGNITION COMING FROM LONGFELLOW.
OFTEN THOSE THAT DO VISIT US THEY THEY REFER TO US AS A
HIDDEN GEM LOCATED IN THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN FRANCISCO
BORDERING DALY CITY. I CAN SEE HOW WE ARE OFTEN
OVERLOOKED AND SEEN AS HIDDEN BUT TODAY WE ARE NOT.
>> WE ARE SEEN. WE ARE HEARD AND YES WE WE WE
ARE WE ARE HERE. LONGFELLOW IS ONE OF AS YOU
MIGHT SAY WHILE LONGFELLOW IS ONE OF TWO PUBLIC ELEMENTARY
SCHOOLS IN THE ENTIRE NATION THAT TEACHES FILIPINO, THE
OTHER IS OUR SISTER SCHOOL BETSY CARMICHAEL APC AND IN THE
SOMA AND SO THAT IS SHOWS THAT OUR SORRY OF GETTING THROWN OFF
THAT IN ITSELF SHOWS THAT OUR VALUE GOAL WAS BEYOND THE
BORDERS OF SAN FRANCISCO KNOWING THAT FILIPINOS ARE ONE
OF THE LARGEST ASIAN ETHNIC GROUPS IN THE ENTIRE COUNTRY
AND WE ARE ONLY ONE OF TWO THAT SAYS A LOT.
WITH THAT SAID, WE ARE WE ARE GOING INTO OUR 14TH YEAR
TEACHING IN THIS PROGRAM SERVING OUR COMMUNITY AND JUST
LIKE OUR FILIPINO AMERICAN HISTORY, IT'S A BEAUTIFUL
STRUGGLE. SO WITH THAT SAID, I ALSO WANT
TO PAY RESPECT TO THOSE THAT HAVE GONE BEFORE US.
THOSE ARE ALLOWED TO STAND ON THEIR SHOULDERS TO BE FOR US TO
BE WHERE WE ARE RIGHT NOW. SO I WANT TO APPRECIATE THOSE
LIKE MISS SAIGON REST IN LOVE MISS LINDSEY A GAL MY
COLLEAGUES JEFFREY LAPID IN KINDERGARTEN MISS MY MY
MENTOR MISS SERAFIN HELEN SERAFINO, A GUARD IN SECOND
GRADE AS THEY SAY VALADE MISS JOANNA MADRAZO.
MISS CHERYL CARRILLO ABAD FOR ALL OF THE PASSION AND LOVE
THAT THEY PUT INTO THEIR CRAFT EVERY SINGLE DAY AND EVERY
SINGLE YEAR AT LONGFELLOW, I ALSO WANT TO PAY RESPECT TO PAP
PINOY, PINAY EDUCATIONAL PARTNERSHIPS FCC FILIPINO
COMMUNITY CENTER AND OUR COMMUNITY FOR CONSTANTLY
SUPPORTING US AND JUST IN OUR EXISTENCE AND MOST IMPORTANTLY
I WANT TO SHOW OUR APPRECIATION TO OUR FAMILIES RIGHT HERE AS
YOU CAN SEE ARE OUR FAMILIES FOR TRUSTING US TEACHERS
AND CHOOSING US TO TEACH OUR CHILDREN, TEACH THEIR CHILDREN
FILIPINO LANGUAGE, FILIPINO AMERICAN HISTORY AND JUST
ALLOWING US TO TEACH THEM TO APPRECIATE AND LOVE THEMSELVES
AND OTHERS. OUR STORY IS A FILIPINO
FILIPINO AMERICAN STORY AND IT'S ALSO AN AMERICAN STORY
. SO I JUST WANT TO I APPRECIATE
YOU FOR ALLOWING US TO BE HEARD TO BE SEEN.
>> WELL, THAT SAID MARAMING MORANIS MARAMING SALAMAT THANK
YOU JUST CONNECT WITH EVERYONE .
GO OUTSIDE. LET'S GO OUTSIDE FOR PICTURE.
>> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MADAM, IF I COULD HAVE MR. DERRICK BROWN COME TO THE
PODIUM PLEASE. COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR
TO PRESENT THIS SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO A MAN WHOSE
LIFE'S WORK EMBODIES LEADERSHIP ,SERVICE AND AN UNWAVERING
COMMITMENT TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
DERRICK BROWN STORY IS ONE DEEPLY ROOTED IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT SHAPED HIM THE FILLMORE AND WESTERN
ADDITION AND ALL ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO PLUS THE VALUES THAT
CONTINUE TO GUIDE HIM. EQUITY, INTEGRITY AND COMMUNITY
OVER THE COURSE OF MORE THAN TWO DECADES, DERRICK HAS BUILT
A REMARKABLE LEGACY OF CIVIC LEADERSHIP AND MISSION DRIVEN
SERVICE THAT BRIDGES THE WORLDS OF PUBLIC POLICY HIGHER
EDUCATION, PHILANTHROPY AND COMMUNITY ACTION.
TODAY AS THE CHIEF ADVANCEMENT AND STRATEGIC PARTNERSHIPS
OFFICER AT THE YMCA OF GREATER SAN FRANCISCO, DERRICK LEADS
WITH BOTH VISION AND HEART. HIS WORK HAS STRENGTHENED THE
Y'S ABILITY TO SERVE FAMILIES AND YOUTH ACROSS THE BAY AREA
AND DRIVE TRANSFORM TRANSFORMATIONAL CHANGE THROUGH
AUTHENTIC PARTNERSHIP. BEFORE JOINING THE Y DERRICK'S
LEADERSHIP AT THE LEO T MCCARTHY CENTER AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO INSPIRED COUNTLESS STUDENTS TO
PURSUE LIVES COMMITTED TO JUSTICE AND THE COMMON GOOD.
>> HIS TIME AS A TRUSTED ADVISOR TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
MAYORS AND LEE LENDING BREE AND MARC FERRO SPEAKS TO THE
DEPTH OF HIS EXPERTISE AND THE RESPECT HE COMMANDS ACROSS OUR
CITY. WHETHER SERVING AT CITY HALL,
THE UNIVERSITY OR WITHIN THE NONPROFIT SECTOR, DERRICK HAS
ALWAYS BROUGHT PEOPLE TOGETHER TURNING SHARED PURPOSE INTO
MEANINGFUL PROGRESS. DERRICK IS NOT ONLY A SKILLED
STRATEGIST AND FUNDRAISER BUT ALSO A BRIDGE BUILDER.
HE IS SOMEONE WHO BRINGS INSTITUTIONS, COMMUNITIES
AND INDIVIDUALS INTO ALIGNMENT TOWARDS THE GREATER GOOD.
>> HE HAS LED MULTIMILLION DOLLAR CAMPAIGNS.
SERVED ON NUMEROUS CIVIC AND NONPROFIT BOARDS.
AND MENTOR THE NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERS WITH HUMILITY
AND GRACE. THROUGH IT ALL, HIS GUIDING
PRINCIPLE HAS REMAINED THE SAME TO UPLIFT OTHERS, BUILD
COMMUNITY POWER AND CREATE SYSTEMS THAT TRULY SERVE
EVERYONE. >> DERRICK YOUR LEADERSHIP AS
ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S OWN CONTINUES TO REMIND US THAT
CHANGE DOESN'T COME FROM ANY ONE PERSON OR ORGANIZATION.
IT COMES FROM THE COLLECTIVE FROM PEOPLE WORKING SIDE BY
SIDE WITH SHARED VISION AND LOVE FOR THEIR COMMUNITY.
MY OFFICE AND SO MANY OTHERS APPRECIATE ALL THAT YOU
CONTINUE TO DO. WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR STEADFAST
SERVICE, YOUR WISDOM AND YOUR ENDURING COMMITMENT TO EQUITY
AND INCLUSION. CONGRATULATIONS DERRICK
AND THANK YOU FOR CONTINUING TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO STRONGER,
FAIRER AND MORE CONNECTED FOR ALL OF US.
AND LIKE YOU ALWAYS SAY, KEEP CROSSING.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. THE REASON THIS IS MADE I KNOW
WE'RE WEIGHING UP THIS ROUND. >> HOLD ON.
OH, LOOK, I DON'T HAVE TOO MANY FRIENDS.
OH, OKAY. >> SUPERVISE MELGAR.
HEY, I THINK YOU. DEREK, YOU DEFINITELY HAVE FANS
. AND I COUNT MYSELF AS ONE OF
YOUR FANS AS WELL. I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE OF
WORKING WITH YOU NOT JUST HERE ON THE BOARD BUT BEFORE THAT
WHEN I WAS AT JAMESTOWN AND YOU ALWAYS BRING EXCELLENCE
AND COMMUNITY TO EVERYTHING YOU DO AND I'VE ALWAYS APPRECIATED
THAT. ONE OF THE THINGS I JUST WANT
TO POINT OUT SINCE I KNEW YOU YOU KNOW AND FROM THE YOUTH
DEVELOPMENT WORLD THAT YOU'RE GOING BACK TO NOW AGAIN IS HOW
MANY OPPORTUNITIES YOU HAVE OPENED UP FOR YOUNG PEOPLE FOR
LIKE MANY, MANY GENERATIONS OF YOUNG PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
YOU HAVE OPENED DOORS. YOU HAVE PROVIDED OPPORTUNITY.
YES. YOU HAVE INTRODUCED MENTORED
YOU KNOW, FUNDRAISE FOR AND YOU HAVE CHANGED THE WORLD, MY
FRIEND, BECAUSE YOU HAVE PROVIDED THAT FOR OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE. SO I AM PROFOUNDLY GRATEFUL.
I CAN'T WAIT TO SEE WHAT YOU DO WITH THIS NEW ROLE BUT I KNOW
THAT WHATEVER YOU DO YOU WILL KEEP BRINGING EXCELLENCE
AND COMMUNITY AND I'M SO GRATEFUL FOR YOU.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHAN.
THANK YOU. >> PRESENT MANDO MAN TRULY I
WANT TO SAY DEREK WHEN YOU JUST HAVE SUCH LIKE PRESENCE
AND ALSO YOU'RE ALWAYS JUST SO KIND.
EVERYWHERE YOU GO AND IT DOESN'T MATTER WHO YOU MEET
AND WHO YOU GREET. AND I KNOW THAT BECAUSE WHEN
YOU JOIN THE YMCA AND YOU CAME TO THE RICHMOND YMCA FOR A FUN
RUN, THE STAFF WERE JUST SO EXCITED TO SEE YOU THERE
AND THAT YOU MADE EVERYBODY FEEL SO WELCOME.
YOU BROUGHT THAT ENERGY AND LIKE REALLY EARLY IN THE
MORNING. >> YEAH WELL THE FUN RUN
AND YOU YOU JUST BROUGHT THAT. BUT I THINK THAT ANOTHER THING
THAT PROBABLY A LOT OF PEOPLE DIDN'T QUITE SEE IS THE CHANGE
THAT YOU DIDN'T JUST MAKE IN THE COMMUNITY BUT THE PEOPLE
THAT YOU SERVE WITH. WE RECENTLY WENT TO THE
UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO NEW PRESIDENT INAUGURATION AND ALL
THESE CONFLICT ARE IMPORTANT. PEOPLE WERE IN THEIR ROLE
AND VERY SERIOUS. BUT THE MOMENT THAT DEREK
STEPPED INTO THAT CHURCH AND THEY SAW HIM THEIR EYES
JUST BRIGHTEN UP AND THEY'RE MAKING EMOTION AND GESTURE
AND THEY CAN'T WAIT TO HUG HIM. >> AND THAT'S HOW YOU KNOW,
THAT'S NOT JUST ON THE SURFACE. >> YOU YOU GO DEEP AS A HUMAN
AND AS A PERSON OF LIKE JUST INTEGRITY.
AND THAT I'M JUST SO APPRECIATIVE OF YOU.
I'M JUST SO GRATEFUL THAT YOU CONSISTENTLY WORKING IN THE
COMMUNITY YOU DIDN'T JUST LEAVE TO GO FOR A BETTER JOB.
>> YOU SOMEHOW JUST STICK TO IT AND BE ABLE TO STICK TO THAT
COMMITMENT SERVING OUR COMMUNITY AND THE MOST
VULNERABLE AND I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON YOU ARE A
BRIDGE BUILDER AND I AGREE WITH SO AS A MALL GUARD THAT YOU
REALLY DO CHANGE A WORLD AND ONE YOUNG PERSON AT A TIME
AND THAT WE ARE FOR THAT. >> WE'RE SO GRATEFUL TO YOU.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU SO. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN DEREK I AM SO APPRECIATIVE THAT WE GOT TO
BE COLLEAGUES AT THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND I STRONGLY SUSPECT THAT THE REASON YOU WANTED TO WORK FOR
BILL SCOTT WAS THE SAME REASON I DID AND THAT WAS THE CHANCE
TO DO SOME WORK ON POLICE REFORM.
FULFILLING THE PROMISE OF PRESIDENT OBAMA'S TASK FORCE ON
21ST CENTURY POLICING AND THE WORK THAT BILL SCOTT DID AS
WHAT WOULD END UP BEING THE ONLY CITY IN THE NATION THAT
WHEN DONALD TRUMP PULLED THE PLUG ON POLICE REFORM THERE WAS
ONLY ONE CITY THAT WENT BACK TO THE DRAWING BOARD, STARTED FROM
SCRATCH AND DID THE WHOLE THING OVER AGAIN AND THAT WAS SAN
FRANCISCO. YOU WERE A PART OF THAT FOR THE
COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT DIVISION WHICH WAS A FOUNDING ELEMENT OF
POLICE REFORM. IT WAS AN HONOR OF MY CAREER TO
BE A COLLEAGUE OF YOURS EVEN IF IT WAS ONLY FOR 6 OR 7 MONTHS.
BUT JUST REALLY PROUD OF YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU, MAN. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> DEREK I JUST WANTED TO
ACKNOWLEDGE AGAIN NOT JUST THE ORGANIZATIONS YOU SERVE FOR BUT
A THEME THAT I FEEL I'VE SEEN ACROSS YOUR CAREER HAS BEEN
THAT YOU GIVE BACK TO THE ORGANIZATIONS THAT YOU WERE A
PART OF THE LEADERSHIP OF AND YOU KEEP GIVING BACK.
>> I KNOW YOU SPENT SOME TIME GROWING UP IN THE TENDERLOIN
THAT MEANS A LOT TO THE COMMUNITY AS WELL.
YOU WORK FOR THE BOYS AND GIRLS CLUB WHICH IS STILL THRIVING AT
DON FISHER CLUBHOUSE, PROBABLY ONE OF THE BEST BOYS AND GIRLS
CLUB IN THE IN THE CITY BUT ALSO IN CHORAL FELLOWSHIPS.
>> MY CHIEF OF STAFF, JESSICA KNOWS YOU WELL FROM WORKING
TOGETHER AND YOU WERE A CHORUS FELLOW AND YOU'VE CONTINUED TO
SERVE AND MENTOR THE NEXT GENERATIONS AFTER AND I THINK
THAT'S WHAT IT TAKES A LOT OF US AND IT'S A GOOD REMINDER TO
ALL OF US THAT WE HAVE TO KEEP GIVING BACK AND THANK YOU FOR
YOUR EXAMPLE AND CONTRIBUTING BACK TO THE FILLMORE AUSTIN
AND MISSION TENDERLOIN IN SAN FRANCISCO.
SO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO AND YOU SAID YOU MAKE US ALL
LOOK BAD. >> I THOUGHT ABOUT IT.
TRY NOT TO WORK TOGETHER. MAYBE MAKE IT HAPPEN.
THANKS FOR EVERYTHING YOU SAYING.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> DEREK BROWN I WANT TO EXTEND
ALSO MY JUST CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU.
YOU DESERVE THIS. THIS IS YOU HAVE CONTRIBUTED SO
MUCH TO THE CITY AND IT'S GREAT TO SEE YOU GETTING HONORED
IN THIS WAY. AND NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH TRULY FOR EXACTLY WHEN I WAS MAKING NOISE
MAKING NOISE. >> AND PRESIDENT MADAM MAYOR,
THANK YOU SO MUCH. I KNOW I'LL SEE YOU TOMORROW AS
WELL. OUR MISSION BRANCH ON THE TOUR
SO LOOKING FORWARD TO THAT. SUPERVISOR JAMAL WALTON.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING ME.
THANK YOU FOR SEEING ME. TO EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THESE
AMAZING BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. IT'S BEEN AMAZING WORKING
ALONGSIDE EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU.
>> I CAN GO DOWN THE LIST. I DON'T KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW. I KNOW I'M PRESSED FOR TIME
AND I KNOW EVERYBODY'S BEEN WAITING FOR A WHILE SO I WANT
TO GO ON AND ON AND ON. BUT I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO
WORK WITH EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU CONNECT WITH YOU WHETHER
IT'S, YOU KNOW, STRATEGY CONVERSATION AND HANGING OUT AT
EVENTS. DANNY REMEMBER EATING SOME CRAB
ADDA IN CHINATOWN REMEMBER A COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO HOLDING IT
DOWN? BUT THIS IS WHAT I DO.
I'M ALL ABOUT THE COMMUNITY, ALL ABOUT THE PEOPLE THAT WE
SERVE. LIKE I SAY, YOU GUYS DONE A
GREAT JOB TALKING ABOUT ME SO I REALLY HAVE TO SAY TOO MUCH SO
I'LL KEEP MY COMMENTS BRIEF BUT I HAVE TO GIVE A HUGE SHOUT OUT
SHOUT OUT TO THE FLOWER THAT POLLINATE TO MY GARDEN MY
BEAUTIFUL WIFE TRACY HOUSTON. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU DAVID. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR PUTTING UP WITH
ME. I MEAN AS YOU GUYS KNOW I'M
ALWAYS OUT AND ABOUT DOING MY THING.
BUT THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING ME TO CONTINUE TO HAVE AN IMPACT
TO THE COMMUNITY AND THE CITY THAT WE'VE BOTH BEEN BORN
AND RAISED IN THE WEST EDITION SO TO BE HERE SO I APPRECIATE
THAT. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
YOU YOU KNOW IF YOUR MOM TAKES ON A CASE IL SEE YOU.
>> OH, AND THEN ALSO LIKE YOU TOUCHED ON BEFORE, YOU KNOW
I'VE BEEN AT A LOT OF DIFFERENT ORGANIZATIONS ALL WITHIN THE
CITY EVEN STARTING OFF THE BOYS AND GIRLS CLUB WORKING WITH
CITY AND COUNTY YOU KNOW ALSO YUSEF AND CURRENTLY HERE AT THE
YMCA OF GREATER SAN FRANCISCO. SO HUGE SHOUT OUT TO OUR CEO
JAMIE BRUNI MILES IN A HOUSE. >> SEE HIM OVER HERE?
OH, THERE YOU GO. THERE WE GO.
AND WE HAVE YOU KNOW, OUR LEADERSHIP TEAM, OUR EXECUTIVE
DIRECTORS, YOU KNOW, BOARD MEMBERS, A LOT OF FOLKS THAT
SHOWED UP AND SHOWED OUT. WE ALSO HAVE FOLKS FROM THE
BOYS AND GIRLS CLUB AS WELL HERE REPRESENTING USF GO DANCE
IN OUR HOUSE. WE GOT OUR OTHER FOLKS IN THE
HOUSE ALSO MY CHORAL FAMILY THEY'RE HERE AS WELL.
OUR BOARD MEMBERS AND COLLEAGUES WE HAVE OUR
SPEED WAS REPRESENTED. THERE IS WE'RE GOING TO HOUSE
AS WELL JEAN PAUL YEP CAME BY HAD TO SLIP OUT PAUL MIYAMOTO
AS WELL WITH THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT THE LIST GOES ON
AND ON WITH THE LEADERSHIP THAT THAT'S COMING OUT AND YOU KNOW
LIKE I SAY WE ALL HAVE COME UP BUT I REMEMBER ALL OF US, YOU
KNOW, IN THE TRENCHES ON THE GRIND MAKING IT HAPPEN FOR SO
FOR ME TO BE IN THE POSITION I AM TODAY IT'S INCREDIBLE.
BUT I STAND ON THE SHOULDER OF GIANTS LIKE IN PARTICULAR I
HAVE ONE OF MY MENTORS HAS BEEN A MENTOR TO ME SINCE I WAS SIX
YEARS OLD. >> NATE FORD WHEN I WAS AT THE
BOYS AND GIRLS CLUB GET UP AT NIGHT DURING THE AFTERNOON KNOW
EXACTLY AND THEN FAST FORWARD YOU KNOW 20 YEARS LATER WHEN I
WAS INSPIRED TO GO BACK TO SCHOOL WITH THE YOUTH THAT I
SERVED AT THE BOYS AND GIRLS CLUB, I TAUGHT THIS THESE
PROGRAMS FOR TEENAGERS AND I CREATED A COLLEGE PREP PROGRAM
AND DAY ONE OF THAT PROGRAM I TRY TO ENCOURAGE THE TEENAGERS
THAT I WORK WITH TO GO TO COLLEGE BUT THEY LOOKED AT ME
AND SAID WAIT A MINUTE, WHY SHOULD I GO TO SCHOOL IF YOU
NEVER BEEN IN THOSE 11 WORDS CHANGED MY LIFE FOR THE BEST.
I ENROLLED IN THE CITY COLLEGE THE NEXT DAY AND CONTINUE TO
CRUSH IT THERE, MAKE IT HAPPEN .
BUT WHEN I GOT THERE YOU KNOW I WAS EVENTUALLY ELECTED TO THE
BOARD OF TRUSTEES. THAT'S WHERE I GOT A TASTE OF
POLITICS AND STUDENT TRUSTEE. BUT THEN THERE WAS ONE
INDIVIDUAL THAT SAW MY POTENTIAL BEFORE I SAW IT
AND HE'S IN HERE RIGHT NOW AND GOING BACK 20 YEARS AGO I
DON'T KNOW WHAT HE SAW IN ME. I WAS JUST YOUNG CAN RUN AROUND
SWEATS, JEANS, T SHIRTS NOT REALLY THINKING ABOUT THE
FUTURE BUT DR. MARK ROBINSON SAW MY POTENTIAL AND DOC I WANT
TO SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALL THE TO BE BACK THERE HIDING
OVER THERE BUT SERIOUSLY HE HE SAW SOMETHING IN ME AND AGAIN
EVERYONE HERE TODAY I MEAN ALL OF MY COLLEAGUES ALL OF MY
FRIENDS, ALL OF MY FAMILY THAT ARE HERE TODAY.
HUGE SHOUT OUT TO MY DAUGHTERS DARIAN AND LAYLA AS WELL.
AND AGAIN, I JUST WANT TO CONTINUE TO LEAD BY EXAMPLE,
CONTINUE TO DO THE AMAZING WORK THAT WE'RE DOING AND CONTINUE
TO WORK SHOULDER WITH EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU.
SO AGAIN TO ALL OF MY LOVED ONES, MY FAMILY, MY COLLEAGUES
,ALL OF THE BOARDS THAT I'VE BEEN ON I MEAN EVERYTHING THAT
I'VE BEEN DOING SERIOUSLY I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU
AND I WANT TO START I GUESS I WANT TO END THE SAME WAY I
STARTED THIS THIS BRIEF CHAT BY JUST SAYING THANK YOU, THANK
YOU AGAIN AGAIN SUPERVISOR WATSON THANK YOU AGAIN
AND AGAIN. THIS WAS SOMETHING ABOUT TO GET
OFF TO BUT I'M GETTING COMFORTABLE NOW SO I'M FEELING
IT SO IF THIS IS THIS THIS IS SO MUCH OF AN HONOR SO I'VE
BEEN ON THE OTHER SIDE FOR YEARS AND YEARS AND YEARS
WATCHING OTHERS GET RECOGNIZED NOT ONCE SAID WHAT ABOUT ME?
>> WHAT ABOUT ME? BUT NO I DON'T DO THIS FOR THE
RECOGNITION BUT I MEAN I KNOW IT'S FUNNY BUT I DON'T I DON'T
OH BUT FOR SOMEONE TO SEE THE WORK THAT I WAS DOING AND THEN
ALL OF YOU SUPERVISORS SAY YES, ABSOLUTELY.
WE HAVE TO APPRECIATE DEREK WE HAVE TO RECOGNIZE HIM AGAIN.
I'M GOING TO TAKE MY SEAT BUT PLEASE, PLEASE DON'T FORGET TO
KEEP IT. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
APPRECIATE WHERE WE ARE, HOW I LOOK I'M GOOD.
I GOT TO THANK YOU GUYS SO MUCH.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> KNOW I DIDN'T KNOW WERE LIKE
YOU. OH, OKAY.
>> DISTRICT ONE SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
IT LOOKS LIKE I'M KEITH SPECKS STEPPING ON OUR COLLEAGUES TOES
ALL DAY TODAY. THAT'S NOW I'M STEPPING ON
YOURS BECAUSE MY NEXT YEAH THANKS HONOREE IS ACTUALLY A
DISTRICT EIGHT RESIDENTS APPARENTLY FOR CRYING OUT LOUD
I KNOW RIGHT? SO COLLEAGUES PLEASE JOIN ME
AND WELCOME KIKI LOPEZ ALSO KNOWN AS MISS KIKI CRUNCH.
>> I HAVE BEEN SO INSPIRED AND ENCOURAGED BY KIKI'S
PRESENCE AND ORGANIZING WORK AT EVERY COMMUNITY EVENTS
AND ESPECIALLY THIS YEAR THAT EVEN THOUGH SHE'S NOT THE
DISTRICT ONE RESIDENTS I KNEW THAT WE HAVE TO RECOGNIZE KIKI
AT TODAY'S FILIPINO HERITAGE MONTH SPECIAL ACCOMMODATE ATION
FROM OUR CHINATOWN PRIDE PARADE AND THE TRANS ASIAN PACIFIC
ISLANDER STRONG RALLY AND MARCH TO GAY ASIAN PACIFIC ALLIANCE'S
RUNWAY AND THIS YEAR'S FIRST VERY VERY FIRST SOMA FILIPINA
PRIDE EVENT. >> KIKI'S PRESENCE IS FELT
EVERYWHERE KIKI MIGRATED FROM PHILIPPINES TO SAN FRANCISCO
IN PURSUIT OF A LIFE THAT SHE DESERVES AS TRANSGENDER WOMAN
SHE ARRIVED WITHOUT A SAFETY NET AND RELY ON SAN FRANCISCO
SANCTUARY CITY STATUS FOR CRITICAL IMMIGRANTS RIGHTS
AND COMMUNITY HEALTH SERVICES THROUGH THE AIDS FOUNDATION'S
WELLNESS CENTER. STROUT THERE SHE MET WITH A
CLINICIAN AND AN HIV HEALTH NAVIGATOR WHO PROVIDED HER WITH
CRITICAL MEDICATION LINK HER TO A LONG TERM CARE CHECK LAPSE,
SIGN HER UP FOR HEALTH INSURANCE THROUGH MEDI-CAL
AND PROVIDED REFERRALS TO GENDER AFFIRMING CARE
AND IMMIGRATION SYSTEM THROUGH THE LGBT ASYLUM PROJECT.
>> TODAY KIKI IS SO AMAZING, SO AMAZING A COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT
COORDINATOR AT THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH
CENTER PAYING FOR THE CARE AND SERVICES TO NEW IMMIGRANTS
PEOPLE LIVING WITH HIV AND THOSE IN TRANSITION WHO ARE
SEEKING SAFETY AND BELONGING IN OUR COMMUNITY.
AS MANY OF YOU ALREADY KNOW, KIKI IS ALSO A DRAG MOTHER
IN PERIL CROWN PRINCESS DAPHNE DORMAN, TRANS ARTIST AWARDEE
AND A COMMUNITY GRANDMA SHOW FOR SAN FRANCISCO PRIDE NOMINEE
NO MATTER WHICH HEELS SHE'S WEARING THAT DAY SHE WEARS THEM
WITH JOY AND PRIDE TO LIFT UP OTHERS AROUND HER.
THIS IS WHY I AM SO HONORED TO BE RECOGNIZING HER TODAY HER
PURE EXISTENCE AS HER AUTHENTIC SELF.
JOY AND STORY AS AN IMMIGRANT, A TRANSGENDER WOMAN, A PERSON
LIVING WITH HIV IS THE PERFECT EMBODIMENT OF RESISTANCE
AND THE POWER THAT WE ALL NEED TO COUNTER TO OPPRESSIVE
POLICIES COMING DOWN FROM THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION RIGHT NOW.
AND SO FOR THAT I'M SO GRATEFUL THAT SHE GRACE US WITH HER
PRESENCE TODAY IN THE CHAMBER AND I WILL JUST SAY SUPERVISOR
JAN THANK YOU FOR HONORING MIXED KIKI CRUNCH WHO IS SUCH A
PHENOMENAL HUMAN BEING AND DOES SO MUCH FOR THE COMMUNITY
AND SOMETIMES IF I'M LUCKY IS WILLING TO BE IN A SELFIE WITH
ME. >> CONGRATULATIONS.
THIS IS WELL-DESERVED. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR CHEN AND OH OKAY AND THANK YOU
SO MUCH BOARD PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR MANDELL MAN AND I
ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE REST OF THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
SHOUT OUT TO SUPERVISOR FIELDER I'M ADMIRING YOU FROM AFAR.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALL THE WORK THAT YOU DO.
I ALSO WANTED TO RECOGNIZE A FEW FOLKS WHO ARE WITH ME RIGHT
NOW. I KNOW THEY HAVE WORK BUT THEY
CHOSE TO BE WITH ME IN SOLIDARITY AND SUPPORT ME
IN THIS MOMENT OF COMMENDATION FROM THE SUPERVISORS LANCE
THOMAS, CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER OF SAN FRANCISCO COMPANY HEALTH
CENTERS HERE KATE FRANZIA MANAGING DIRECTOR OF ASSOCIATES
IS ALSO HERE. CHRISTINA GREENHOUSE VIGIL
DIRECTOR OF WORKFORCE TRANSFORMATION IS HERE THEATER
ROSALIA AQUINO CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER AND OF COURSE MY
DEAREST FRIEND HE'S ALSO MY WORK SUPERVISOR.
>> HE'S THE ONE WHO PROMOTED ME THIS YEAR ROLLIN MENDOZA,
ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR OF PREVENTION SERVICES I ALSO HAVE
MY IMPERIAL COURT OF SAN FRANCISCO FAMILY HERE WITH ME
MY DRAG MOTHER AND ALSO THE CURRENT REIGNING EMPRESS OF SAN
FRANCISCO OR EMPRESS AFRICA AMERICA.
>> JOHN BRETT OF THE IMPERIAL COURT OF SAN FRANCISCO WAS ALSO
HERE AND I WOULD LIKE TO GIVE A HUGE SHOUT OUT TO TO MY OTHER
COLLEAGUES RUPERT AND CHRIS WHO ARE ALSO HERE AND MY MY BOY AM
I ALLOWED TO SAY MY MY BOY SISTERS DEEDEE MARIE HOLLIDAY
DRAG RACE PHILIPPINES SEASON TWO AND AND MY ETERNAL SISTER
NATASHA AND OF COURSE MY LOVING LOVING PARTNER HE IS A TALL,
HANDSOME MAN. >> MY PARTNER WYATT, THANK YOU
SO MUCH FOR COMING. >> MY NAME IS KIKI LOPEZ ALSO
KNOWN AS MIXED KIKI CRUNCH. YOU CAN CATCH ME ON THE BART
STATION MUNI STATION DOING DRAG OR SOMETIMES IN OTHER SIDEWALKS
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. I AM A PROUD IMMIGRANT TRANS
WOMAN OF COLOR LIVING WITH HIV. I AM NOT ASHAMED OF MY STATUS.
I SERVE AS ONE OF THE PROGRAM MANAGERS AT THE SAN FRANCISCO
COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER AS IMPERIAL CROWN PRINCESS FOR THE
DIAMOND COURT OF DIVERSITY, EXCELLENCE AND JOY OF THE
IMPERIAL COURT OF SAN FRANCISCO AND AS THE SOCIAL CHAIR OF
GLOBE TISSUE PLUS ASIAN AND PACIFIC ALLIANCE ALSO KNOWN
AS KAPPA. >> WHAT A PRIVILEGE HERE TO
STAND BEFORE ALL OF YOU TODAY AND WHENEVER I SPEAK I MAKE IT
INTENTIONAL. I MAKE SURE THAT I CARRY THE
VOICES OF TRANSGENDER LUMINARIES WHO CAME BEFORE ME,
THOSE WHO PAVED THE WAY SO PEOPLE LIKE ME COULD LIVE LOVE
AND FIGHT A LITTLE LOUDER ESPECIALLY IN THIS CURRENT
POLITICAL CLIMATE THAT WE HAVE. >> AND I MAKE SURE TO ECHO THE
VOICES OF MY TRANS SIBLINGS WHO CANNOT SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES
THEIR STRENGTH AND RESILIENCE GUIDE ME EVERY SINGLE DAY BEING
HERE INSIDE THIS HISTORIC CHAMBERS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS MORE THAN JUST A MILESTONE FOR ME
THIS VERY SPACE HOLDS THE SPIRIT OF AND POWER OF TRANS
WOMEN WHO HAVE STOOD BEFORE ME LIKE NIKKIE CALLED MY TITA IDA
ONE OF MY MENTORS CECILIA CHANG HONEY MAHOGANY AND MANY MORE
WHO SPEAK THE TRUTH TO POWER AT A TIME WHEN BEING INVISIBLE WAS
AN ACT OF RESISTANCE. IT ALSO CARRIES THE POWERFUL
LEGACY OF ASIAN AND PACIFIC ISLANDER HIV ADVOCATES
AND COMMUNITY LEADERS LIKE LANCE TOMA AND VINCE CHRYSOSTOM
OF SAN FRANCISCO AIDS WHO FOUGHT FOR CARE AND JUSTICE
DURING THE HEIGHT OF THE HIV EPIDEMIC A TIME WHEN OUR
COMMUNITIES WERE PUSHED TO THE MARGINS BUT NEVER GAVE UP THE
FIGHT FOR SURVIVAL. >> THIS CHAMBERS ALSO HOLD LOTS
OF FILIPINO WOMEN EARLIER AS YOU'VE SEEN HOLD THE VOICES OF
FILIPINO LEADERS AND CULTURAL BEARERS WHO ORGANIZE AND FOUGHT
AGAINST DISPLACEMENT, PROTECTING THE SOUL OF SOMA
PILIPINAS THE FILIPINO CULTURAL HERITAGE DISTRICT, SOME PARTS
OF THE TENDERLOIN AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE FILIPINO
FAMILIES BUILT THEIR LIVES. THEIR FIGHT FOR HOUSING,
CULTURAL PRESERVATION AND DIGNITY HAS KEPT OUR
STORIES ALIVE IN THIS CITY. >> THE COURAGE OF THIS
COMMUNITY LEADERS AND ADVOCATES MAY THIS CHAMBER IS HISTORIC.
THEIR VOICES OPEN THE DOORS THAT ALLOWED PEOPLE LIKE ME TO
STAND HERE TODAY NOT JUST TO SURVIVE BUT TO LEAD AND TO BE
CELEBRATED. >> IT BELONGS TO THE AND TRANS
COMMUNITY TO FOLKS LIVING WITH HIV THE FILIPINO AND ASIAN
AMERICAN PACIFIC ISLANDER IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES AND TO
EVERY PERSON WHO HAS EVER HAD TO FIGHT TO BE SEEN AND TO BE
HEARD. I STAND ON THE SHOULDERS OF
COUNTLESS ELDERS, COMMUNITY LEADERS AND CHOSEN FAMILY WHO
MADE THIS MOMENT POSSIBLE. SO I WANTED TO SPECIALLY THANK
SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHEN FOR THIS COMMENDATION.
>> IT IS AN HONOR TO WORK ALONGSIDE WITH YOU IN LAUNCHING
PROJECTS THAT UPLIFT THE AAPI AND LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITIES
IN THE CITY. AND SO EVERYONE WHO CONTINUES
TO STAND WITH US ESPECIALLY AT A TIME WHEN TRANS RIGHTS
AND LIVES ARE UNDER ATTACK AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL.
THANK YOU. I SAW THAT VIDEO LAST WEEK OF
MARY LOU RHEE ADDRESSING THE CITY AND I SAW SUPERVISOR MATT
DORSEY BEHIND SUPERVISOR MOTHER WAS ALSO THERE AND OF COURSE
BOARD PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN THANK YOU.
BECAUSE IN MOMENTS LIKE THIS PERFORMATIVE ACTIVISM HAS NO
PLACE SO YOUR GENUINE ACTIONS OF SOLIDARITY AND ALLYSHIP
MATTER DEEPLY. I ALSO WANT TO HONOR MY WORK
FAMILY AT SAN FRANCISCO HUMAN HEALTH CENTER, MY COLLEAGUES
AND MENTORS WHO SAW MY POTENTIAL BELIEVE IN ME
AND GAVE ME A SPACE TO GROW AND LEAD WITH PURPOSE
AND HEART. THANK YOU TO ROLLIN, TITA, IDA,
LANCE AND CHRISTINA FOR ALWAYS HEARING MY WHILE CRAZY SUPER
GAY GLITTER FILLED IDEAS AND MAKING THEM REAL BEYOND MY
PROFESSIONAL WORK. MY HEART IS DEEPLY ROOTED
IN THE COMMUNITY. I AM ONE OF THE CO-FOUNDERS OF
TOPICS STRONG AND TRANS API STRONG ALONGSIDE FOLKS FROM THE
OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER INITIATIVES INCLUDED INCLUDING
CHERRY AND FOLKS FROM TRANSGENDER MARCH ORGANIZATION
LANA AND NICO A MOVEMENT TO PROTECT AND UPLIFT AND TRANS
AAPI COMMUNITIES. >> I AM ALSO A CO-FOUNDER OF AS
MENTIONED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN EARLIER THE FIRST EVER SOMA
PILIPINAS PRIDE TOGETHER WITH TITA IDA ROLON CHRISTINA
AND RAQUEL OF SOMA PILIPINAS ORGANIZATION AND NEEL A
FILIPINO AMERICAN CINEMA BECAUSE THE REPRESENTATION OF
FILIPINO ACTS JOY, RESILIENCE AND CULTURAL POWER MATTERS.
BOTH EVENTS WERE LAUNCHED THIS YEAR AND WILL CONTINUE ANNUALLY
BECAUSE OUR STORIES AND CELEBRATIONS DESERVE
PERMANENCE. AND BECAUSE I HAVE COMMUNITY
LEADERS HERE AND PUBLIC OFFICIALS LISTENING TO MY
SPEECH, I KNOW THAT THIS FOLKS WOULD SUPPORT THIS COMMUNITY
EVENTS. >> CAN I GET AN IMAGE UP
IN HERE AND THAT'S RIGHT. >> AND AS ONE OF THE MATRIARCHS
OF AN ALL FILIPINO DRAG TROUPE, I HAVE WITNESSED THE POWER OF
ART PERFORMANCE AND DRAG TO BUILD SOLIDARITY AND TELL HER
STORIES ON HER OWN TERMS. >> TOMORROW WE WILL BE
WITNESSING THE NEW DRAG LAUREATE AND THAT COULD EXCITE
ME MORE. >> OUR EXISTENCE IS A
REVOLUTION. THIS COMMENDATION IS A REMINDER
THAT REPRESENTATION IS NOT A PRIVILEGE.
IT IS A RIGHT. AND WHEN THE WORLD REFUSES TO
GIVE US A SEAT AT THE TABLE WE WILL BUILD OUR OWN TABLE WITH
GLITTER AND RAINBOW COLORS. >> AND SO EVERY YOUNG
AND TRANS PERSON WATCHING THIS MOMENT YOU HAVE A FAMILY HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO, A COMMUNITY THAT WILL HELP YOU NOT JUST
SURVIVE BUT THRIVE. SO THANK YOU FOR SEEING ME
AND THANK YOU FOR SEEING US THE REST OF THE TRANSGENDER
COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH
. >> I NOTE THAT WE HAVE BEEN
JOINED IN THE CHAMBER BY FORMER SUPERVISOR AMOS AMOS BROWN.
SO GOOD TO HAVE YOU HERE, SIR. AND NEXT UP THAT'S AN APPLAUSE
LINE AND. >> AND NEXT UP FROM DISTRICT
TWO, SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> THANK YOU.
WE OKAY REALLY? >> OKAY.
I THINK WE I THINK WE'RE GOING TO MAKE IT.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN WOULD JANET ALVARADO PLEASE
COME FORWARD? >> YEAH.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M HONORED TO COMMEND JANET ALVARADO,
FOUNDER AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE ALVARADO PROJECT
IN CELEBRATION OF FILIPINO-AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH
HERE IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
JANET, AS MANY OF YOU KNOW, HAS DEDICATED HER LIFE TO
PRESERVING AND SHARING FILIPINO-AMERICAN HERITAGE
THROUGH THE POWERFUL PHOTOGRAPHER FATHER RICARDO
ALVARADO WHOSE WORK DOCUMENTS FILIPINO COMMUNITY LIFE
AND POST WORLD WAR TWO SAN FRANCISCO.
RICARDO IMMIGRATED TO THE UNITED STATES AT AGE 14, LATER
SERVING AS A U.S. ARMY MEDIC DURING THE WAR IN THE PRESIDIO
LOCATED IN DISTRICT TWO BEFORE SETTLING IN THE CITY.
HIS PHOTOGRAPHS CAPTURE EVERYDAY FILIPINO LIFE FROM
CELEBRATIONS AND GATHERINGS TO THE QUIET MOMENTS THAT DEFINED
AN AREA OF AN ERA. EXCUSE ME OF RESILIENCE
AND COMMUNITY AFTER HIS PASSING IN 1976, JANET DISCOVERED HIS
ARCHIVE OF NEARLY 3000 IMAGES AND SAW A CULTURAL TREASURE.
IN 1998 SHE FOUNDED THE ALVARADO PROJECT, A NONPROFIT
DEDICATED TO PRESERVING HIS LEGACY AND PROMOTING
MULTICULTURAL UNDERSTANDING THROUGH ART STORYTELLING
AND EDUCATION. THE PROJECT'S EXHIBITIONS
INCLUDING THROUGH MY FATHER'S EYES WHICH DEBUTED AT THE
SMITHSONIAN IN 2002 AND OF COURSE MORE RECENT ONES IN THE
PRESIDIO ARE NOW PART OF STANFORD UNIVERSITY'S LIBRARY'S
PERMANENT COLLECTION. AND MOST EXCITINGLY THERE IS AN
EXHIBITION CURRENTLY FEATURED AT SFO TERMINAL THREE ON
THROUGH MAY 10TH 2026. >> SO BUY YOUR AIRLINE TICKETS
AND GO SEE IT. TOGETHER THESE WORKS CONTINUE
TO INSPIRE COMMUNITY AND DEEPEN AWARENESS OF FILIPINO AMERICAN
HISTORY ACROSS GENERATIONS. JANET'S LEADERSHIP EXEMPLIFIES
THE SPIRIT OF FILIPINO AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH WHEN A FAMILY
LEGACY AND COMMUNITY. THROUGH HER WORK SHE ENSURES
THAT THE STORIES AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF FILIPINO
AMERICANS REMAIN VISIBLE AND CELEBRATED IN OUR CITY'S
CULTURAL FABRIC. >> BUT ON A MORE PERSONAL NOTE
. JANET AND I MET IN MAY NOT
IN AN EVENT FOR THE ALVARADO PROJECT BUT AN EVENT WHERE THE
ALVARADO PROJECT AND SPECIFICALLY JANET HERSELF
WERE RAISING AWARENESS FOR CANCER THROUGH LIGHTS OF HOPE.
IT'S THAT KIND OF ENGAGEMENT IN THE COMMUNITY NOT JUST
SEEING THIS IS MY THING I WILL CARRY IT FORWARD BUT SAYING
THIS IS MY COMMUNITY AND I WILL HELP CARRY ALL OF US FORWARD
TOGETHER. IT'S THAT ATTITUDE, THAT SPIRIT
AND HER TENACITY THAT INSPIRES ME AS WELL.
>> SO TODAY WE HONOR JANET ALVARADO FOR YOUR VISION, YOUR
DEDICATION AND YOUR TIRELESS ADVOCACY IN UPLIFTING THE
FILIPINO AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND UPLIFTING ALL OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR ALL OF OUR FUTURE GENERATIONS.
JANET, CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU AND TO YOUR FAMILY AND THE MIKE
IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO 20 EIGHT YEARS OF DOING THIS WORK.
>> FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU VERY, VERY MUCH FOR RECOGNIZING
THE LATTER PART OF THE CHAPTER OF THIS JOURNEY FOR ME
PERSONALLY. >> THANK YOU.
THAT MEANS THE WORLD SO AS EVERYBODY HAD PREFACED, THIS IS
A MAGNET EFFICIENT SPACE TO THE END.
AND IT'S A GREAT DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO TO BE RECOGNIZED FOR
FILIPINO-AMERICAN HERITAGE AS HISTORY MONTH.
AND I'M REALLY PROUD TO TELL YOU THAT I AM THE DAUGHTER OF
AN IMMIGRANT, AN EARLY IMMIGRANT AND LIKE A LOT OF MY
NEWER CONTEMPORARIES SO I AM FROM THIS CITY IN THIS COUNTY I
GREW UP HERE. I WAS BORN AND RAISED HERE.
AND THE REASON THAT THE PRESIDIO WAS ESPECIALLY
PERSONAL AND A GREAT PLACE FOR ME WAS BECAUSE THAT WAS MY
FATHER'S IMPROVED EMPLOYMENT PLACE OF WORK FOR HIS LIFE
AFTER WORLD WAR TWO AS A CIVILIAN COOK AND STANFORD DOES
CARRY THE COLLECTION NOW. AND BEFORE I GO A STEP FURTHER
I HAVE STAGE FOUR METASTATIC CANCER AND IT RECURRED IN 2023.
SO I WOULD BE REMISS IF I DID NOT STAND UP HERE AMONG YOU ALL
TO SAY THANK YOU ON BEHALF OF MY FAMILY.
THIS PROJECT HAS BEEN AN INCREDIBLE LIFELINE TO SO MANY
WONDERFUL THINGS AND YET I'D LIKE TO JUST STAND BEHIND ME
AND YOU KNOW I HAVE A MENTOR NOW BECAUSE I'M OLD NOW.
I'M AN ELDER AND I'M LISTENING TO ALL THESE YOUNGER PEOPLE
COME UP HERE TO THE MIC AND WHEN I WAS BORN AND RAISED
THERE WERE PROBABLY TWO OTHER LITTLE FILIPINO PEOPLE IN MY
CLASSROOM AT MONROE ELEMENTARY SCHOOL IN 1965.
SO IN MY EYES THERE WE WERE THE GLOBAL FILIPINOS.
I HAVE MY FRIENDS HERE I'D LIKE TO ASK THEM TO PLEASE STAND WHO
HAVE BEEN CONTINUING TO CARRY THIS LEGACY FORWARD FOR MYSELF
AND MY DAD AND THIS BEAUTIFUL CITY WITH SO MANY DISTRICTS HE
CAPTURED HERE. I THINK I WORKED WITH YOU
IN 2022. RIGHT?
GAVE YOU OKAY. SO AGAIN, I HOPE TO CONTINUE TO
DO THESE KINDS OF PROJECTS WHICHEVER IT BRIDGES MY
PERSONAL ADVOCACY FOR SOME OF THE CANCER THINGS I'M VERY
INVOLVED WITH OF A VISION TO DO SOMETHING WITH THE PRESIDIO
DISTRICT. I'M FROM DISTRICT NINE.
I HAVEN'T YET MET MY SUPERVISOR YET BUT HEY I'LL PAY YOU A
VISIT SOON AND I HOPE TO TALK WITH YOU A MORE OXFORD STREET F
Y I AND I. I JUST STOPPED BY YOUR OFFICE
SO I'D LIKE TO ASK PEOPLE THAT ARE INVOLVED WITH MY PROJECT TO
PLEASE STAND UP OR JUST WAVE BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW HOW MUCH
LONGER I HAVE TO CONTINUE THIS BEAUTIFUL LEGACY PROJECT THIS
IS THERE ARE EIGHT PHOTOGRAPHS HANGING AT TERMINAL TWO AND I
BROUGHT EXTRA COPIES FOR EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU.
AND JUST TO GIVE YOU A VISUAL POINT OF REFERENCE, THIS IS
PROBABLY THE IMAGE I GREW UP LEARNING ABOUT IN ASIAN STUDIES
IN THE EARLY 90S. >> THIS FARM WORKERS RIGHT HERE
TO DO LABOR. MY FATHER WAS NOT CUT OUT FOR
THAT WORK AND I AGAIN I'M JUST TAKING TIME TODAY BECAUSE I'M
HAVING A GOOD WEEK I'M STILL IN ACTIVE TREATMENT.
I HAVE MY MAKEUP DONE BECAUSE YOU KNOW THAT BEAUTIFUL GIRL
THAT JUST TALKED BEFORE ME? WELL WHAT CAN I SAY?
>> OH, I WANTED TO SHOW MY BEST FOOT FORWARD TO HONOR MY
ANCESTORS WHO HAVE BEEN COMING TO SAN FRANCISCO WHO LANDED
HERE IN THE 19 TENS. THERE WERE HOUSE BOYS ON
WASHINGTON JONES SO I WAS BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
MY PARENTS LIVED ON BAKER AND PINE WHERE I WAS CONCEIVED.
I'LL BE BURIED AT ST DOMINIC'S CHURCH.
I DECIDED I WAS BAPTIZED AT ALL HOLLOWS.
>> I WENT TO THE EXCELSIOR AND THEN WE FORMALLY RESIDE.
NOW I DO BY MYSELF ON OXFORD STREET DISTRICT NINE SO I
ENCOURAGE EVERYBODY TO TAKE A COPY OF THIS.
>> THIS IS WHAT MY DAD LOOKED LIKE BACK WHEN AND HIS LIFE WAS
CUT SHORT ALSO BY LEUKEMIA. >> SO MY VISION IS THAT
HOPEFULLY THE PROJECT WILL CONTINUE TO THRIVE.
THESE IMPORTANT DOCUMENTS THEIR 3000 GLASS PLATE IMAGES OF
BLACKS FILIPINO PUERTO RICANS, PEOPLE LIVING PARTYING.
IT'S A VERY BEAUTIFUL COLLECTION AND I'M NOT JUST
SAYING THAT BECAUSE HE'S MY DAD BECAUSE I'VE HAD PEOPLE HELPING
ME FOR THE LAST 30 YEARS AND THEY'VE ALL GONE FORWARD.
SO PEOPLE LIKE VICTOR ROSARIO I WAS STILL HEALTHY.
20 THAT'S MIC STAND UP IN THE LAST TIME I WAS HERE WAS FOR
FILIPINO-AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH.
I TOOK AN ENTOURAGE OF 30 PEOPLE BACK TO LAHTI FOR
ANOTHER IMPORTANT TIE INTO THE PROCEDURE WHICH WAS THE WORLD
WAR TWO LIBERATION AND THAT WAS IN OCTOBER AND THEN I BECAME
ILL AND ONCE I GOT PAST MY FIRST ROUND OF TREATMENT I WENT
ON TO DO A SHOW FOR THE BAYVIEW AND THAT ALMOST KILLED ME
BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW WHAT I WAS THINKING.
AND THEN WE DID THE STANFORD SHOW AND IT'S ONLY BEEN THREE
SHORT YEARS. SO AGAIN I'M HERE TODAY BECAUSE
I WANTED TO TAKE THE OPPORTUNITY TO SAY THANK YOU
REALLY THANK YOU AND I HOPE THE CANCER DOESN'T COME BACK.
BUT THAT'S OKAY IF IT DOES BECAUSE I'M HERE RIGHT NOW
AND I WANT TO AGAIN JUST THANK ESTELLA.
SHE'S BEEN IN THE TRENCHES TEACHING FOR DECADES AND AND WE
DON'T GET OVERLOOKED PEOPLE DON'T FORGET ME BECAUSE THE
CITY AND COUNTY HAS THIS SITTING UP IN ALL ITS GLORY AT
STANFORD UNIVERSITY SPECIAL COLLECTIONS LIBRARY.
MY DREAM IS FOR THIS CITY TO BE CONNECTED AND BUILD MORE
PARTNERSHIPS WITH THE DISTRICTS .
I'M NOT A TEACHER. I'M NOT ACADEMIC.
I'M A CREATIVE PERSON AND I LOVE DOING THESE PROJECTS
BECAUSE THE POWER OF THIS PROJECT IS IN THE NARRATIVE,
IN THE STORIES I DON'T HAVE ANY AGENDA EXCEPT TO AGAIN
HEARTFELT HEARTFELT THANK YOU TO EACH OF YOU FOR AND THAT'S
IT. >> THANK YOU
. >> DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY
HONOR TO RECOGNIZE SHERRY YOUNG.
>> CAN SHERRY COME TO THE PODIUM?
>> SHERRY IS AN EXTRAORDINARY ARTIST VISIONARY LEADER
AND TIRELESS ADVOCATE WHOSE WORK HAS TRANSFORMED THE
CULTURAL LANDSCAPE OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE PAST 30
YEARS. >> SHERRY IS THE FOUNDER
AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN SHAKESPEARE
COMPANY, WHICH SHE ESTABLISHED IN 1994 TO PROVIDE ACTORS OF
COLOR WITH THE OPPORTUNITY TO PERFORM CLASSICAL WORKS AND TO
REINTERPRET THEM IN WAYS THAT RESONATE WITH DIVERSE
AUDIENCES. >> A GRADUATE OF THE AMERICAN
CONSERVATORY THEATER'S MFA PROGRAM SHERRY WAS INSPIRED TO
CREATE A SPACE WHERE BLACK ARTISTS COULD THRIVE A STAGE
WHERE STORIES COULD REFLECT THE RICHNESS AND COMPLEXITY
AND BEAUTY OF OUR COMMUNITIES. >> OVER THE PAST THREE DECADES
SHERRY HAS DIRECTED MORE THAN 16 PRODUCTIONS DEVELOP
SIGNATURE PROGRAMING INCLUDING THE BELOVED AND ANNUAL HOLIDAY
TRADITION OF CINDERELLA AND HAS GROWN THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
SHAKESPEARE COMPANY INTO A VIBRANT HUB FOR ARTISTIC
EXPRESSION, EDUCATION AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.
UNDER HER LEADERSHIP, THE COMPANY'S SERVES OVER 7500
PATRONS ANNUALLY AND HAS EXPANDED ITS REACH THROUGH
YOUTH PROGRAMS, SCHOOL TOURS AND INNOVATIVE
REINTERPRETATIONS OF CLASSICS LIKE JULIUS CAESAR AND A
MIDSUMMER'S NIGHT'S DREAM EACH INFUSED WITH THE RHYTHMS OF
HUMOR AND HEART OF BLACK CULTURE.
>> SHERRY'S LEADERSHIP EXTENDS BEYOND THE STAGE.
SHE HAS SERVED AS A COMMISSIONER FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION UNDER MAYOR GAVIN NEWSOM
AND CONTINUES TO SPEAK NATIONALLY ABOUT THEATER EQUITY
AND CULTURAL REPRESENTATION. >> HER WORK HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED
BY THE NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS SEVEN BY SEVEN BAY
AREA AND SHE RECEIVED THE SILVER JEFFERSON AWARD FOR
COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT. >> PERHAPS HER MOST PROFOUND
IMPACT IS THE ONE SHE HAS HAD ON GENERATIONS OF YOUNG PEOPLE
AND IN LONG STANDING COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO SEE THEMSELVES
REFLECTED IN THE STORIES SHE BRINGS TO LIFE.
>> AS BARBARA WILSON PUT IT, SHERRY IS AMAZING.
SHE IS AN OUTSTANDING ASSET TO OUR COMMUNITY AND THE FILLMORE
AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO MANY, MANY YEARS WITH HER.
>> THIS MONTH MARKS 30 YEARS SINCE SHERRY FOUNDED THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN SHIRT SHAKESPEARE COMPANY.
FOR THREE DECADES SHE HAS SHOWN US THAT THEATER CAN BE BOLD,
BRILLIANT AND TRANSFORMATIVE. >> SHE HAS BUILT A HOME FOR
CREATIVITY A PLATFORM FOR BLACK EXCELLENCE AND A LEGACY THAT
WILL CONTINUE TO INSPIRE ARTISTS AND AUDIENCES FOR
GENERATIONS TO COME. SHERRY, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
YOUR ARTISTRY AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AND YOUR COMMITMENT
TO MAKING THEATER A SPACE WHERE EVERYONE BELONGS.
>> THROUGH YOUR WORK YOU TELL THE STORY OF OUR COMMUNITY, OF
OUR CITY, ITS CULTURE AND THE POWER OF CREATIVITY
AND COMMUNITY. THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO
AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS AND IF I COULD JUST ALSO EXTEND MY
CONGRATULATE. IT IS WONDERFUL TO SEE YOU.
I GOT TO KNOW YOU A LITTLE BIT. KNOCKING ON DOORS FOR KAMALA
IN NEVADA IN NEVADA. BUT IT'S THIS IS SO WELL
DESERVED. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
FOR FOR DOING THIS HONOR. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD CAN I ASK MY STAFF TO COME AROUND THOSE FAR
LEFT? KEVIN JAZEERA YOU GUYS SHOULD
COME DOWN AND UM. >> ALEX BECAUSE THIS IS NOT MY
STORY. >> THIS IS REALLY SORRY.
OH, SARAH. TARA YOU COME UP HERE TOO.
>> THIS IS ABOUT THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SUPPORTED ME AT A TIME
WHERE I HAD NO MONEY. I DIDN'T KNOW WHAT I WAS DOING.
I STILL SOMETIMES DON'T KNOW WHAT I'M DOING.
>> BUT THAT'S WHAT THEATER DOES.
THEATER GETS YOU ACTIVATED. >> YOU DREAM ABOUT THINGS.
>> YOU HAVE PEOPLE SUPPORTED AND YOU'RE MY HOPE.
>> SO I STAND BEFORE YOU TODAY NOT JUST AS A FOUNDER BUT AS A
WITNESS TO THE EXTRAORDINARY JOURNEY.
>> SORRY. >> I DON'T KNOW WHY I'M SO
EMOTIONAL. I APOLOGIZE.
NO, NO, NO. >> I DON'T APOLOGIZE.
I DON'T APOLOGIZE. BUT I GUESS THIS MEANS A LOT
MORE THAN I THOUGHT I WOULD JUST LIKE OH OH RECOMMENDATION.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> BUT THIS IS ABOUT THE TALENT
AND RESILIENCE I HAVE SUSTAINED US FOR 30 YEARS.
THIS MILESTONE BELONGS TO THESE HEROES THAT BUILT THIS COMPANY
WITH THEIR HEARTS, HANDS AND HOPE AND THESE PEOPLE WHO
ARE IN THE GALLERY. >> BARBARA I MEAN I CAN'T NAME
ENOUGH OF YOU GUYS. DENISE BRIAN EVEN REVERENT AMOS
BROWN YOU KNOW, I WAS WITH THIRD BAPTIST WHEN I WAS A KID
SO YOU KNOW SO IT MEANS SO MUCH MORE.
>> AND CLARA WHO'S NOT STANDING UP AND GWYNN METCALF YEAH, I'M
CALLING YOU OUT SO AND WE HAD STEADFAST SUPPORTERS WHO GAVE
US SIGNIFICANT DONATIONS WHEN WE DIDN'T KNOW HOW TO ASK FOR
HELP AND THEY ARE THE QUIET FORCE BEHIND OUR CURTAIN RISING
TO OUR ARTISTS TO I SAT DOWN AND MET WITH OVER THE YEARS
AND I SAID OVER COFFEE ONE DAY THAT I DON'T EVEN REMEMBER BUT
THEY DO. RICO ANDERSON WHO WAS IN A
MUHAMMAD ALI MOVIE AS MOHAMMED'S FATHER CAME INTO
TOWN TO CELEBRATE OUR 30TH AND HE SAID I REMEMBER WHEN YOU
AND I TALKED IN A COFFEE SHOP AND YOU HAVE THIS IDEA I DON'T
REMEMBER IT BUT I BELIEVE IT BECAUSE ANY IDEAS THAT COME
IN MY HEAD TENDS TO COME OUT OF MY MOUTH AND MY STAFF WOULD
KNOW THAT BECAUSE THEY'VE DONE A LOT OF CRAZY THINGS FOR MY
IDEAS. >> DAVID MOORE DESIGNER KEVIN
MYRICK. CHICO PURDUM AND GLORY BONNIE
STINGLEY, VICTORIA EVANS, KERRVILLE, PETER TEMPLE
AND COLMAN DOMINGO WAS WITH US BEFORE HE BECAME COLMAN DOMINGO
. >> THEY GAVE US THEIR GIFTS
WHEN WE HAD SO LITTLE TO OFFER AND THEY MADE MAGIC ANY WAY
POSSIBLE. I WAS PAYING OUR ACTORS $200
FOR THE WHOLE REHEARSAL AND PROJECT.
NOW THEY'RE GETTING PAID A WHOLE LOT MORE.
>> BUT THIS IS WHAT IS DREAMING OF AN INSTITUTION LIKE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN SHAKESPEARE. WE'VE HAD ANGELS THAT LOANED US
COSTUMES, REHEARSAL SPACE AND BELIEF.
SAN FRANCISCO. SHAKESPEARE, CALIFORNIA.
SHAKESPEARE. >> MILLS COLLEGE.
YUSEF MARIA MC VARIOUS. THEY GAVE US ROOM TO DREAM.
>> OUR PREDECESSORS FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE LONDON BREED THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN ART AND CULTURE CENTER WHO USED TO
BE THE WESTERN EDITION CULTURAL CENTER.
>> WHEN I MET MANNY YOU COULD TELL FROM CIVIC JOY FUND HE
HELPED US WITH OUR 30TH ANNIVERSARY.
>> GAVIN NEWSOM THE ARTS COMMISSION GRANTS FOR THE ARTS
EVEN MAYOR DANIEL LOWRIE WHO DOESN'T KNOW WHO I AM BUT HE'S
BEEN VERY SIGNIFI CANT IN HELPING US THRIVE IN THE
ARTS. >> I MENTIONED MY STAFF SOMEHOW
TO GO AND TEACH A CLASS BUT DEVIN CUNNINGHAM JAMES MERCER.
STEPHAN BEN IF YOU SEE OUR GRAPHICS AT 460 GOLF THAT'S
STEPHAN WHERE IS SHE? >> OH SHE'S OVER HERE.
SHE'S HIDING TO A DAIRY IN CANE A LIMA.
ELI MACINTYRE BENJAMIN ATLANTIS CLAY YOU ARE THE BACKBONE
AND THE BRILLIANCE OF THIS ORGANIZATION AND TO OUR
PARTNERS SUCH AS USF PLAY ON SAN FRANCISCO SHAKESPEARE
BOOKER T COMMUNITY CENTER I MENTIONED BARBARA WILSON I
THINK HAYS VALLEY MERCHANT ASSOCIATION, HAYS VALLEY
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION. ANDREW WITH THE PROMENADE YOU
ALL HAVE HELPED US GROW AND TO OUR BOARD MEMBERS WHO DO NOT
GET PAID ANYTHING AND YET THEIR LEADERSHIP GUIDES US THROUGH
EVERY SEASON WHETHER THERE BE TORRENTIAL DOWNPOURS OR SUNNY
SKIES. I CANNOT THANK ENOUGH PEOPLE
LIKE BERNICE BROWN, WAYNE METCALF, WAYNE KITCHEN,
LYNNETTE LOCKETT. EVERETT.
ALEXANDER MORRIS BREWSTER, WALTER FREEMAN, MOREL AND DAWN
HARRIS. >> THERE IS A WHOLE GROUP OF
PEOPLE THAT HAS MADE THIS ORGANIZATION WHAT IT IS TODAY.
>> BUT I CANNOT END THIS WITHOUT THINKING MY FATHER
WHO'S SITTING IN THE AISLE AT 89 YEARS OLD.
>> HE'S LIKE WHAT IF I DON'T TELL MY AGE?
HE WAS MY MOTHER, BLESS HER HEART HAS PASSED AWAY.
BUT MY FATHER WAS THE ONE THAT CHAMPIONED ME BEHIND THE SCENES
WHEN MY MOTHER WAS AFRAID ABOUT SOMEONE GOING INTO THE ARTS.
THAT'S NOT A STABLE CAREER, YOU KNOW WHO'S GOING TO TRUST YOU
IF YOU HAVE MULTIPLE JOBS? >> WELL, I MEAN I FORESAW THE
GIG ECONOMY YEARS AGO AND BUT MY FATHER WOULD ALWAYS BE
IN THE BACKGROUND SAYING I'M PROUD OF YOU, YOU COULD DO
THIS. YOU'RE LEARNING, YOU'RE
GROWING. >> KEEP ON.
MY SISTERS WHO ENCOURAGED ME WHEN I WAS IN BROKEN TEARS THAT
NOBODY WAS SHOWING UP TO THE SHOWS MY COUSINS, MY UNCLES, MY
AUNTIES, MY UNCLE JUST LEFT. >> HE HAD TO GO GET HIS CAR
BEFORE IT GOT TOWED. >> SO THEY ALL GAVE ME THE
MOMENTUM TO KEEP PUSHING FORWARD.
SO THIS IS A CELEBRATION OF COMMUNITY, OF LEGACY, OF LOVE.
>> THANK YOU. >> ESPECIALLY YOU GUYS AND YOU
GUYS IN THE GALLERY. THANK YOU ALL FOR BELIEVING
IN AFRICAN-AMERICAN SHAKESPEARE COMPANY AND HERE'S TO THE NEXT
30 YEARS AND THEN THE NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERS.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. YES, I KNOW THE LAST ONE YOU
WELL, MADAM CLERK, THAT WAS ALL TOO ENJOYABLE.
>> LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 31. >> OKAY.
>> UH OH. NOW THERE'S MORE PEOPLE IN THE
QUEUE. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN. BACK TO ITEM 31.
FIRST I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR SAUDER AND HIS TEAM
FOR THEIR HARD WORK ON THIS. YOU KNOW, A FEW THINGS ARE
PROMPTING ME TO SPEAK FIRST AT A HIGH LEVEL I BELIEVE WE NEED
TO BECOME A CITY OF YES IN GENERAL THE MORE ONEROUS THE
HURDLES THE HIGHER THE BARS THE HARDER IT IS FOR YOUNG
ENTREPRENEURS, FOR IMMIGRANT ENTREPRENEURS, FOR AN
ENTREPRENEURS WHO ARE FIGHTING TO SCRATCH OUT A LIVING
FIGHTING TO START THEIR CAREERS, WHO DO NOT HAVE A HUGE
BANK ACCOUNT BEHIND THEM IT IS JUST HARDER FOR THEM TO SUCCEED
IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A PLACE FOR PEOPLE TO COME
AND START CAREERS AND START BUSINESSES AND BUILD THE
FUTURE. AND WE NEED TO BE CLEAR EYED
ABOUT THAT. THE NEXT TWO THINGS I WANT TO
MENTION HERE ARE RELATED TO THE NOT ONE BUT THE TWO TIMES THIS
WAS HEARD AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT HAS STOOD OUT TO ME IS OBVIOUSLY
THERE ARE DIFFERENCES OF OPINION HERE NOT ONLY AMONG US
BUT ALSO AMONG SOME OF THE MERCHANTS IN THESE
NEIGHBORHOODS. BUT I WAS PERSONALLY
OVERWHELMED BY THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE AS MY COLLEAGUE FROM
DISTRICT FIVE SAID WHO TOOK TIME AWAY FROM THEIR
STOREFRONTS AWAY FROM THEIR BUSINESSES, AWAY FROM THEIR
LIVELIHOODS TO MAKE THEIR VOICES HEARD IN SUPPORT OF THIS
LEGISLATION THAT WAS VERY, VERY MOVING TO ME.
AND I THINK WE WOULD BE REMISS TO IGNORE THAT.
WHILE ACKNOWLEDGING THAT OBVIOUSLY THERE ARE DIFFERENCES
OF OPINION. BUT THE FINAL THING THAT I WANT
TO MENTION IS AGAIN THERE WERE NOT ONE BUT TWO TIMES THAT THIS
WAS HEARD AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
I DON'T QUITE UNDERSTAND WHY THESE AMENDMENTS WERE NOT PUT
FORTH BEFORE THE LAND USE COMMITTEE, WHY THEY WERE NOT
THE WAY THEY WERE. THEY ARE NOT CONSIDERED TO BE
PUT FORTH. THERE WAS PLENTY OF TIME FOR
THIS TO HAPPEN. WE HAVE PROCESSES.
WE HAVE COMMITTEES. IF I COULD UNDERSTAND IF THEY
WENT FORTH BUT MAYBE WERE REJECTED.
I COULD UNDERSTAND IF THEY HADN'T BEEN CONSIDERED BUT
THERE WAS PLENTY OF TIME FOR THIS AND I SIMPLY DON'T
UNDERSTAND WHY WE'RE WAITING THIS LONG GOING OUTSIDE OF
THIS. THIS IS VERY UNUSUAL AND I
THINK IT SERVES TO BE LESS ABOUT POLICY AT THIS POINT
AND MORE ABOUT OTHER THINGS. SO I WOULD ENCOURAGE US TO
CONTINUE TO ENGAGE IN SUBSTANTIVE POLICY
DISCUSSIONS. BUT AT THIS POINT THIS SEEMS
LESS ABOUT POLICY AND MORE ABOUT OTHER THINGS.
I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING THE AMENDMENTS.
I WILL BE SUPPORTING THE LEGISLATION THAT HAS BEEN
INTRODUCED AND I COMMEND MY MY COLLEAGUE AND DISTRICT THREE
FOR WORKING SO HARD AND FIGHTING FOR HIS
NEIGHBORHOOD DESPITE THE OBJECTIONS OF SOME IN SUPPORT
OF OTHERS. AND I DO KNOW THAT HE WILL
STAND UP FOR FOR ALL OF THOSE INDIVIDUALS REGARDLESS OF WHERE
THEY STAND ON THIS ISSUE. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY, THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN. COLLEAGUES, I INTEND TO SUPPORT
THE PLANNING CODE AMENDMENT AS SUPERVISOR SUTTER WROTE IT WITH
CONSIDERABLE INPUT FROM THE COMMUNITY AND BUSINESSES HE
REPRESENTS. AND I WON'T BE SUPPORTING THE
MOTION TO DIVIDED. THE PROCESS OF AMENDING OUR
PLANNING CODE IS INTENTIONALLY DELIBERATIVE WITH MANY CHECKS
AND BALANCES AND MANY OPPORTUNITIES FOR INPUT.
THIS LEGISLATION WENT THROUGH THAT DELIBERATIVE PROCESS WITH
A PLANNING COMMISSION HEARING, A SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION
HEARING AND TWO LAND USE COMMISSION HEARINGS COMMITTEE
HEARINGS. THERE HAVE BEEN AMPLE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR ENGAGEMENT ON THE LEGISLATION AND ENDED HAS
BEEN REFINED BY THE INCLUSIVE AND COLLABORATIVE PROCESS THAT
HAD BENEFITED FROM GIVEN THAT THIS LEGISLATION WAS INTRODUCED
BACK IN JUNE AND HAS GONE THROUGH A ROBUST DELIBERATIVE
AND PARTICIPATORY PROCESS. I SEE NO RATIONALE TO REOPEN
THE HOOD ON IT NOW AT THE LAST MINUTE.
THE CHANGES SUPERVISOR SAUTER IS PROPOSING ARE SENSIBLE
AND FRANKLY LONG OVERDUE AND I KNOW SUPERVISOR SAUTER WELL
ENOUGH TO HAVE EVERY CONFIDENCE THAT HE IS WELL REPRESENTING
HIS DISTRICT AND LEGISLATING CONSCIENTIOUSLY HONORING THE
NEEDS OF TODAY'S MANY SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS AND RESIDENTS
WHO ARE ANXIOUSLY AWAITING THESE NEEDED REFORMS.
>> THANK YOU. ROSE DORSEY ALL RIGHT, SO WE
HAVE IN FRONT OF US A MOTION. WELL, IT'S NOT EVEN A MOTION
AND IN ANY I THINK ANY MEMBER OF THIS COMMITTEE AND I'M GOING
TO LEAN ON THE CLERK AND HOPE TO READ YOU IN THE I MEAN WE
DON'T NEED A MOTION TO DIVIDE THE FILE AS WE PROPOSE BUT WE
DO NEED A MOTION TO SENATE THAT DIVIDE THE PORTION BACK TO
COMMITTEE AND THAT WAS MY INTENDED MOTION TO SEND IT BACK
TO COMMITTEE OF THE DIVIDE A PORTION BY ALLOW.
>> OKAY SO AND THIS IS PARTLY FOR MY BENEFIT PROBABLY FOR THE
BEST OF MY COLLEAGUES SO UNDERSTAND HOW THIS PLACE
WORKS. AM I RIGHT?
MR. CITY ATTORNEY ANY MEMBER OF THE BOARD CAN DIVIDE A
QUESTION. THE POINT OF THAT IS THAT OR
DIVIDE A FILE. THE POINT OF THAT IS THERE MAY
BE THAT THERE ARE THINGS IN THERE THAT PEOPLE WANT TO
VOTE FOR DON'T WANT TO VOTE FOR.
>> WE'VE DONE THIS IN THE PAST. THAT IS THE THING GENERALLY
THAT IS THE PRIVILEGE OF ANY MEMBER OF THIS BOARD TO TO VOTE
ON STUFF IN FRONT OF US, SEPARATE IT OUT IF WE WANT TO.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSTY
UNDER THE BOARD RULES ANY MEMBER OF THE BOARD CAN REQUEST
TO DIVIDE THE QUESTION WHICH WOULD MEAN THAT THE BOARD WOULD
CONSIDER THE ORIGINAL THE STRIPPED OUT PORTION SEPARATE
FROM THE REST OF THE ORDINANCE IN ORDER FOR THAT TO BE OKAY
BOTH PORTIONS HAVE TO STAND BE ABLE TO STAND ON THEIR OWN
IN THIS CASE DUE TO THE COMPLEXITY OF WHAT SUPERVISOR
CHEN HAS REQUESTED IT'S NOT POSSIBLE FOR ME TO DETERMINE
WHETHER BOTH PARTS CAN STAND ON THEIR OWN AT THIS TIME.
>> IF THE BOARD WANTED TO CONSIDER THIS QUESTION WE COULD
IT COULD CONTINUE THE ITEM TO NEXT WEEK BUT I WOULD SUGGEST
THAT IN ORDER FOR US TO BE CERTAIN THAT THESE ARE TWO
ORDINANCES THAT CAN STAND ON THEIR OWN THAT WE WORK WITH
SUPERVISOR CHAN'S OFFICE OVER THE NEXT WEEK SO THAT SHE CAN
PROPOSE AMENDMENTS TO THIS ORDINANCE TO ACCOMPLISH THE
CHANGES THAT SHE'S TRYING TO MAKE HERE.
>> SO BASED ON THE HEARING FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY, I BELIEVE
THAT WE WOULD NEED I MEAN THE RESOLUTION HAS THE RIGHT TO
VOTE ON THIS AND DIVIDED WHERE IF THEY IF WE CAN AND WE CANNOT
DO THAT TODAY. >> AND SO IF THE DESIRE IS TO
DO THAT AND IF THERE IS A MAJORITY OF THE BOARD THAT
WANTS TO DO THAT, WE WOULD NEED TO CONTINUE THIS A WEEK.
OKAY? >> SUPERVISOR CHAN I MEAN I'M I
DON'T SEE THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE DIVIDER POINT WELL
I MEAN I THINK THAT IF WE WERE TO DO THAT THEN WE ARE
BASICALLY WELL FIRST OF ALL WE DON'T NEED A MOTION AND THE
VOTE TO DIVIDE THE FILE AND THE FACT THAT I ALREADY DIVIDED THE
FILE WITH SPECIFIC PORTION WHAT I'M TRYING TO ACTUALLY DO IS
THAT TO MAKE SURE THE AND THAT THERE'S A THERE'S A VERSION OF
THE FILE AS ORIGINAL COMING OUT OF LAND USE THE DIVIDED PORTION
SPECIFICALLY READ OUT LOUD IT'S DIVIDED FROM THE FILE THAT
WHICH THEN WE CAN VOTE ON AND HOWEVER WAY WE WANT TO VOTE
ON EITHER CONTINUE FOR A WEEK OR SEND IT BACK TO COMMITTEE
THAT SHOULD BE NO DIFFERENCE. WELL WE CAN'T AND I MEAN IF
THIS IS TO LIKE IF THIS TECHNICALLY DOESN'T STAND THEN
IT'S TO THEN DUPLICATE A FILE WHICH AGAIN I CAN DO ON MY OWN
AND THEN WITH THE DUPLICATE A FILE IT'S THEN TO HAVE JUST THE
PORTION OF THE NORTH BEACH AND JACKSON SQUARE TO SEND IT
BACK TO COMMITTEE. LIKE I MEAN IT'S REALLY JUST
DIFFERENT APPROACH TO THE VERY SAME AND BUT LIKE IT SHOULDN'T
BE SO TO DIVIDE SO I GUESS AS THE PRESIDING PERSON ON THIS ON
THIS BOARD I THINK THAT WE CANNOT THIS BODY CANNOT VOTE ON
A PIECE OF THIS LEGISLATION AS DESCRIBED BECAUSE WE'RE BECAUSE
WE ARE NOT SURE WHAT'S IN THERE AND THE CITY ATTORNEY IS NOT
SURE WHAT'S IN THERE. >> SO TO DO THAT IF THAT'S WHAT
THE BODY WANTS TO IF THAT'S WHAT A MAJORITY WANTS TO DO, WE
NEED TO CONTINUE THIS WEEK. IN THAT TIME THE CITY ATTORNEY
CAN VERIFY WHETHER THESE TWO PIECES STAND ON THEIR OWN.
WE CAN DO WHATEVER WE WANT TO IF WE WANT TO DUPLICATE SOME OF
IT SO WE CAN CONTINUE THIS ITEM FOR A WEEK IF WE'RE VOTING
TODAY WE'RE VOTING ON THE UNDIVIDED FILE.
>> SUPERVISOR JAN HOW ABOUT THIS?
LET ME MAKE IT EASIER TO DUPLICATE A FILE AND THEN WE
CAN VOTE ON ONE TO ALLOW IT TO TO ONE SEND IT BACK THEN I WILL
MAKE THE MOTION TO SEND THE DUPLICATE OF FILE ITS ENTIRETY
BACK TO COMMITTEE. THAT WILL BE MY MOTION THEN I
THINK THAT'S MUCH EASIER. OKAY SOUNDS GOOD TO THROUGH THE
PRESIDENT TO SUPERVISOR CHAN JUST VERBALLY SAY YOU'VE
RESCINDED YOUR MOTION TO DUPLICATE THE FILE.
>> THANK YOU. WHILE I CONTINUE TO DIVIDE THE
QUEST DIVIDE THE QUESTIONS I RESENT THAT MY MOTION MY
QUESTION AND SEND THAT DIVIDED PORTION BACK TO COMMITTEE.
I RESCINDED THAT MOTION AND INSTEAD I'M PROPOSING A NEW
MODE WHILE AND AND INSTEAD FIRST I DUPLICATE A FILE
AND THEN I'M MAKING THE MOTION TO SEND THE DUPLICATE A FILE
BACK TO LAND USE COMMITTEE THAT WOULD BE MY MOTION.
>> OKAY. AND SO THAT THAT MOTION HAS
BEEN MADE AND SECONDED SO YEAH RIGHT.
>> SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR WALTON AND I'M GOING TO ASK THE
CLERK AND THE CITY ATTORNEY TO TELL ME ORDER OF OPERATIONS IF
WE VOTE ON THE ORIGINAL FILE FIRST AND THEN WHAT TO DO WITH
THE DUPLICATE YOU WOULD SEND THE DUPLICATE TO COMMITTEE
FIRST TO TAKE THAT MOTION FIRST AND THEN VOTE ON THE ORIGINAL.
>> IF 11 MEMBERS ARE FINE WITH THAT THEN YOU CAN DO THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION AND IF THE TEN MEMBERS ARE FINE WITH THAT
THEN YOU CAN DO THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION JUST TO SEND IT TO
COMMITTEE. >> OKAY?
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD I'M CURIOUS TO GET THE PERSPECTIVE OF THE
ORIGINAL AUTHOR OF THIS LEGISLATION WHO REPRESENTS
DISTRICT THREE AND WHAT HE WOULD PREFER TO DO ON BOTH
ITEMS ON THIS ORDINANCE. THANK YOU.
AND CAN I JUST FOR EVERYONE'S UNDERSTANDING CAN I ASK FOR
YOUR PROPOSAL TO BE READ AGAIN AND COULD I ASK FOR THE CITY
ATTORNEY TO WEIGH IN PLEASE? >> WELL, I THINK AT THIS POINT
THE MOTION TO DO TO DIVIDE THE TWO DIVIDED BY OFFER FILE UP
HAS BEEN RESCINDED. SO WE HAVE AS YOU KNOW, WE HAVE
THE LEGISLATION IN FRONT OF US. THERE'S ALSO DESIRE BY SOME
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TO WORK ON IT TO CONTINUE WORKING ON IT.
>> SO THERE IS GOING TO BE A VOTE TODAY ON TWO THINGS AND I
UNDERSTAND THE ORDER TO BE FIRST WE'RE GOING TO VOTE ON
WHETHER TO SEND A DUPLICATE TO LAND USE COMMITTEE FOR PEOPLE
TO CONTINUE TO WORK ON IT IF THEY WOULD LIKE TO THAT
DUPLICATE WILL SURVIVE AS LONG AS THE ORIGINAL.
>> WELL HOW DOES THAT WHAT HAPPENS TO THAT DUPLICATE SIR
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSTY THE DUPLICATE WILL SURVIVE
UNTIL THE ORIGINAL ORDINANCE BECOMES EFFECTIVE IF THE
DUPLICATE WOULD NEED TO BE AMENDED BEFORE THAT DATE
IN ORDER TO SURVIVE. >> OKAY SO IT GOES TO THE
COMMITTEE FOLKS WANT TO DO SOMETHING WITH IT IN THE
COMMITTEE THEY CAN IF NOT IT GOES AWAY.
THE ORIGINAL FILE WILL ALSO GET VOTED ON HERE TODAY.
SO THOSE ARE THE TWO THINGS THAT ARE GOING TO HAPPEN.
SO WE'RE VOTING ON DUPLICATING THE FILE AND SENDING IT TO THE
THE DUPLICATION HAPPENS BECAUSE ANYBODY WANTS TO DO IT.
THE VOTE IS TO SEND IT TO LAND USE NUMBER ONE AND THE SECOND
VOTE IS THE ORIGINAL FILE TO PASS IT OR NOT PASS OR NOT.
>> OKAY. VERY WELL THANK YOU.
>> NO ALL RIGHT. SO ON THE MOTION TO SEND A
DUPLICATE OF THE FILE TO THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO SEND THE
DUPLICATE TO LAND USE COMMITTEE SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR NO SUPERVISOR SARDAR NO SADR NO
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO.
THERE ARE FIVE EYES AND FIVE NOS WITH SUPERVISORS DORSEY
MAHMOOD MELGAR, SADR AND CHERYL VOTING NO.
>> SO THE MOTION FAILS JUST GO FOR FIVE EYES THE ACTION IS BY
A MAJORITY OF THE BOARD WHICH IS STILL SIX VOTES SO THE
MOTION FAILS. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE ORIGINAL FILE. SO PLEASE JUST FOR THE RECORD
SINCE THE DUPLICATE HAS NOT GONE TO COMMITTEE IT WILL JUST
FALL TO THE FLOOR. >> OKAY.
>> ON ITEM 31 CHAN ARE YOU CHEN CHEN IT'S NOT CHAN SORRY THANK
YOU PRESIDENT MOUNTAIN THANK YOU.
PURSE AMENDMENT I. I WANT TO WEIGH IN FOR THIS
ITEM AS WELL. >> I KNOW THAT SOME ADVISOR
SALTER IT IS WRITTEN BEING IN THE COMMITTEE FOR TWO
HEARING AND AND I HAVE BEEN ENGAGING WITH A LOT OF DISTRICT
THREE MERCHANTS AND AGENTS ASSOCIATION AND COMMUNITY
MEMBER AND ALSO HAVING BEEN HAVING ONGOING CONVERSATION
WITH SOME OF US SOLDERS OFFICE AND MY UNDERSTANDING IS THAT
SUPERVISORS SALTER IS RESPONDING TO VERY SPECIFIC
REQUESTS FROM SMALL SOME OF THE SMALL BUSINESS IN HIS DISTRICT
AND I WANT TO BE SUPPORTIVE OF HIS EFFORTS TO PROBLEM SOLVE
AND TRY NEW APPROACHES. >> I WANT TO ALSO CHAMPION OUR
CITY'S SMALL BUSINESS AND ENSURE THAT THEY CAN THRIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> I AM HEARING THAT IN NORTH
BEACH EXISTING BUSINESSES WANT ACCESS TO TOOLS THAT ENABLE
THEM TO BE SECURE AND I ALSO HEAR THAT THERE ARE NEW
BUSINESS THAT WANT TO BE ABLE TO EXPAND AND I BELIEVE IT IS
CRITICAL THAT WE FIND A BALANCE TOO BETWEEN THESE TWO GOALS.
WHEN THIS LEGISLATION CAME BEFORE THE LAND USE COMMITTEE
AGAIN I HEARD SO MANY DIFFERENT VOICES INCLUDING FEARS
AND CONCERNS FROM SMALL BUSINESS COMMUNITY, THE
STAKEHOLDERS ARE GRAPPLING WITH HOW TO PROTECT THE ECOSYSTEM OF
SMALL BUSINESS TO TO PREVENT AN OVERSATURATION OF SPECIFIC
KINDS OF ESTABLISHMENTS AND MAINTAINING A DIVERSITY OF
USE AND A DIVERSITY OF USES AND SMALL BUSINESS.
>> THEY BELIEVE THAT NORTH BEACH IS SUCCESSFUL.
IT'S A SUCCESSFUL STORY. WAS IT PROTECTING THAT STRING?
IT'S COMING FROM ENABLING THE DIVERSE MOM AND POPS
ENTERPRISES THAT MAKE IT SO SPECIAL.
>> THIS IS WHY IN THE COMMITTEE REPEATEDLY AND I WOULD LIKE TO
SEE DATA THAT ACTUALLY SHOWED HOW THE EXISTING CONTROL ARE
WORKING OR NOT WORKING. I HAVEN'T SEEN MUCH OF THE DATA
THAT COULD HELP ME TO JUSTIFY THE CHANGE THAT ARE BEING
PROPOSED IT IN A WAY THAT IT ACHIEVING A HEALTHY BALANCE
WITHOUT DATA I WOULD REALLY DEFER I WOULD REALLY PREFER TO
SEE SOME OF THE CHANGE TO BE MORE SPECIFIC I THINK REAL TIME
NEEDS OF PARTICULAR PROJECTS. >> I THINK THAT OVERALL THE
BOARD HAS REALLY REPEAT REPEATEDLY DEMONSTRATED THAT WE
ARE OPEN TO ACCOMMODATING THIS QUESTS THAT COME FORWARD TO
ADVANCE PARTICULAR PROJECTS. >> I ALSO UNDERSTAND OUR
STAKEHOLDERS ARE REQUESTING THAT IN A SUP AREA IN THE HEART
OF NORTH BEACH AND AN AREA THAT HAS A MUCH LOWER VACANCY RATE
THAT SOME OF THE PROTECTIONS ON ADDITIONAL RESTAURANTS
AND STAFF AND MERGERS TO BE RESTORED AND WITH THAT OFFSET
IT IT'S REALLY AT THE MOMENT WHERE THE COMMUNITY IT'S THE
SMALL BUSINESS IS STILL HAVING DIFFERENT VOICES BUT I ALSO
HAVE SO MANY CONVERSATION WITH SUPERVISOR SALTER AND HE IS
COMMITTED HE IS COMMITTED TO CONTINUE TO MONITOR THE
CONCERNS AND CONTINUE TO ENGAGE WITH IMPACTED MERCHANTS AND I
AM GIVING FAVOR TO MY COLLEAGUES WITH MY TIME AND HIS
OFFICE IS COMMITTED TO CRAFT SOMETHING THAT WILL BE MORE
BALANCE IN THE NEXT COUPLE MONTHS.
>> IT'S COMING AND I ALSO WANT TO SAY THAT ACCOUNTABLE
AND TRUST AND PARTNERSHIP WITH OUR COMMUNITY AND ALSO WITH
THIS BOARD WILL GO A LONG WAY AND AS SOMEONE ALSO SPENT A LOT
OF MY YOUTH TIME IN IN THE NORTH BEACH AND CHINATOWN I
ALSO LOVE THERE NOT BEACH AND WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO
SAY THAT I'M GOING TO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION.
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 31
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
AND CHAN VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 32 ITEM 32 WAS CONSIDERED
BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
OCTOBER 27TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED WITH A
NEW TITLE TO IDENTIFY THE NAME OF THE APPOINTEE.
ITEM 32 IS A MOTION TO APPOINT JESSE RUIZ NAVARRO TERM ENDING
JUNE 6TH, 2026 TO THE IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 32 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I THERE ARE EIGHT THERE ARE TEN
EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED AND MADAM
CLERK LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL SUPERVISOR WALTON IS FIRST UP
TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH MADAM
CLERK COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE TWO RESOLUTIONS IN MEMORIAM.
I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION REAFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S
WATCH ACT. ACROSS THE COUNTRY WE ARE
SEEING A DISTURBING RISE IN GOVERNMENT SURVEILLANCE DATA
COLLECTION AND TARGETING OF COMMUNITIES UNDER THE GUISE OF
SECURITY AND PUBLIC SAFETY. FEDERAL AGENCIES CONTINUE TO
EXPAND THEIR REACH INTO LOCAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS OFTEN
WITHOUT WARRANTS, TRANSPARENCY OR MEANINGFUL OVERSIGHT.
IN TIMES LIKE THESE REAFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S WATCH ACT IS
NOT SYMBOLIC. IT IS ESSENTIAL.
IT REMINDS US THAT LOCAL GOVERNMENTS HAVE BOTH THE RIGHT
AND THE RESPONSIBILITY TO PROTECT THE PRIVACY, CIVIL
LIBERTIES AND CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS OF OUR RESIDENTS.
THE WATCH ACT WAS CREATED IN RESPONSE TO GROWING PUBLIC
CONCERN OVER THE SWEEPING POWERS GRANTED THE US PATRIOT
ACT FOLLOWING 911 AND IN 2004 SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS APPROVED A
CHARTER AMENDMENT THAT GAVE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THE POWER
TO REVIEW AND RESPOND TO FEDERAL OR STATE DEMANDS FOR
CITY RECORDS THAT COULD VIOLATE INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS.
>> THE BOARD THEN ENACTED THE WATCH ACT ORDINANCE 50 1-05
CO-SPONSORED BY FORMER SUPERVISOR JAKE MCGOLDRICK TO
PUT THIS PROTECTION INTO LAW ASSURING THAT SAN FRANCISCO
WOULD NEVER BE COMPLICIT IN UNCONSTITUTIONAL
SURVEILLANCE OR DATA COLLECTION.
>> THE PATRIOT ACT REMAINS THE ONLY LAW EVER DESIGNATED UNDER
THIS SAFEGUARD REFLECTING SAN FRANCISCO'S LONGSTANDING
LEADERSHIP AND UPHOLDING DUE PROCESS AND CIVIL LIBERTIES.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS STOOD ON THE SIDE OF FREEDOM
AND ACCOUNTABILITY REAFFIRMING THE WATCH ACT ENSURES THAT OUR
CITY DEPARTMENTS WILL NOT COMPLY WITH ANY STATE OR
FEDERAL ORDER THAT VIOLATES DUE PROCESS OR INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS REMAINS VIGILANT AGAINST ANY
MISUSE OF POWER THAT THREATENS OUR IMMIGRANT LGBTQ PLUS
ACTIVISTS AND WORKING CLASS COMMUNITIES AND ALL OF OUR
RESIDENTS. THIS RESOLUTION MAKES CLEAR
THAT SAN FRANCISCO WILL CONTINUE TO LEAD WITH
TRANSPARENCY, COURAGE AND THE RULE OF LAW ESPECIALLY WHEN
THOSE VALUES ARE BEING TESTED AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL.
I ALSO WANT TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION THAT DISCUSSES THE
HARMS THAT ARE IMMEDIATE TO OUR STATE AND LOCAL GOVERNMENTS.
ON NOVEMBER 1ST SNAP BENEFITS WILL BE DISRUPTED LEAVING 42
MILLION PEOPLE ACROSS THE COUNTRY FOOD INSECURE
AND UNABLE TO PURCHASE BASIC NECESSITIES LIKE GROCERIES.
IN SAN FRANCISCO ALONE, 111,855 PEOPLE WILL BE AFFECTED.
THIS INCLUDES WORKERS AND FAMILIES WITH YOUNG
CHILDREN. FOOD BANKS ARE ALREADY SOUNDING
THE ALARM AS FAMILIES BRACE FOR AN UNPRECEDENTED CRISIS.
THIS IS A CRISIS THAT COULD HAVE BEEN 100% PREVENTED.
WHILE OUR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CONTINUES TO TAKE MONEY FROM
EVERY SINGLE WORKER WHO OWNS A PAYCHECK EARNS A PAYCHECK, THEY
HAVE STOPPED SERVICES THAT SERVE THE PEOPLE INCLUDING
INSTALLING FEDERAL DOLLARS FOR FOOD ASSISTANCE, HEALTH CARE,
EDUCATION, INFRASTRUCTURE AND PUBLIC SAFETY.
THIS IS NOT FISCAL RESPONSIBILITY.
IT IS MORAL NEGLIGENCE. >> COMMUNITIES ARE BEING HELD
HOSTAGE BY POLITICAL DYSFUNCTION AND THE MOST
VULNERABLE ARE PAYING THE PRICE.
IN CALIFORNIA ALONE, MORE THAN 250,000 FEDERAL EMPLOYEES
AND CONTRACT WORKERS MANY OF THEM UNION MEMBERS ARE BEING
FORCED TO WORK WITHOUT PAY. THERE WAS A TIME IN HISTORY
WHEN WORKING WITHOUT COMPENSATION WAS CALLED SLAVERY
AND THE ECHOES OF THAT INJUSTICE SHOULD NOT BE
TOLERATED IN ANY FORM TODAY. AS LOCAL LEADERS WE ARE ALWAYS
ACCOUNTABLE TO OUR CONSTITUENT ONCE.
BUT WHEN FEDERAL INACTION DISRUPTS SERVICES AND STALLS A
THIS UNDERMINES PUBLIC TRUST AND THE ABILITY TO SERVE OUR
COMMUNITIES. CITIES LIKE SAN FRANCISCO MUST
CONTINUE TO STEP UP WHERE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS FAILED
BY PROTECTING OUR RESIDENTS STANDING WITH WORKERS
AND FIGHTING TO KEEP FAMILIES FED.
HOUSED AND SAFE. THAT'S WHY I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO STAND WITH THE S.F. LABOR COUNCIL TO CALL ON
FEDERAL LEADERS TO FUND THE GOVERNMENT, FIX THE HEALTH CARE
CRISIS AND PUT WORKING PEOPLE FIRST AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.
AND LASTLY, I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM FOR THE LEGENDARY
MISS BELVA DAVIS. >> WHEN CBS SUNDAY MORNING
RECENTLY PAID TRIBUTE TO BELVA DAVIS, THEY ENDED WITH HER OWN
WORDS. DON'T BE AFRAID OF THE SPACE
BETWEEN YOUR DREAMS AND REALITY .
IF YOU CAN DREAM IT YOU CAN MAKE IT SO THOSE WORDS CAPTURE
WHO WAS A WOMAN WHO DREAM BIG. >> AND AGAINST ALL ODDS.
BORN IN MONROE, LOUISIANA IN 1932 BELVA CAME TO THE BAY
AREA AS A YOUNG GIRL FLEEING THE JIM CROW SOUTH.
FROM HUMBLE BEGINNINGS SHE BECAME A TRAILBLAZER.
SHE WAS THE FIRST BLACK WOMAN TO ANCHOR TELEVISION NEWS ON
THE WEST COAST. >> SHE DIDN'T JUST REPORT
HISTORY. SHE HELPED SHAPE IT.
BELVA VOICE CARRIED US THROUGH SOME OF THE MOST DEFINING
MOMENTS OF OUR TIME FROM THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT AND BLACK
PANTHER ERA TO THE AIDS CRISIS AND THE WARS ABROAD.
WITH POISE AND PURPOSE, SHE TOLD THE STORIES OTHERS IGNORED
GIVING VOICE TO THE UNHEARD INVISIBILITY TO THE UNSEEN.
>> ACROSS FIVE DECADES AND BAY AREA NEWSROOMS FROM KPIX TO
KQED TO KIRO IN THERE WAS BRILLIANCE, INTEGRITY
AND EMPATHY CHANGE JOURNALISM FOREVER.
HER INTERVIEWS SPANNED ICONS LIKE JAMES BALDWIN, MARTIN
LUTHER KING JR. MUHAMMAD ALI AND EVERY
PRESIDENT FROM REAGAN TO BUSH. BUT WHETHER SHE WAS SITTING
WITH WORLD LEADERS OR NEIGHBORS FROM HER COMMUNITY, SHE TREATED
EVERY STORY WITH EQUAL CARE AND RESPECT.
BEYOND THE NEWSROOM, BELVA WAS A TIRELESS ADVOCATE FOR
EQUALITY THE ARTS AND EDUCATION .
SHE BROKE BARRIERS FOR WOMEN, FOR WOMEN AND PEOPLE OF COLOR
IN MEDIA FOUGHT FOR FAIR LABOR STANDARDS AND HELPED BUILD
INSTITUTIONS LIKE THE MUSEUM OF THE AFRICAN DIASPORA.
>> BILL WAS ACCOLADES FROM EMMY AWARDS TO HALL OF FAME
INDUCTIONS ONLY BEGAN TO MEASURE HER IMPACT.
SHE WAS AS MAYOR WILLIE BROWN ONCE SAID, NOT ONLY THE BEST
JOURNALIST I EVER KNEW BUT ONE OF THE FINEST HUMAN BEINGS SHE
SHARED 62 YEARS OF LOVE AND PARTNERSHIP WITH HER
HUSBAND BILL MOORE AND A UNION OF PIONEERS WHO OPENED THE
DOORS FOR GENERATIONS TO COME. >> BELVA DAVIS LEAVES BEHIND A
LEGACY OF COURAGE, GRACE AND CONVICTION.
SHE TAUGHT US THAT TRUTH TELLING IS AN ACT OF LOVE
AND THAT DREAMS NO MATTER HOW DISTANCE HOW DISTANT ARE WORTH
PURSUING. >> MAY WE CONTINUE TO WALK
THROUGH THE DOORS SHE OPENED AS.
I HAVE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO DO AND KEEP HER LIGHT SHINING
AND EVERY STORY YET TO BE TOLD. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
SUPERVISOR CHIN. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
FIRST I WANT TO SHARE MY SENTIMENT.
CONCURRING WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON AND WOULD LIKE TO JOIN
IN THE MEMORIAM FOR MS.. DAVIS.
I MET HER WHEN I WAS A TO OUR THEN DISTRICT ATTORNEY KAMALA
HARRIS AND WAS JUST IN ODD OF HER PRESENCE AND I COULDN'T
AGREE MORE ABOUT HOW SHE INSPIRE A WHOLE NEW GENERATION
OF WOMEN WOMEN OF COLOR IN LEADERSHIP BUT PARTICULARLY
IN JOURNALISM. >> SHE GAVE ALL OF US HOPE
AND THE SPACE TO DREAM AND BE BETTER AND TO BELIEVE THAT WE
CAN DO ALL THOSE THINGS AND BEYOND.
SO FOR THAT I'M JUST SO GRATEFUL FOR HER LEGACY.
>> COLLEAGUES ALSO I WOULD LIKE TO INTRODUCE AND IN MEMORIAM
FOR RETIRED ASSISTANT CHIEF FRY FRANK BLACKBURN OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT, A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE.
ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURNE WAS BORN IN 1933.
HEY BOB, OUR HIGH SCHOOL ALUM. U.S. NAVY VETERAN AND A
DEDICATED 35 YEAR MEMBER OF SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT.
>> HE CAME FROM A FAMILY WITH LONG CAREERS AS FIREFIGHTERS.
HIS FATHER, BATTALION CHIEF F.P. BLACKBURN AND HIS TWO
BROTHERS CAPTAIN RICHARD BLACKBURN AND LIEUTENANT ROBERT
BLACKBURN. ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURN
JOINED THE DEPARTMENT IN 1956 AND SOON DISTINGUISHED HIMSELF
AS A BRIGHT AND AND PASSIONATE STUDENT AND STUDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTING HISTORY TACTICS AND STRATEGY.
>> HE DEVELOPED AN INCREDIBLE UNDERSTAND OF THE DEPARTMENT'S
WATER SUPPLY REQUIREMENTS AND THE INFRASTRUCTURE THAT
DELIVER IT TO THE HYDRANT. AN EARLY CAREER IN THE 1950S
AND 1960S BEFORE FIRE WAS A STIFF CONSTRUCTION
AND SPRINKLERS SYSTEM AND COUPLED WITH A BROAD MIX OF
RESIDENTIAL HIGH RISE AND INDUSTRIAL STRUCTURES.
ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURN INTEGRATED HIS PARTICLE
FIREFIGHTING EXPERIENCE WITH HIS UNDERSTANDING OF A JUNIOR
RING. >> DUE TO HIS NAVY TRAINING
COMBINED WITH HIS NATURAL AND GREAT CREATIVITY AND GREAT
MIND SAN FRANCISCANS AND FUTURE GENERATION ARE NOW THE
BENEFICIARY OF HIS INSIGHTS AND DISCIPLINE WITH PLANS
DATING BACK TO IN 1895 FOR THE PROPOSAL FOR A HIGH PRESSURE
ACCELERATOR HYDRANT SYSTEM. ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURN BEGAN
TO STUDY EARTHQUAKES AND THE FIRES THAT DESTROYED SAN
FRANCISCO IN THE 1906 EARTHQUAKE IN THE MID 1980S.
ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURN AFTER ABOUT TWO YEARS AND WITH THE
HELP OF THE CITY'S MACHINE SHOP DEVELOPED A PROTOTYPE FOR A
PORTABLE HYDRANT TO ADAPT TO EXISTING FIRE HOSES THAT COULD
BE DEPLOYED AS NEEDED. TWO DIFFERENT LOCATIONS
THROUGHOUT THE CITY. >> IN ADDITION TO MANAGING THE
HYDRANT EXPANSION PROJECT, BLACK ASSISTANT CHIEF BLACKBURN
ALSO MANAGED TO COMPLETE FOUR PORTABLE WATER SUPPLY SYSTEM
HOSE TENDER UNITS A WEEK AFTER A COMPREHENSIVE SERIES OF
TRAINING DRILLS TO ENDURE ALL FIRE DEPARTMENT MEMBERS THAT
ARE NOW FAMILIAR WITH HOW TO DEPLOY AND OPERATE THE NEW
PORTABLE HYDRANT SYSTEM. >> THE OCTOBER 17TH, 1989
EARTHQUAKE HAPPENED BUT WITH THE WATER MAIN RUPTURE IN THE
MARINA. PORTABLE HOSE TENDERS WERE
IMPLEMENTED TO ADDRESS QUICKLY AS THE THE QUICKLY ESCALATING
FIRE. BECAUSE OF HIS INVENTION WE
REALLY BE ABLE TO SAVE LARGE PART OF SAN FRANCISCO ASSISTANT
CHIEF BLACKBURN RETIRED IN 1991 SPENDING MUCH OF HIS TIME
IN EUROPE WHEN VISITING FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
HE WAS OFTEN CALLED UPON BY OUR FIRE DEPARTMENT TO CONSULT ON
MATTERS OF DISASTER PREPAREDNESS.
HIS LEGACY OF PUBLIC SERVICE INSPIRE A CULTURE OF
PREPAREDNESS, ENCOURAGING EFFECTIVE TRAINING
AND INNOVATIVE DESIGN EQUIPMENT ENSURING THAT ALMOST ANY ANY
FIREFIGHTING EMERGENCY IN SAN FRANCISCO COULD BE ADDRESSED.
HE WILL BE GREATLY MISSED. >> HE IS HE WAS A LEGEND
AND THAT WE ALL SHOULD BE SO THANKFUL TO HIS LEGACY AND THE
REST. I SUBMIT THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. THANK YOU, MADAM KURT.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCED IN A HEARING REQUEST
AND LETTER OF INQUIRY TO MULTIPLE CITY AGENCIES ABOUT
THEIR PROTOCOLS AND TRAINING FOR INTERACTIONS WITH FEDERAL
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT. >> I AM MAKING THIS REQUEST AS
DUE TO THE SIGNIFICANT INCREASE IN FEDERAL IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT MONTHS AND SUBSEQUENT FEAR, CHAOS
AND MISINFORMATION IN THAT IT'S IMPACTING OUR CITY'S IMMIGRANTS
COMMUNITIES. CONCURRENTLY THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN SHUT DOWN FOR NEARLY A MONTH CUTTING OFF
ACCESS TO ESSENTIAL SERVICES THAT INDIVIDUALS RELY ON FOR
EDUCATION FOR HEALTH CARE AND MORE.
THE DEPARTMENTS THAT I AM ASKING TO RESPOND
AND REQUESTING APPEAR AT THE FUTURE HEARING ARE RESPONSIBLE
FOR ENTITIES, BUILDINGS OR VEHICLE THAT CIVILIANS GO TO OR
UTILIZE FOR SERVICES OF INFORMATIONS.
>> THIS INCLUDE THE PUBLIC LIBRARY HEALTH CLINICS, POLICE
STATIONS, BUSSES AND MORE. >> AS A SANCTUARY CITY THAT HAS
COMMITTED TO PROTECTING, STABILIZING AND SUPPORTING OUR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES, IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT OUR RESIDENTS
KNOW THAT IT IS SAFE FOR THEM TO VISIT CITY OWNED
AND OPERATED FACILITIES AND THAT OUR CITY AGENCIES
AND STAFF HAVE BEEN TRAINED ON PROTOCOLS AND PROTECT THEM FROM
HARASSMENT OR ABUSE. >> THE QUESTIONS I'M ASKING
INCLUDE WHAT POLICIES AND PROCEDURES THAT ARE
IN PLACE WHEN ICE AGENTS ENTER OUR FACILITY OR PUBLIC TRANSIT
WHETHER OR NOT CITY STAFF RECEIVE TRAININGS ON HOW TO
INTERACT WITH FEDERAL IMMIGRATION AGENTS.
IF DEPARTMENT STAFF ARE FULLY TRAINED ON OR APPLICABLE RECENT
STATE LAW CHANGES WHETHER OR NOT POLICIES ARE POSTED ON
SITES OR ONLINE IN LANGUAGE AND MORE.
>> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MATT MORE FOR HIS COLLABORATION
AND EARLY SUPPORT OF THIS INQUIRY AND HEARING REQUESTS
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> I WOULD JUST LIKE TO ADD MY VOICE ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR
CHAN'S TO THE BEAUTIFUL IN MEMORIAM SUPERVISOR WALTON
OFFERED TO THE LATE BELVA DAVIS .
I HAVE PROBABLY WORKED WITH HUNDREDS OF JOURNALISTS OVER
THE COURSE OF MY CAREER AND I THINK ONLY ONE INTIMIDATED ME
NOT NOT BECAUSE OF ANYTHING SHE DID BUT JUST BECAUSE OF HER
GRAVITAS AND CLASS AND THE INSTITUTION THAT BELVA DAVIS
WAS AND BAY AREA JOURNALISM IN ADDITION TO HER
CONTRIBUTIONS TO JOURNALISM OF COURSE SHE WAS ALSO
INSTRUMENTAL IN FOUNDING THE MUSEUM OF THE AFRICAN DIASPORA
DIASPORA IN MY DISTRICT AND I KNOW SHE IS VERY MUCH MISSED
IN CULTURAL CIRCLES AS WELL AS JOURNALISM.
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
COLLEAGUES TODAY WITH A HEAVY HEART I REQUEST THAT WE ADJOURN
THIS MEETING IN MEMORIAM OF DANIEL CASANOVA WHO PASSED AWAY
SUDDENLY ON JULY SECOND. DANIEL WAS A BELOVED HUSBAND
FATHER AND AN INSPIRING LEADER IN OUR COMMUNITY WHOSE WORK
LEAVES BEHIND A LEGACY OF POWERFUL ADVOCACY AND JUSTICE.
>> IN 2024, DANIEL BECAME THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE
EVICTION DEFENSE COLLABORATIVE, AN ORGANIZATION SERVING OVER
3000 AT RISK SAN FRANCISCAN TENANTS EACH YEAR.
>> DURING HIS 14 MONTHS LEADING THE ORGANIZATION, HE ENGAGED
IN TIRELESS ADVOCACY FOR THE NETWORK OF HOMELESS PREVENTION
AGENCIES ACROSS THE CITY. HE MADE HIS MISSION TO KEEP SAN
FRANCISCANS SAFE AND HOUSED. DANIEL'S DIRECT WORK HELPED
HUNDREDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS AT RISK OF EVICTION WITH LEGAL
REPRESENTATION KEEPING THEM IN THEIR HOMES.
DANIEL'S FAMILY AND COWORKERS HAVE SHARED WITH ME THAT WHAT
MADE HIM STAND OUT WAS HIS OPEN MIND ACCEPTING HEART AND DEEP
APPRECIATION FOR DIFFERENT CULTURES.
>> THESE QUALITIES ALLOWED HIM TO FORM STRONG RELATIONSHIPS
THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE AND LONG CAREER IN NONPROFIT
AND COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS WHICH OVER THE
YEARS TRAVERSED THE GLOBE AND EDC.
DANIEL WORKED TO PROVIDE RENTAL ASSISTANCE, LEGAL ASSISTANCE
AND ADVOCACY FOR SHELTER CLIENTS AND HELP PREVENT
HOMELESSNESS. >> HIS LEADERSHIP WAS CRITICAL
IN KEEPING THOUSANDS HOUSED. DANIEL WAS A DEDICATED MENTOR
TO STAFF AND WAS KNOWN FOR DEVELOPING CREATIVE SOLUTIONS
TO PROBLEMS THINKING OUTSIDE THE BOX AND VALUING THE
EXPERIENCES OF THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND STRENGTHENING HIS
WORK. DANIEL'S ONE TRUE SUPERPOWER.
WHAT MADE HIS WORK SO EFFECTIVE WAS HIS ABILITY TO CONNECT TO
PEOPLE. HE HAD A CONTAGIOUS ENTHUSIASM
AND PASSION FOR LIFE THAT WAS GROUNDED IN A FOUNDATION OF
LOVE AND ACCEPTANCE FOR EVERYONE.
HE WAS ABLE TO QUICKLY BUILD RELATIONSHIPS WITH PEOPLE
FRIENDS, CLIENTS, COWORKERS, COMMUNITY PARTNERS BECAUSE HIS
RADIANT LOVE MADE EACH PERSON FEEL SPECIAL AND IMPORTANT.
HE VALUED THE EXPERIENCES OF THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS HIS
AGENCY AND OTHERS SERVED AND THEIR INPUT HELPED SHAPED
HIS APPROACH TO THE WORK HE DID EVERY DAY.
DANIEL WAS LARGER THAN LIFE A MAN WITH UNBOUNDED CONFIDENCE,
INFINITE ENERGY AND WILD AND CREATIVE IDEAS.
HE IS DEEPLY MISSED. I WANT TO EXTEND MY HEARTFELT
CONDOLENCES TO DANIEL'S FAMILY, FRIENDS AND COWORKERS.
REST IN PEACE AND POWER DANIEL CASANOVA.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MARK WOOD COLLEAGUES
TODAY I'M INTRODUCING LEGISLATION ESTABLISHING THE
SECOND DISTRICT FIVE ENTERTAINMENT ZONE.
>> THIS TIME ON FILLMORE STREET .
>> THE FILLMORE HAS LONG BEEN KNOWN AS THE HARLEM OF THE
WEST. >> KNOWN FOR ITS JAZZ, BLUES
AND DANCE CLUBS. >> AS TIME HAS GONE ON AND THE
CHARACTER OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD HAS CHANGED MANY OF THESE
VENUES HAVE UNFORTUNATELY SINCE SHUT DOWN.
>> NEVERTHELESS, THE ENTERTAINMENT POTENTIAL OF THE
FILLMORE HAS NEVER WANED. >> WE HEARD LOUD AND CLEAR FROM
THE COMMUNITY LEADERS ABOUT THE NEED FOR CREATIVE WAYS TO
SUPPORT NIGHTLIFE AND ENTERTAINMENT OPTIONS
IN THE FILLMORE. >> THE HEART AND SOUL OF WHAT
MADE FILLMORE THE HARLEM OF THE WEST IS STILL EMBEDDED IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD'S SPIRIT. >> THE ENTERTAINMENT ZONE
LEGISLATION WILL ALLOW ALCOHOL SERVING ESTABLISHMENTS ON THE
FILLMORE CORRIDOR TO SELL DRINKS TO GO DURING SPECIFIED
EVENTS. >> THE FOCUS AT THE START WILL
BE AROUND LARGER EVENTS LIKE THE ANNUAL JUNETEENTH
CELEBRATION. >> BUT THE BUSINESS COMMUNITY
WILL EXPLORE OTHER EVENTS TO ACTIVATE THE CORRIDOR AS WELL.
>> THESE EVENTS WILL HELP BUSINESSES LIKE MINNIE BELL'S
SOUL MOVEMENT AND SHEBA JAZZ LOUNGE BETTER CONNECT WITH
EVENTS GOING ON IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND CREATE AN
ENTERTAINMENT ECOSYSTEM THAT WILL HELP REVITALIZE THIS
CORRIDOR. >> OUR OFFICE IS ALSO
PARTNERING WITH THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT TO EXPLORE WAYS TO SUPPORT ENTERTAINMENT ZONE
EVENTS AS PART OF A LARGER STRATEGY TO HELP NEW BUSINESSES
OPEN AND EXISTING BUSINESSES STAY OPEN ON FILLMORE STREET.
I WANT TO GIVE MY EXPRESS THANKS TO REVEREND AND DR. AMOS
BROWN FOR HIS ADVOCACY ON THIS ISSUE AS WELL AS BEN JAN
CRAWFORD AND ERICA SCOTT FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP THAT THEY'VE
SHOWN ON THE ENTERTAINMENT ZONE FOR WORK, FOR THE WORK AND THE
WORK THEY'LL CONTINUE TO PUT INTO THIS TO MAKE THIS A
SUCCESS. >> I ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT WE'VE HEARD FROM THE COMMUNITY LOUD AND CLEAR ABOUT
THE URGENCY FOR SUCH ACTIONS AS WELL BECAUSE IT SHOWS A
COMMITMENT FROM THE CITY THAT THE FILLMORE DESERVES AS MUCH
ATTENTION AS THE REST OF THE CITY AS MUCH AS DOWNTOWN MUCH
AS ANY OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD. AND BASED ON THAT URGENCY I
WILL BE REQUESTING A 30 DAY WAIVER FROM THE PRESIDENT TO
HEAR THIS ENTERTAINMENT ZONE AS FAST AS POSSIBLE TO SHOW
AND CONTINUE THAT LONG OVERDUE CYCLE OF REBUILDING TRUST WITH
THIS COMMUNITY TO SHOW THAT WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT INVESTMENT
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD. >> I BELIEVE THE PRESIDENT HAS
HAS OFFERED TO GRANT THAT 30 DAY WAIVER AS WELL.
>> LASTLY, I WANT TO THANK BEN VAN HOUTEN AND KELLY VARIAN
FROM THE WDAS NIGHTLIFE TEAM FOR HELPING WITH THIS PROCESS.
>> AND LARRY MCLENDON ALSO FOR ONLY WD FOR HIS WORK SUPPORTING
BUSINESSES ON FILLMORE AND COORDINATING FUTURE SUPPORT
FOR ENTERTAINMENT ZONE EVENTS. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK
DRAFTING ATTORNEY VICKIE WONG, CAPTAIN MCCORMICK FROM NORTHERN
STATION AND MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE RENELL COOPER FOR THEIR
ASSISTANCE AS WELL AND CITED TO WORK WITH EVERYONE IN THE
COMMUNITY WHO'S COME OUT TODAY AND CONTINUING TO SUPPORT AS
WELL. >> SECOND, COLLEAGUES WANT TO
TALK ABOUT HOW SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG PRIDED ITSELF ON BEING
A SANCTUARY CITY A PLACE WHERE EVERYONE REGARDLESS OF
BACKGROUND OR IMMIGRATION STATUS DESERVES TO FEEL SAFE.
>> BUT LAST WEEK'S NEWS LEFT MANY OF OUR RESIDENTS FEELING
ANXIOUS AND UNCERTAIN ABOUT WHAT COMES NEXT.
>> WHILE THE FEDERAL OPERATIONS IN THE BAY AREA HAVE NOW BEEN
CALLED OFF, MY OFFICE CONTINUES TO HEAR CONCERNS FROM MANY OF
OUR NEIGHBORS BECAUSE WE KNOW THAT ICE HAS ALREADY BEEN HERE
FOR MONTHS. JUST LAST WEEK I GOT A CALL
FROM RESIDENTS IN THE TENDERLOIN WORRIED ABOUT THEIR
FRIEND WHO HADN'T COME HOME AFTER GETTING HIS FINGERPRINT
WORK DONE AT IMMIGRATION COURT. >> OUR OFFICE CONNECTED THESE
FOLKS TO THE SF RAPID RESPONSE NETWORK WHICH IN TRACKING THE
CASE LEARNED THAT HE HAD IN FACT BEEN DETAINED.
WE MUST DO MORE TO PROTECT OUR RESIDENTS.
>> THAT'S WHY TODAY ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR CHEN WE'RE
COAUTHORING AND INTRODUCING A DRAFTING REQUEST TO EXPLORE
LEGISLATION AROUND ICE FREE ZONES IN SAN FRANCISCO TO
PROTECT CITY OWNED PROPERTY FROM ACCESS TO ICE AND OTHER
FEDERAL AGENTS. >> I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A
DRAFTING REQUEST FOR LEGISLATION THAT REAFFIRMS OUR
SANCTUARY CITY STATUS IN THE CONTEXT OF A FEDERALIZED
NATIONAL GUARD DEPLOYMENT IN THE FORM OF A RESOLUTION.
>> THIS IS ALL PART OF A BROADER SAFE CITY'S BLUEPRINT A
PLAN TO STRENGTHEN LOCAL PROTECTIONS AGAINST ICE
AND FEDERALIZE NATIONAL GUARD, REAFFIRM OUR SANCTUARY CITY
VALUES AND DEFEND OUR COMMUNITIES FROM FEDERAL
OVERREACH. >> THROUGH THE SAFE CITIES
BLUEPRINT, WE'RE WORKING CLOSELY WITH THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S BOARD COLLEAGUES AND PARTNER CITIES ACROSS THE
COUNTRY TO SHARE IDEAS AND LEARN FROM ONE ANOTHER.
THE HOPE IS THAT TOGETHER WE CAN BUILD A MODEL FOR HOW
CITIES CAN STRENGTHEN THEIR LAWS TO PROTECT THE RESIDENTS
SO WE NEVER LOSE SIGHT OF OUR SHARED VALUES.
>> I WANTED TO THANK SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN CHAN,
MELGAR, SAUTER AND MENDELSOHN FOR YOUR EARLY SUPPORT FOR THIS
BLUEPRINT AND TO MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM LOGAN AND CHIEF OF
STAFF JESSICA GUTIERREZ GARCIA AND IN MY OFFICE AS WELL AS
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI FOR THE MANY LATE CALLS LAST
WEEK REVIEWING THIS BLUEPRINT AND LEGISLATION.
>> WHAT OUR RESIDENTS WANT MOST IS TO FEEL SAFE, TO FEEL
PROTECTED AND TO KNOW THAT THEIR CITY HAS THEIR BACK.
THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT THIS WORK IS ABOUT AND I HOPE TO HAVE THE
BOARD'S PARTNERSHIP AND THIS GOAL IN THE WEEKS AND MONTHS
AHEAD. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN THANK
YOU, MADAM CLERK. FIRST OF ALL, I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE IN MEMORIAM FOR BELVIDERE,
MISS. IF IT IS ALL RIGHT, I'D LIKE TO
ASK THAT THAT BE DONE ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD AND WE CAN DO
THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION, MADAM CLERK.
>> GAVEL. I WILL GAVEL.
YES, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
AND SECONDLY, I DO HAVE A RESOLUTION I AM INTRODUCING TO
RECOGNIZE NOVEMBER 1ST THROUGH THE NINTH AS RESTAURANT WEEK
IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
RESTAURANT WEEK IS AN ANNUAL EVENT THAT CELEBRATES SAN
FRANCISCO'S VIBRANT FOOD CULTURE, PROMOTES SMALL
BUSINESSES AND ENCOURAGES RESIDENTS, VISITORS
AND TOURISTS TO EXPLORE NEW DINING EXPERIENCES AT
DISCOUNTED PRICES. THE CULINARY SCENE IN SAN
FRANCISCO PLAYS A VITAL AND INTERNATIONALLY RECOGNIZED
ROLE IN OUR LOCAL ECONOMY REPRESENTING 9% OF THE CITY'S
WORKFORCE, ATTRACTING TOURISTS AND CONTRIBUTING TO THE
VIBRANCY OF EACH OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THIS YEAR 188 RESTAURANTS ARE PARTICIPATING IN RESTAURANT
WEEK, EACH OFFERING SPECIALLY CURATED PREFIXED MENUS
SHOWCASING THEIR ORIGINALITY. THIS WEEK IS AN OPPORTUNITY FOR
THESE BUSINESSES TO ENGAGE NEW CUSTOMERS AND WELCOME BACK OLD
REGULARS. S.F. RESTAURANT WEEK IS A BIG
JOB THAT REQUIRES COMPLEX COORDINATION AMONG OWNERS,
CHEFS, SPONSORS AND CUSTOMERS. THE RESULT IS A FANTASTIC EVENT
THAT CELEBRATES ENHANCES THE CITY'S CULTURE CULTURAL,
CULINARY AND SOCIAL FABRIC. I WANT TO THANK THE GOLDEN GATE
RESTAURANT ASSOCIATION ESPECIALLY LORI THOMAS AND AMY
CLEARY FOR PULLING THIS OFF ANNUALLY FOR MORE THAN A DECADE
WHILE MORE THAN A DECADE AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. >> I HAVE TWO IN MEMORIAM.
FIRST SAN FRANCISCO MOURNS THE PASSING OF FATHER TONY LATORRE,
A BELOVED NATIVE SON WHOSE WARMTH HUMOR AND FAITH TOUCHED
GENERATIONS ACROSS OUR CITY. FROM HIS EARLY DAYS AT LINCOLN
HIGH SCHOOL TO HIS ORDINATION AT SAINT PATRICK'S SEMINARY,
FATHER TONY DEVOTED HIS LIFE TO MINISTRY, COMPASSION
AND CONNECTION. HIS PRESENCE AT MANY WEST SIDE
PARISHES STEPHEN SAINT MONICA SAINT THOMAS, THE APOSTLE SAINT
THIN BAR AND PARISHES ACROSS THE BAY AREA BROUGHT COMFORT
AND WARMTH TO THE FAITHFUL AND FRIENDSHIP TO ALL.
EVEN IN RETIREMENT HE CONTINUED TO VISIT THE SICK, BAPTIZE
BABIES AND CELEBRATE MASS WITH JOY.
FATHER TONY'S LOVE FOR HIS COMMUNITY HIS DOGS, HIS FAMILY
IN HIS CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO WAS AS BOUNDLESS AS HIS
GENEROSITY. MAY HE REST IN PEACE.
>> THE SECOND. COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO
CLOSE TODAY'S MEETING IN HONOR OF JOHN J.
>> BOUVIER THE THIRD. JOHN WAS LOVINGLY REFERRED TO
AS THE MAYOR OF SIXTH AVENUE, A TITLE HE ABSOLUTELY DESERVED OR
WAS AS BEAUTIFULLY WRITTEN IN THE END JUDY CHRONICLES BLOG
BY GREG THE WAR THE RICHEST PERSON IN SAN FRANCISCO THE
RICHEST PERSON IN SAN FRANCISCO WAS NOT A TECH TITAN NOR A
MEMBER OF THE WEALTHY ELITE AND DOES NOT HAVE ANY BUILDINGS
WITH HIS NAME ON THEM OR AN EXPENSIVE YACHT TO RACE.
HE WAS ALWAYS THE RICHEST PERSON IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE
HE LEAVES BEHIND A PRICELESS LEGACY OF KINDNESS,
FRIENDLINESS AND COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT THAT WAS A SOURCE
OF POSITIVE ENERGY WHENEVER HE WENT.
HIS IMPACT ON THE WORLD AROUND HIM IS ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO
CALCULATE IN WHY IT HURTS SO MUCH TO HAVE HIM GO SO
SUDDENLY. >> JOHN HAD A SPECIAL GIFT FOR
BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER NOT JUST FOR EVENTS BUT IN EVERYDAY
LIFE. DURING THE ISOLATION OF THE
COVID 19 LOCKDOWN WHEN SO MANY FELT ALONE, JOHN TOOK IT UPON
HIMSELF TO FOSTER CONNECTION THROUGH FRIDAY OUTDOOR MEET UPS
OUTSIDE HIS HOME. THE FRIDAY MEET UPS BECAME A
BELOVED TRADITION OF THE INNER SUNSET COMMUNITY AND CONTINUED
FOR 280 FRIDAYS UNTIL JOHN'S PASSING.
WHETHER YOU LIVED ON SIXTH AVENUE OR WERE JUST WALKING BY
WITH YOUR DOG IN THE INNER SUNSET HE CREATED A SPACE WHERE
EVERYONE BELONGED. JOHN WAS RECENTLY NOMINATED BY
MANY OF HIS NEIGHBORS FOR THE INAUGURAL GOOD NEIGHBOR AWARD
AND HE WAS MORE THAN JUST A NEIGHBOR.
HE WAS SOMEONE COMMUNITY MEMBERS COULD ALWAYS TURN TO
FOR HELP, ADVICE OR JUST A LISTENING EAR.
NEIGHBORS DESCRIBED JOHN AS A TRUE RAY OF SUNSHINE.
>> THE HEART OF A BLOCK AND SIMPLY THE BEST.
>> JOHN TURNED A LONELY AND UNCERTAIN TIME INTO
SOMETHING JOYFUL AND LASTING AND THAT'S THE TRUE MARK OF A
COMMUNITY LEADER. WE WILL MISS YOU DEEPLY, JOHN.
YOUR PRESENCE WILL LIVE ON EVERY TIME NEIGHBORS GATHER,
SHARE A LAUGH AND REACH OUT TO HELP ONE ANOTHER.
>> MAY WE CONTINUE YOUR LEGACY BY KEEPING THAT SPIRIT OF
CONNECTION AND KINDNESS ALIVE OR IN OUR OWN HEART IN OUR OWN
BLOCKS AND AT THE PIE CONTEST IN THE INNER SUNSET.
THANK YOU JOHN, FOR REMINDING US WHAT COMMUNITY TRULY MEANS.
THIS PAST SATURDAY THE INNER SUNSET COMMUNITY CAME TOGETHER
FOR A MEMORIAL PROCESSION LED BY THE SUNSET COMMUNITY BAND
AND WE MARCHED FROM JOHN'S HOME TO THE COUNTY FAIRGROUND
BUILDING IN JUST A SHEER NUMBER OF PEOPLE WHO SHOWED UP IN THE
RAIN DEMONSTRATED JUST HOW MUCH JOHN MEANT TO SO MANY PEOPLE
ACROSS THE SAN FRANCISCO. IN ADDITION TO THE MANY, MANY
ORGANIZATIONS, JOHN WAS ACTIVE WITH, HE WAS ALSO AN ORDAINED
MEMBER OF THE SISTERS OF PERPETUAL INDULGENCE KNOWN AS
JOHN THE BAPTIST PURVEYOR OF BUT MAY HIS MEMORY FEE FOR A
BLESSING. HE WAS A TOUCHING TRIBUTE
AND HIS LEGACY LIVES ON THROUGH KINDNESS ON EVERY PERSON THAT
HE INSPIRED. SO TO HIS SISTER KRISTIN, HIS
FAMILY AND THE COMMUNITY WHO HE BROUGHT TOGETHER YOU HAVE OUR
DEEPEST CONDOLENCES SAN FRANCISCO LOST ONE OF ITS VERY
BEST. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER, MR. PRESIDENT, THAT CONCLUDES
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. ALL RIGHT.
AT THAT TIME AT THIS IS THE TIME IF YOU'RE HERE TO PROVIDE
YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT TO THE BOARD CAN LINE UP ON YOUR
RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. I SEE FORMER SUPERVISOR
AND REVEREND AMOS BROWN IS GOING TO GO FIRST.
>> MR. PRESIDENT. MADAM CLERK, MEMBERS OF THIS
AUGUST BODY AND ESPECIALLY MY SUPERVISOR I MOVE WE THANK YOU
FOR INTRODUCING THAT ENTERTAINMENT LEGISLATION.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, YOUR PREDECESSOR SAT IN THAT CHAIR
AND VOTED TO LEAD THIS BODY IN GIVING AN APOLOGY FOR THE
ENSLAVEMENT OF AFRICAN-AMERICANS >> AND ALSO
FOR THE DISCRIMINATORY PRACTICES BY THIS CITY.
MORE SPECIFICALLY THE REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY IN THE
DISPLACEMENT OF BLACK PEOPLE FROM THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> WE THANK GOD FOR A
SUPERVISOR WALTON WHO CARRIED THE LEGISLATION TO BRING THIS
BODY TO THIS POINT. HISTORICALLY THAT WAS DONE
IN 2019. WHEN WE ESTABLISH A REPARATIONS
TASK FORCE MY FRIENDS, I WANT TO APPEAL TO YOU THIS AFTERNOON
TO DO MORE THAN ISSUE AN APOLOGY.
>> NOW IS THE TIME FOR ACTION AND ACTION FOR COMMUNITY THAT
HAS BEEN FAR TOO LONG EXCLUDED .
AND NOW WE WILL HEAR FROM THE EXECUTIVE LEADERSHIP OF THE
FELLOWSHIP THAT HAS COME TOGETHER TO ENSURE THAT WITHOUT
DELAY AND WITH DELIBERATE SPEED WE WILL REVITALIZE THE FILLMORE
AND THE HERITAGE BUILDING. I PRESENT TO YOU NOW MY GREAT
SUCCESSOR, THE REVEREND MR. DAVON CRAWFORD, WHO WILL STILL
BE THE PROPHET IN THE LAND MAKING SURE THAT YOU DO JUSTICE
,LOVE MERCY AND WHILE COMPLY WITH YOUR GOD, YOUR PRINCIPLES
FOR LIVING WITHIN. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS THE REVEREND DEVIN JEROME CRAWFORD.
I SERVE AS THE SENIOR PASTOR OF THE THIRD BAPTIST CHURCH OF SAN
FRANCISCO, THE OLDEST AFRICAN-AMERICAN BAPTIST CHURCH
WEST OF THE ROCKY MOUNTAINS. WE'VE HAD A CONTINUOUS PRESENCE
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 173 YEARS.
THIS YEAR. >> HONORABLE SUPERVISORS I RISE
TODAY NOT ONLY AS A PASTOR, NOT ONLY AS THE SUCCESSOR OF THE
REVEREND DR. AMOS BROWN BUT I RISE TODAY AS A SON OF A
TRADITION WHO BELIEVES THAT MEMORY IS SACRED.
>> THE FILLMORE HERITAGE CENTER AND THE FILLMORE COMMUNITY IS
ONE OF THE LAST STANDING VESSELS OF AFRICAN-AMERICAN
PRESENCE, CREATIVITY AND COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> TO LOSE IT WOULD NOT ONLY BE A LOSS TO A NEIGHBORHOOD BUT IT
WOULD BE AN ERASURE OF SACRED GROUND ITSELF FOR GENERATIONS.
>> THE FILLMORE HAS BEEN WHERE JAZZ AND JUSTICE WALK HAND
IN HAND. IT HAS BEEN A PLACE WHERE
PEOPLE FROM ACROSS THE ASPIRA COME TOGETHER AND CONTINUE TO
FIND EACH OTHER AND CALL EACH OTHER NEIGHBOR AND THIS PLACE
IS A REFUGE FOR EXPRESSION OF WISDOM A PLACE WHERE KIND JOY
CAN MEET EACH OTHER EVERY DAY. AND WHEN WE HEAR THE SOUND OF
OUR MUSIC AND EACH OTHER'S VOICES TO ALLOW ANOTHER ANCHOR
INSTITUTION OF BLACK LIFE TO VANISH IS TO WOUND THE FABRIC
OF THE FILLMORE ITSELF. IT IS TO SAY THAT OUR STORY A
STORY THAT IS WOVEN THROUGH EXILE AND ENDURANCE NO LONGER
MATTERS. >> BUT I STAND HERE TODAY TO
SAY THAT IT DOES MATTER. >> INDEED.
OUR PRESENCE HERE IS A TESTAMENT TO THE FACT THAT IT
MATTERS BECAUSE WHEN THE FILLMORE THRIVES SAN FRANCISCO
REMEMBERS WHO SHE IS. A CITY OF RESILIENCE OF ART,
INCLUSION AND RADICAL HOPE. AND SO I APPEAL TO THIS BODY
TODAY NOT MERELY TO PRESERVE A BUILDING, NOT MERELY TO
PRESERVE RELICS BUT TO REVIVE A HEARTBEAT OF A COMMUNITY.
>> THE FILLMORE IS NOT ONLY ABOUT WHAT IT WAS BUT ABOUT
WHAT CAN BE A LIVING TESTAMENT FOR US ALL BACK THEN.
>> THANK YOU, REVEREND. AND THANK YOU TO THE REVEREND
AMOS BROWN FOR YOUR COMMENTS PREVIOUSLY.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> I'M ARCHBISHOP LONZO KING OF
THE AFRICAN ORTHODOX CHURCH GLOBAL SPIRITUAL COMMUNITY.
WE'VE BEEN SERVING THIS CITY NOW FOR 56 YEARS.
SPEAK FOR JUSTICE. SERVING THE PEOPLE DEALING WITH
LEGAL FORECLOSURE. BUT MOST OF ALL WE'VE BEEN
DEALING WITH THE ART AND THE CULTURE OF THIS CITY BECAUSE WE
ARE THE INSTITUTION THAT HAS BEEN KNOWN CANONIZING ONE JOHN
WILLIAM COLTRANE AS A SAINT AND THAT JOHN SAID THAT HE HAD
A SPIRITUAL AWAKENING THAT WAS A LEAD TO A RICHER, FULLER,
MORE PRODUCTIVE LIFE. AND AT THAT TIME HE ASKED TO BE
GIVEN THE PRIVILEGE TO MAKE OTHERS HAPPY THROUGH MUSIC.
AND FOR US TODAY BEING HAPPY IS BEING BEING ACKNOWLEDGED AND WE
FIND OURSELVES IN A VERY IMPORTANT TIME IN THE HISTORY
OF THIS CITY. AND THAT YOU AS BOARD MEMBERS
ARE IN THE ROLE OF CITY GOVERNMENT AND THEY HAVING THE
OPPORTUNITY TO CORRECT INJUSTICES THAT HAVE BEEN
COMMITTED AGAINST THE AFRICAN-AMERICA COMMUNITY.
WE CAME TOGETHER AND WE COME TOGETHER IN ONE VOICE THAT WE
HAVE RAISED VOICES THAT HAVE BEEN RAISED IN THE PAST
AND VOICES YOU ARE HEAR FRESH IN A NEW.
WE ARE SAYING THERE'S A DELIBERATE URGENCY THAT YOU
MOVE WITHOUT DELAY AND RETURN. SHOULD WE SAY THAT YOU CORRECT
WHAT HAS HAPPENED TO THE DEVASTATION OF THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND THE FILLMORE OF THE WEST BY
REINSTATING WHAT HAS BEEN PUT ON THE BOARD?
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, REVEREND ARCHBISHOP
KING, WELCOME. >> THANK YOU.
SO I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR THE FILLMORE
ENTERTAINMENT DISTRICT. IT'S GOING TO BE A VERY
BUSINESSES AND ENTREPRENEURS AND ARTISTS AND CULTURAL
CREATIVES ARE VERY EXCITED ABOUT THE OPPORTUNITY FOR THIS.
I ALSO WANT TO MY FAMILY CAME FROM ARKANSAS LEAVING JIM CROW
AND EVERYTHING THEY SURVIVED. THEY COME TO SAN FRANCISCO TO
MAKE A BETTER LIFE FOR THEMSELVES AND IN COMING HERE
WITH WITH NOTHING. OUR COMMUNITY WE TURN THE
FILLMORE INTO A SOMETHING THAT WAS RECOGNIZED AROUND THE WORLD
SOMETHING THAT THAT COULD BE THE ECONOMIC POWER THAT YOU SEE
IN THE MISSION DISTRICT IN CHINATOWN AND OTHER
NEIGHBORHOODS. >> MY GREAT UNCLE PLAYED ON
FILLMORE STREET IN THE HARLEM AND WAS BIG.
HE'S HE'S RIGHT THERE. I HAVE PICTURES OF HIM TO SHOW
ME HOW TO PLAY WHEN WHEN I WAS A KID MY FATHER ALSO PLAYED THE
SAXOPHONE BUT HE WENT TO THE MILITARY.
BUT WHEN HE CAME BACK HE WANTED TO FULFILL THE DREAM OF OF THE
LEGACY OF OUR FAMILY ENTERTAINMENT AND FILLMORE WHEN
HE CAME BACK THE FILM WAS BULLDOZED.
>> IT BROKE HIS HEART. IT BROKE OUR COMMUNITY'S HEART
. >> HE LEFT TO GO TO FRANCE TO
PLAY MUSIC BECAUSE HE LEARNED THAT THAT'S WHERE YOU GO TO
PLAY MUSIC WHEN YOU'RE AFRICAN-AMERICAN NOT IN YOUR
OWN COUNTRY WHERE OUR QUARTERS ARE BULLDOZED.
>> BARBER KNEW ACROSS THE COUNTRY HE NEVER CAME BACK.
HE DIED OF A HOPE, HOPE A BROKEN HEART OUT THERE.
IT'S EMOTIONAL FOR ME. AND SO THE FILLMORE HERITAGE
CENTER IS REALLY THE LAST THING WE HAVE AS A COMMUNITY.
IT'S A LAST OPPORTUNITY OF THE CITY TO UNDO THE ECONOMIC
VIOLENCE THAT WAS IMPOSED ON OUR COMMUNITY BY URBAN RENEWAL
. AND SO I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD BECAUSE HE'S OUT THERE IN THE COMMUNITY.
HE'S BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS WITH A LOT OF PEOPLE IN THE
COMMUNITY WHICH IS KEY TO WHAT NEEDS TO GET DONE.
BUT THIS IS AN OPPORTUNITY BY THE CITY TO UNDO THE HARM OF
THOSE COMMUNITY MEMBERS THAT WERE ECONOMICALLY AND VIOLENTLY
HARM. BARBARA NO.
SO PLEASE OPEN THE FILLMORE HERITAGE CENTER AS SOON AS
POSSIBLE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. MAJID WELCOME TO THE NEXT
SPEAKER. >> HELLO AMERICA'S GOT THANK
YOU BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR ACKNOWLEDGING US HERE TODAY.
SUPERVISOR BLOUGH THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SINCERE ACTION.
AS REVEREND BROWN SAYS, WE SEE IT IN ACTION AND ALWAYS WANT TO
SAY THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR WATSON FOR HIS ADVOCACY.
>> I GREW UP HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THIRD GENERATION MY
KIDS NOW OUR FOURTH GENERATION GROWING UP IN THE FILLMORE I
JUST CAME BACK FROM VISITING MY DAUGHTER IN COLLEGE AT HBCU
UNIVERSITY IN TEXAS. I RECENTLY I HAVE SHARED THIS
BEFORE BUT I WAS SHOCKED BUT IT'S IMPORTANT FOR ME TO SAY IT
AGAIN. I'VE BEEN STUDYING THE
DOCUMENTARIES AND SPEECHES OF THE DR. MARTIN LUTHER KING JR
AND CORETTA SCOTT KING AND MARTIN LUTHER KING SAID IT
THE MOST RACIST PLACE HE HAD EVER VISITED IN THE WORLD WAS
SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA >> COMING I'M SORRY WALKING ON THE
CAMPUS OF THE SCHOOL WHEN MY DAUGHTER ATTENDS.
>> I UNDERSTOOD THAT STATEMENT THERE'S A PLACE FOR BLACK
PEOPLE. >> THERE'S A PLACE FOR THRIVING
BLACK PEOPLE. >> THOUSANDS OF BLACK STUDENTS
STUDYING TOGETHER. YOU WALK ON THE CAMPUS, YOU SEE
PROFESSOR THERE'S YOU SEE DOCTORS THERE AND CHEMISTRY
LABS. IT'S A REAL TANGIBLE SPACE FOR
SUCCESS. WE DON'T HAVE THAT IN SAN
FRANCISCO. WE ARE ASKING THE CITY, THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO MAKE THAT POSSIBLE THROUGH THE FAIR
THE FILLMORE HERITAGE CENTER. >> SO WE ARE VERY GRATEFUL FOR
THE INTRODUCTION OF THEIR ENTERTAINMENT SO WE CAN'T HAVE
ENTERTAINMENT IF WE DON'T HAVE A SPACE.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS OPPORTUNITY AND I'M JUST
IMPLORING YOU ALL TO FIGHT WITH US THAT WE NEED ACCESS TO THAT
BUILDING. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU ERIC FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> JUST FOR THOSE INDIVIDUALS, IF THIS IS YOUR FIRST TIME
THERE ARE NO AUDITORY SOUNDS IN SUPPORT OR AGAINST OF
SPEAKERS. >> PLEASE WELCOME SIR CHARLES
RICHARD BROTHERS AGAINST GUNS A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE 57 YEARS
I'VE BEEN HERE BORN AND RAISED IN FILLMORE I AM THE FOURTH OR
MAYBE FIFTH GENERATION TO BE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
MY GRANDKIDS, MY KIDS COME AFTER ME.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS OF LAW FOR INTRODUCING THIS.
THANK YOU. ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE ALL
THE SUPERVISORS HERE ALONG WITH OUR PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR AND I
ALSO WANT TO GIVE A BIG SHOUT OUT TO OUR SUPERVISORS SHAMAR
WALTON WHO'S BEEN A BACKBONE FIGHTING FOR SAN FRANCISCO
BLACK FOLKS IN SAN FRANCISCO ACROSS THE CITY BORN AND RAISED
IN FILLMORE LOST TWO BROTHERS TO GUN VIOLENCE MURDER IN 95
AND 99 WATCHED THE FILLMORE CENTER GET BUILT WHEN IT WAS
JUST A DIRT PATH AND WATCH THE HAIRS CENTER GET BUILT WHEN
HE'S A DIRT PAL. >> WHEN LEE HILL HUTCH WAS A
DIRT PAL BORN AND RAISED AND SEEN THINGS GO UP AND I
LOOK AROUND AND I SEE OTHER NATIONALITIES GETTING THINGS
THAT THEY ASKED FOR BUT THE BLACK COMMUNITY HAVE NOT
RECEIVED ANYTHING THAT WE ASKED FOR AND WE'RE STILL FIGHTING TO
GET WHAT WE NEED. >> HERE IT IS 30 YEARS LATER.
THAT'S UNACCEPTABLE. WE DO NOT HAVE ANYTHING LEFT
STANDING BUT THE HERITAGE CENTER THAT WE WANT TO GET BACK
INTO OUR COMMUNITY, OUR HANDS AND I ASK YOU GUYS TO PLEASE
SUPPORT THIS MOVE FORWARD ON THIS LEAVE US A LEGACY THAT WE
CAN HAVE FOR OUR GRANDKIDS, OUR KIDS OR GRANDKIDS AND OTHER
KIDS TO COME. SO WITH THAT BEING SAID,
SUPPORT WHAT WE'RE ASKING FOR AND THAT'S THE LEGACY OF THE
HERITAGE CENTER. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SEAN RICHARDS FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. YEAH, I'M KEVIN JOHNSON, NATIVE
SAN FRANCISCAN. THE HERITAGE CENTER MEANS SO
MUCH TO THE BLACK COMMUNITY. Y'ALL KNOW WHAT HAPPENED TO THE
FILLMORE. AND THIS CITY IS RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE FOR THE DEVASTATION. SO THIS IS OUR LAST OPPORTUNITY
. AND THERE THE MAYOR HAS
ESTABLISHED AN ENTERTAINMENT ZONE TO, YOU KNOW, ENTERTAIN
AND WE'RE KNOWN FOR ENTERTAINMENT.
WE'VE GOT SO MUCH ENTERTAINMENT IN THE FILLMORE SCHIST IN OUR
BONES. YOU KNOW, LIKE IF YOU WE WANT
THIS CITY TO BE GREAT AND WE WANT OUR COMMUNITY TO BE A
GREAT COMMUNITY. SO GIVE US THIS OPPORTUNITY.
THE FILLMORE HERITAGE CENTER WAS BUILT FOR US.
IT WAS BUILT TO HELP REVITALIZE THE COMMUNITY.
WE'RE NOW LOOK AT IT THE CITY HAVE NOT TAKEN CARE OF THE
BUILDING THAT JUST DECIDED THE THE POSTERS IS ONE OF OUR GREAT
SONG SONG. >> OUR SINGERS AND AND PEOPLE
THAT THE POSTERS ARE FALLING DOWN I MEAN THIS IS THIS THIS
IS AWFUL GIVE US THE OPPORTUNITY TO REBUILD THE
FILLMORE HERITAGE CENTER AND BRING BACK THE
ENTERTAINMENT TO OUR COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. KEN JOHNSON FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. THE NEXT SPEAKER YES, WE'LL CAN
COLLECT THAT FROM YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. FOR THE RECORD MY NAME IS CHRIS
CHRISTOPHER KLEIN. I ALSO GO BY SERGEANT KLEIN OF
THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS. FIRST I WANTED TO APPLAUD THE
BOARD FOR TACKLING OVERREACH OF SURVEILLANCE BY A CITY, COUNTY,
STATE, FEDERAL AND FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS.
SO THANK YOU. I ALSO WANTED TO COMPARE THE
TIME IS NOT GOING BUT THANK YOU FOR THE EXTRA TIME.
I WANTED TO COMPARE JULY 1969 TO OCTOBER 2025.
AND THESE ARE FROM THE NEW YORK TIMES JULY 8TH, 1969 103 HEROIN
USERS DIED HERE IN JUNE. THAT'S NEW YORK CITY.
THAT NUMBER IS DOUBLE NORMAL. THE AVERAGE AGE WAS 22ND JULY
NINTH, 1969. U.S. PLANES WATCHING SOVIET
CRAFT IN THE ATLANTIC OFF THE COAST OF MAINE AND MARYLAND
HEADING TO CUBA. MAJOR EVENTS HAPPENING DURING
THAT WEEK THAT IMPACTED ME AND MY FAMILY.
AND IT WAS THE PRECURSOR TO MY GRANDFATHER JOHN SROKA.
THAT LAST NAME IS SPELLED C O C A THAT WENT MISSING IN JULY OF
1969 JULY 9TH, 1969. A BIG BROTHER KEEPS AN EYE ON
SPEEDING CARS. ELECTRONIC MACHINE GETS
EVIDENCED BY TAKING PHOTOS JUST LIKE SURVEILLANCE A DAY SPEED
CAMERAS JULY 19TH, 1969 CROWDS STILL FLOATING NIAGARA WITH THE
WATER TURNED OFF. IMAGINE THE TECHNOLOGY TO TURN
OFF THE NIAGARA FALLS IN 1969 BUT WE HAVE NOT MOVED FORWARD
SINCE THEN. JULY 24TH, 1969 THE US THANKS
THE SOVIETS FOR APOLLO PRAISE THE UNITED STATES RESPONDING TO
A SOVIET TRIBUTE WHEN THE APOLLO ASTRONAUTS TODAY
EXPRESSED HOPES THAT THE FRATERNAL SPIRIT DEMONSTRATED
BY SOVIETS AND AMERICAN SPACEMAN WILL LEAD TO
COOPERATION ON THE EARTH. ALSO MORE PEACE, LESS WAR.
IF THE TECHNOLOGY WAS SO GREAT BACK THEN WHY DID WE GET RID OF
IT? BECAUSE PEOPLE WERE USING IT
FOR HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS. WHAT WE NEED IS STRONG
INDIVIDUALS FOR STRONGER FAMILIES THAT FORMED THE
STRONGEST COMMUNITIES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
YES, GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ACE.
>> I'M ON THE CASE AND CURRENTLY I'M THE FILLMORE
CORRIDOR AMBASSADOR AND IT WOULD BE REMISS IF I DIDN'T GET
UP AND SEE SOMETHING ABOUT THE FEEL BOARD PARTICULARLY ABOUT
THE HERITAGE CENTER. I STAYED RIGHT ACROSS THE
STREET IN MISS KING'S HOUSE AND I WATCHED THEM AS THEY
STARTED TO FEEL MORE CENTER. OKAY.
THE BRICKS AND EVERYBODY THAT CAME BY.
I WAS THERE WHEN THEY WENT THROUGH THE DIFFERENT PROCESS
OF THE RFP PIECE. >> I WAS THERE WHEN THEY
SUBMITTED EVERYTHING. I GOT THE DOCUMENTS AND I PLAN
TO REVEAL IT IN A SHOW CALLED THE REWIND THE TAPES.
BUT I'M HERE SPECIFICALLY ACTUALLY ALL THE SUPERVISORS
FIRST OF ALL I WANT TO THANK MY SUPERVISOR MARLENE FOR HELPING
US OUT IN THE MAYOR. BUT IN BREATHY YELL GO SIGN ON
TO I SUSPECT. BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT HOW
IMPORTANT THIS HERITAGE CENTER IS TO THE FILLMORE AND TO MY
FAMILY. I'M NOT ONLY A FATHER, I'M A
GRANDFATHER. I'M A GREAT GRANDFATHER.
MOST PEOPLE LOOK AT ME SAY ACE, WHERE YOU CAME FROM SPACE NO,
I'VE BEEN HERE IN THE FILLMORE ALL MY LIFE AND I'M SAYING THIS
FROM MY HEART WITHOUT ANY DELAY .
>> WE NEED SUPPORT FROM THE REST OF THE SUPERVISORS AND THE
MAYOR AND I'M SURE HE CARES FOR THE HERITAGE SITES THE ADDITION
YOSHI'S WE NEED THAT SPOT FOR THE COMMUNITY IN OUR YOUNGER
GENERATION WHO WILL BE OF MY GENERATION UNDER ME SAID DADDY
WHAT DID YOU DO ALL THOSE YEARS AND WE DON'T HAVE NOTHING TO
SHOW FOR IT. >> I WOULD BE REMISS BY SAYING
I'M 71 YEARS OLD AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT SOMETHING IS
RESERVED FOR OUR COMMUNITY AND THAT IS THE HERITAGE CITY.
MY NAME IS FAITH AND I'M ALL THE CASE.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
MR. WASHINGTON. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME.
>> OH MY NAME IS MICHAEL KEMP. I'M A LONG TIME RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO. I CAME HERE 40 YEARS AGO TO
ATTEND LAW SCHOOL AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I'M ALSO A CURRENT MEMBER AND HAVE BEEN A MEMBER OF THIRD
BAPTIST CHURCH IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT HAVE KEPT ME HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
HAS BEEN ITS CULTURAL DIVERSITY .
JAPANTOWN HAS THIS CELEBRATION .
CHINATOWN HAS A CELEBRATION. THE DISTRICT HAS THIS
CELEBRATION. >> LITTLE ITALY HAS THIS
CELEBRATIONS. FILLMORE HAS ITS CELEBRATIONS.
WHEN I WAS 18 OR 19 GOING TO COLLEGE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO, I ACTUALLY READ IN MAGAZINES ABOUT JAZZ SINGERS
HARLEM LITTLE STREET IN NEW ORLEANS.
THEY HAD A LITTLE BOURBON STREET AND IF THEY HAD BEALE
STREET IN SAN FRANCISCO THEY HAD FILLMORE STREET.
SO AS I GOT OLDER I HAD A CHANCE TO VISIT ALL THESE
PLACES AND I KIND OF NOTICED THAT THE JAZZ WAS BEING PLAYED
BY WHITE MUSICIANS. BUT THAT'S OKAY.
THEY WERE PRESERVING THE HISTORY, PRESERVING THE
CULTURE. SO I'M ASKING YOU GUYS TO
SUPPORT THIS ENTERTAINMENT RESOLUTION BECAUSE IT'S GOING
TO BRING PEOPLE FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD TO SAN FRANCISCO.
EVERYONE LOVE YOUR MUSIC. IT'S ALSO GOING TO BE THAT'S A
SOURCE OF TAX REVENUE. SO SUPPORT THAT RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
MICHAEL KIM. >> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME
AND GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME'S MARIO BENTON.
I'VE NOT BEEN HERE SINCE 2:00 SO I'M MARIO BENTON AND I'M
BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO RIGHT IN THE FILLMORE
ON 14TH AND BUCHANAN STREET AND EVERY DAY AFTER SCHOOL I
WOULD PLAY AT THE PERFORMING ARTS OF THE WESTERN EDITION
CULTURAL CENTER WHERE I WOULD LEARN DANCE MODELING, ACTING
AND JAZZ. AND I GREW UP IN THE CREATIVE
ARTS AND IN ME GROWING UP IN FILLMORE I WAS ALSO
DISPLACED EARLY AT THE AGE BECAUSE I CAME OUT THE CLOSET
OF BEING A GAY PERSON EARLY AND I WAS KIND OF BULLYING
AND RAN AWAY FROM THE FILLMORE AND KIND OF RAN DOWN TO THE
TENDERLOIN AS A YOUNG YOUTH WHO HAD BEEN DISPLACED IN SAN
FRANCISCO. BUT AS YEARS WENT ON I WAS ABLE
TO FIND MYSELF. I WENT THROUGH TRAUMA AND DRAMA
BUT I WAS ABLE TO FIND MYSELF AND ONCE I FOUND MYSELF I TAP
BACK INTO THE CREATIVE ARTS AND IN THE ARTS I'VE BEEN
TRAVELING ALL OVER THE WORLD DOING MODELING AND DANCE
AND PERFORMANCES AND I'M BACK IN FILM WHERE I'VE BEEN WORKING
WITH THE JAZZ JUNETEENTH FESTIVAL.
I'VE BEEN PART OF THAT JUNETEENTH ALL MY LIFE AND ONE
OF THE ORGANIZERS OF HELPING DEVELOP THE JUNETEENTH
AND WE'VE DONE SUCH A GREAT JOB AT MAKING IN SUCH A BIG, BIG
EVENT NOW AND EXTENDING THE BLOCKS AND JUST THE NEW
DEVELOPMENT OF JUNETEENTH AND I'M PART OF MAKING SAN
FRANCISCO GROW WITH OUR JUNETEENTH AND WE WANT TO SEE
FILLMORE STREET AS WELL AS ALL THE OTHER EVENTS.
>> I'M ALSO PART OF I'M INTO THE STREETS OF DOWNTOWN EVENTS
AND INTO THE STREETS AND A LOT OF PRIDE AND ALL OF THOSE
EVENTS I'M CONNECTED TO THOSE EVENTS AND I WANT TO SEE THE
FOOTPRINT OF FILLMORE WEST IN ADDITION GROW JUST AS WELL
AS ALL THE OTHER PLACES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I THINK FILLMORE
STREET WOULD BE A BEAUTIFUL PLACE TO BRING THE MUSIC
AND ENTERTAINMENT AND THE FOOTPRINT OF ENTERTAINMENT ON
FILLMORE STREET. >> THAT'S ME.
THANK YOU, MARIO. THANK YOU MARIO BENTON FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
OR TO SUPER POWERS PRESIDENT MEN AND THE BOARD MEMBERS.
MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON I ALMOST FAINTED LAST WEEK
AND I WANT TO APOLOGIZE OUR RICH ISN'T HERE TO HE HAD LEFT
THE BUILDING LAST WEEK WHEN I ALMOST FAINTED.
BUT IN ANY EVENT I JUST WANTED TO REAFFIRM MY OPPOSITION TO
THE MAYOR ADOPTING HIS OWN COMMUTER SYSTEM AS THE CITYWIDE
COMPUTER SYSTEM. THIS GIVES HIM AN OWN UNBRIDLED
POWER THAT IF YOU CAN IT'S ONE THING TO CONTROL THE COMPUTER,
IT'S ANOTHER THING TO CONTROL THE OPERATING SYSTEM.
IT'S ANOTHER THING TO CONTROL THE APPLICATION.
WHEN HIS COMPANY LET'S CALL IT TRIPPING HAS SPENT TEN YEARS
WITH AN APPLICATION PROGRAM AM DESIGNED FOR TRIPPING POINT.
HE IS INTIMATELY KNOWLEDGEABLE ABOUT THAT PROGRAM AND THAT IS
GOING TO COST ALL OF YOU YOUR POWER TO OPPOSE HIM.
I USUALLY TALK ABOUT PARCEL TAXES BUT THAT'S ALMOST DOWN
THE LINE ONCE HE HAS CONTROL OF THE COMPUTER FOR SAN FRANCISCO
HE HAS CONTROL OF WHAT INFORMATION IS AVAILABLE, WHAT
INFORMATION IS RELEASED AND WHO CAN USE THE INFORMATION.
AND I THINK YOU SHOULD BE FOREWARNED THAT THIS IS
EXTREMELY DANGEROUS PRECEDENT. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
WHEN DO I START? NOW.
OKAY. YES.
REGARDING AS YOU KNOW REGARDING FAMILIES OWNING I WAS UNABLE TO
COME TO THE PLANNING LAND USE RATHER COMMITTEE LAST WEEK SIR
. >> YES.
ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN?
I WAS I CALLED UP YOUR OFFICE AND ASKED IF I COULD DO IT
DURING PUBLIC COMMENT AND THEY SAID YES.
I TALKED TO RICHARD. I CALLED THE CLERK'S OFFICE
TODAY, SAID COULD I TESTIFY? AND HE TOLD ME I COULD COME
DURING PUBLIC COMMENT BECAUSE IT'S NOT ON THE AGENDA.
>> YOUR RICHARD'S SIR YOU ARE CORRECT.
>> YOU CAN SPEAK ABOUT IT. OKAY.
I'M SORRY. JUST DRAW THAT MICROPHONE A
LITTLE CLOSER FOR ME. >> OKAY?
THANKS TO ME. YES.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
I CHECKED TO MAKE SURE SO REGARDING FAMILY ZONING, THE
CRITERIA CONSIDERED BY LAND USE LAST WEEK ADDING PROTECTIONS TO
RENT CONTROL UNITS APPLIES EQUALLY TO TENANTS LIVING
IN REGULAR NON RENT CONTROLLED UNITS.
THESE TENANTS ALSO SHOULD BE PROTECTED TENANTS AND NON RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS ARE EQUALLY LIKELY TO BE STRUGGLING TO PAY
RENT AND STAY IN SAN FRANCISCO TENANTS AND NON RENT CONTROLLED
UNITS ARE JUST AS LIKELY TO BE SENIORS AND WE KNOW THIS AT ST
VINCENT DE PAUL IN NORTH BEACH WHO ARE ONCE EVICTED OR
DISPLACED BY PRIOR DEMOLITIONS OR OWNER MOVE INSTANCES WHERE
WERE THEY FOUND TO LIVE AND SO THEY'RE LIVING IN A PLACE
THAT'S TOO EXPENSIVE FOR THEM NON RENT CONTROL TENANTS ARE AS
VALUABLE TO OUR CULTURAL HERITAGE.
WE SHOULD TREAT THEM WITH THE SAME RESPECT AND PROTECTIONS
ARTISTS, MUSICIANS AND POETS GRADUATE EACH YEAR FROM COLLEGE
AND HIGH SCHOOLS AND EVEN WITHOUT GRADUATION AS ARTISTS
THEY TAKE THEIR UNIQUE TALENTS AND USE THEM TO MAKE OUR CITY
MORE EXCITING. THEY ADD TO OUR ECONOMY AN
ARTIST ARRIVING JUST ONE YEAR AGO IN SAN FRANCISCO MIGHT NOT
BE LIVING IN A RENT CONTROLLED UNIT BUT THEIR RENTAL IS NO
LESS VULNERABLE TO UP ZONING. THEY SHOULD BE PROTECTED WITH
THE SAME FORCE AND DIRECTNESS AS RENT CONTROLLED UNITS.
WE CAN AFFORD TO DO THIS. JD MORRIS JUST REPORTED IN THE
CHRONICLE THAT IF THE RENT CONTROL PROTECTIONS PASS,
84,000 UNITS WILL BE PROTECTED FROM THE UP ZONING BUT THIS IS
THE TOTAL NUMBER OF RENT CONTROLLED UNITS IN THE CITY
NOT ONLY THOSE ON THE FAMILY ZONING MAPS.
AND WE KNOW THIS THAT ST VINCENT DE PAUL AND NORTH BEACH
BECAUSE WE MADE A SUNSHINE REQUEST AND WERE TOLD AN
ADULTERER LEE THAT THAT THERE ARE NO STATISTICS THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT SAID ON THIS MATTER THEY DON'T KNOW WHAT THE ANSWER
IS SO WE SAY PROTECT ALL TENANTS ADDING THEM IS
EQUITABLE, GOOD FOR OUR CITY AND HELPS THE ECONOMY AND IT
GIVES STABILITY TO NEIGHBORHOOD BECAUSE IT TELLS ALL TENANTS
WHO ARE RENTING AND THAT'S WHAT IT MEANS TO LIVE AFFORDABLY
THAT THEY ARE GOING TO BE TREATED THE SAME AND LOOKED OUT
FOR GOVERNMENT WHATEVER THE LABEL MAY BE WHERE THEY LIVE.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO, MY NAME IS AMANDA MAIA
AND I'M THE PROGRAM DIRECTOR FOR THE LAWYERS COMMITTEE FOR
CIVIL RIGHTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA.
A CORE PART OF OUR WORK IS REPRESENTING IMMIGRANTS WHO ARE
DETAINED BY ICE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND SECURING THEIR
FREEDOM WITH HABEAS CORPUS PETITIONS.
WE PARTICIPATED IN THE ATTORNEY OF THE DAY PROGRAM IN SAN
FRANCISCO IMMIGRATION COURT AND JUST LAST MONTH WE SUED THE
ADMINISTRATION TO END ILLEGAL COURTHOUSE ARRESTS.
I HAVE HAD THE VERY DIFFICULT JOB OF TELLING IMMIGRANTS AT
THEIR MASTER CALENDAR HEARINGS THAT THEY ARE GOING TO BE
DETAINED WHEN THEY EXIT THE COURTROOM.
I HAVE HAD THE TERRIBLE JOB OF HAVING TO CONTACT THEIR FAMILY
MEMBERS TO LET THEM KNOW THAT THEIR FAMILY MEMBERS WERE NOT
GOING TO BE RETURNING HOME THAT NIGHT.
>> THE INDIVIDUALS WE REPRESENT ARE OUR NEIGHBORS, ESSENTIAL
WORKERS AND PARENTS OF CHILDREN IN OUR SCHOOLS.
>> WE COME TO YOU TODAY TO OFFER OUR STRONGEST SUPPORT FOR
THIS CRITICAL BUDGET SUPPLEMENTAL.
>> WE ARE SPEAKING TO YOU AT A MOMENT OF PROFOUND CRISIS AS
THE ADMINISTRATION THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION HAS UNLEASHED AN
INHUMANE CRACKDOWN ON OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES.
>> SANCTUARY CITIES LIKE SAN FRANCISCO ARE THE LAST LINE OF
DEFENSE THE $3.5 MILLION ALLOCATED TO THE IMMIGRATION
LEGAL SERVICES COLLABORATIVES IS A LIFELINE OF OUR WORK.
IT WILL FUND ATTORNEYS WHO STAND BETWEEN OUR COMMUNITY
MEMBERS AND FAMILY SEPARATION. >> SAN FRANCISCO HAS A PROUD
HISTORY OF STANDING UP FOR JUSTICE AND DEFENDING OUR MOST
VULNERABLE RESIDENTS. TODAY YOU HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO AFFIRM THAT LEGACY IN THE MOST CONCRETE WAY POSSIBLE.
WE URGE YOU TO APPROVE THE FULL 3.5 MILLION TO SUSTAIN OUR
CITY'S IMMIGRATION LEGAL DEFENSE NETWORK, OUR CLIENTS
AND OUR SHARED COMMUNITY IN OUR SHARED COMMUNITY ARE COUNTING
ON YOUR LEADERSHIP. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WE JUST ASK THAT YOU HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE WELCOME.
HELLO. WE HAD QUITE THE WEEK LAST WEEK
IT WE DID ANYONE ELSE NOTICE THAT OUR MAYORS ACTUALLY
GENERATIVE? I BOUGHT WHO TRAINS ON OTHER
MAYORS RESPONSES AND SPITS OUT A HOLLOW VERSION OF A MAYORAL
RESPONSE TO EMERGENCIES LIKE THAT.
>> I DID WELL, HE'S STILL OUR MAYOR.
SO WE HAVE ANOTHER EMERGENCY COMING UP COME NOVEMBER WITH
THE SNAP BENEFITS NOT BEING FUNDED.
THIS IS WHAT OUR MAYORS SAID TO THE SAN FRANCISCO MARIN FOOD
BANK WHEN HE WAS CAMPAIGNING FOR MAYOR.
>> WE NEED TO TREAT FOOD SECURITY AS A CORE PUBLIC
HEALTH ISSUE AND USE EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL INCLUDING
FEDERAL AND STATE FUNDING TO ENSURE NO SAN FRANCISCAN GOES
HUNGRY. HE ALSO SAID I WILL PRIORITIZE
ENSURING THAT ALL SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE ACCESS TO
NUTRITIOUS FOOD. WE MUST STRENGTHEN OUR
PARTNERSHIPS WITH COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS LIKE FOOD BANKS
TO IDENTIFY LONG TERM SUSTAINABLE SOLUTIONS THAT GO
BEYOND EMERGENCY PANDEMIC FUNDING.
MY ADMINISTRATION WOULD ENSURE THAT SAN FRANCISCO ACTIVELY
SEEKS OUT AND APPLIES FOR EVERY AVAILABLE DOLLAR TO TACKLE
HUNGER AND POVERTY WE NEED TO TREAT FOOD SECURITY AS A CORE
PUBLIC HEALTH ISSUE AND USE EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL
INCLUDING FEDERAL AND STATE FUNDING TO ENSURE NO SAN
FRANCISCAN GOES HUNGRY. >> CAN I GET AN UPDATE ON THAT
CAMPAIGN PROMISE THAT WOULD BE LIKE REALLY AWESOME TO KNOW
RIGHT NOW BEFORE NOVEMBER HITS. WHERE WHERE IS HE IN THIS PLAN
OF HIS TO KEEP SAN FRANCISCO FROM STARVING.
>> HELLO. >> SO SOMETHING THAT'S VERY
SIMILAR NOW I JUST HAVE THESE LIKE 2020 COVID FLASHBACKS OF
EVERYONE SHELTERING IN PLACE EXCEPT NOW THEY'RE SHELTERING
IN PLACE BECAUSE THEY'RE AFRAID OF ICE AND THEY'RE AFRAID OF
BEING KIDNAPED AND DEPORTED TO PLACES THEY DON'T KNOW WHERE OR
TORTURED IN CONCENTRATION CAMPS.
>> THE BILLIONAIRES ARE STILL HANGING AROUND HOARDING THEIR
THEIR WEALTH INSTEAD OF SWOOPING IN TO SAVE THE DAY
AND LIKE FEED PEOPLE AND HOUSE PEOPLE AND STUFF.
>> AND THE REASON THAT THEY'RE NOT DOING ANYTHING IS BECAUSE
THEY REQUIRE THIS MASSIVE HUMAN SACRIFICE TO BE BILLIONAIRES.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> HI. MY NAME'S BRIAN STORE.
>> I SPOKE TO THE CITY COUNCIL ABOUT A COUPLE OF MONTHS AGO
ABOUT THIS SAME TOPIC I'VE SENT SOME OF YOU GUYS EMAILS I'M
HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE MOST ILLEGAL GENESIS LONG RANGE
ACOUSTIC KILLING DEVICE OPERATORS IN AMERICAN SOIL.
THEY'RE FROM SOUTHERN OREGON AND THESE OPERATORS CONTINUE TO
TARGET MY HEART AND HEAD TRYING TO RESONATE WITH MY HEART
AND CAUSE HEART FAILURE AS WELL AS BRAIN DAMAGE.
THIS HAS GONE ON SINCE 2023. THEY CONTINUE TO COMMIT FELONY
CRIMES ON MILITARY EQUIPMENT 20 473 65 AND NOBODY STOPS THEM.
THEY BRAG ON THE ROADS AT FBI WON'T BE ABLE TO CATCH THEM.
THEY'RE BASICALLY UNTOUCHABLE. THE EL RAD OPERATORS HAVE SAID
THEY WILL TAKE THREE LIVES IN THE NEXT YEAR.
ME MY MOM'S IN MY AUNT'S. THEY HAVE ALSO SAID THEY WOULD
PAY $100,000 FOR SOMEONE TO TAKE MY LIFE.
THEY STILL HAVEN'T BEEN CHARGED OR ARRESTED FOR THESE CRIMES
THEY COMMITTED THEM FOR OVER A WEEK IN SAN FRANCISCO AND OVER
THREE WEEKS IN THE BAY AREA ON MILITARY EQUIPMENT AND THEY'RE
STILL FREE TO COMMIT THE SAME CRIMES.
THIS IS NOT ABOUT JUST BEING AUTO TRACKED BY THE GENESIS
LONG RANGE ACOUSTIC KILLING DEVICES AS THEY CONTINUE TO USE
FORCE AND PRESSURE FROM THE ACOUSTIC WEAPONS.
SINCE THE LAST TIME I SPOKE HERE MY SON'S LEG WAS INJURED
BY THE GENESIS LONG RANGE ACOUSTIC DRONE DEVICE OPERATORS
AND CAUSED HIM TO HAVE A LIMP. NOTHING HAS BEEN DONE.
THEY ALSO CONTINUE TO TRY AND TURN VICTIMS INTO SUSPECTS.
LAW ENFORCEMENT CONTINUES TO LET THEM COMMIT CRIMES EVERY
DAY. THEY ALSO CONTINUE TO BRAG ON
THE RADS ABOUT TAKING MY AUNT'S LIFE IN DANVILLE A COUPLE OF
MONTHS BACK. I HAVE FBI TIPS I'VE MADE THAT
I WOULD LIKE TO PUT ON THE RECORD.
ME AND MY FAMILY URGENTLY NEED HELP GETTING THIS STOPPED
AND INTO A FEDERAL COURTROOM SO THESE CRIMINAL LONG RANGE
ACOUSTIC KILLING DEVICE WEAPON OPERATORS CANNOT FOLLOW THROUGH
WITH THEIR THREATS OF VIOLENCE AGAINST ME AND MY FAMILY.
THE PUBLIC IS IN DANGER ANYWHERE THESE OPERATORS CAN
TOUCH EL ROAD IF THEY'RE NOT STOPPED THERE WILL BE MORE
VICTIMS. THEY NEED TO BE ARRESTED
AND TRIED IN A COURTROOM FOR THEIR FELONY CRIMES MILITARY
EQUIPMENT PLEASE ME AND MY FAMILY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AS YOU JUST DID WITH YOUR
PUBLIC COMMENT. OKAY.
WOULD YOU LIKE TO SUBMIT A DOCUMENT WE'RE HAPPY TO TAKE
THAT FROM YOU. THANK YOU.
HE'S COMING TO PICK IT UP FROM YOU.
>> WELCOME. CAROLYN GUZMAN.
THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CAROLYN GOOSEN AND I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE TO SHARE OUR STRONG
SUPPORT FOR THE SUPPLEMENTAL INTRODUCED TODAY TO INCREASE
FUNDING FOR NONPROFIT IMMIGRANT LEGAL SERVICES.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN WALTON
FIELDER, MAHMUD MELGAR AND MANDOLIN FAIR CO-SPONSORS
SHIP WE GREATLY THANK YOU THESE PAST FEW WEEKS AND INDEED THIS
PAST YEAR HAS REMINDED US OF JUST HOW CRITICAL IT IS THAT
ALL OF OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY MEMBERS HAVE ACCESS TO
IMMEDIATE LEGAL REPRESENTATION AND RESOURCES.
OUR PUBLIC DEFENDER IMMIGRATION UNIT HAS HAD A LONG STANDING
PARTNERSHIP WITH THE NONPROFIT IMMIGRANT LEGAL RESOURCES
IN SAN FRANCISCO'S NONPROFITS AND COORDINATES CLOSELY WITH
S.F. IDC S.F. ISLAND AND THE RAPID RESPONSE NETWORK TO
REPRESENT THE MAXIMUM AMOUNT OF PEOPLE POSSIBLE IN PARTICULAR
IN THIS MOMENT OF CHAOS, FEAR AND A DRAMATIC INCREASE
IN DETENTIONS BY ICE. >> WE'RE WORKING TOGETHER MORE
CLOSELY THAN EVER BEFORE TO PROVIDE RAPID RESPONSE
IMMIGRATION LAWYER CONSULTATIONS TO SAN FRANCISCO
RESIDENTS DETAINED AT ICE CHECK INS OR COURT AT 630.
>> SINCE THE CURRENT ENFORCEMENT TRENDS UNDER THIS
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAVE PRESENTED A TREMENDOUS NEED FOR
ADDITIONAL REPRESENTATION AND SPECIFICALLY FOR PETITIONS
FOR HABEAS CORPUS FOR NONCITIZENS UNLAWFULLY DETAINED
AT 630 SANSOM RIGHT HERE IN DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> IT HAS ALSO SKYROCKETED THE INCIDENTS OF DETAINED SAN
FRANCISCAN RESIDENTS. >> WE URGE YOU TO PASS THIS
BUDGET SUPPLEMENTAL TO EXPAND CAPACITY FOR HABEAS PETITIONS
AND OTHER EMERGENCY LEGAL SUPPORTS TO RESPOND TO THE
INCREASED ICE ENFORCEMENT AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS AT THE WOODROW AREA AND I'M THE DIRECTOR OF THE
AFRICAN ADVOCACY NETWORK. WE DO PROVIDE IMMIGRATION LEGAL
SERVICES TO AFRICAN AFRO-CARIBBEAN IMMIGRANTS
AND WE WE BASED HERE IN THE CITY.
BUT I WILL START WITH THE PERSONAL NOTE THANKING, YOU
KNOW, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS BECAUSE I'M OF THE NEW
APPOINTEES ON THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION THAT YOU KNOW, YOU
DID CONFIRM THIS THIS VERY AFTERNOON.
SO THANK YOU AGAIN FOR GIVING US A CHANCE FOR BETTER
REPRESENTATION ON OUR COMMISSIONS AND WE LOOK FORWARD
WORKING ALONG YOU KNOW, OTHER COMMITTEES.
AND I'M ALSO HERE TO REMIND EVERYBODY THE DIVERSITY OF THE
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY I KNOW MOST EVERY TIME YOU KNOW PEOPLE
SPEAK ABOUT HISPANICS OR SPEAK ABOUT API BUT YOU KNOW THE
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY IS EXTREMELY DIVERSE.
YOU KNOW, IT'S THE PICTURE OF THE WORLD AND A FEW DAYS AGO I
WAS HERE I WAS SHARING THAT YOU KNOW, I LEARNED IN SAN
FRANCISCO THEY WERE CHOOSING AND TO ME, YOU KNOW, IT WAS A
WAKE UP CALL, YOU KNOW, FINDING MYSELF IN THE WORLD WHERE
DIVERSITY, INCLUSION, INTEGRATION SEEMS TO BE A
REALITY AND THEN HERE WE ARE TODAY WE ALL OF US KNOW THAT
WHAT IS HAPPENING IS WRONG. YOU DON'T CALL OTHER HUMAN
BEINGS ANIMALS. YOU DON'T TREAT OTHER HUMAN
BEINGS LIKE ANIMALS. AND I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, YOU
ARE IN THE RIGHT POSITION TO REMIND EVERYBODY IN SAN
FRANCISCO THAT SOMETHING IS GOING IS ONE AND THAT, YOU
KNOW, WHATEVER IS HAPPENING NOW IS A SEA IS A THING FOR A TIME
THAT IS GOING TO GO BUT BEFORE IT'S GONE AGAIN, YOU KNOW, WE
LIKE TO BEG YOU SO BUT YOU ARE YOU SUPPORT YOU ON THE
SUPPLEMENTAL OR THE WORK HAS TO CONTINUE IS GOING TO CONTINUE
BEYOND YOU KNOW THIS THIS ADMINISTRATION BUT FOR THE TIME
BEING THE JOB IS TO BE DONE AND AGAIN, YOU KNOW, I WOULD
LIKE TO BEG YOU, YOU KNOW, TO SUPPORT, YOU KNOW, THE
SUPPLEMENTAL SO WE CONTINUE TO WORK, YOU KNOW, TAKING CARE OF
OUR COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND FOR BETTER INTEGRATION
AND INCLUSION IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> SO WELCOME.
OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS SARAH GAVIGAN. I'M A SENIOR IMMIGRATION
ATTORNEY AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN RESOURCE CENTER.
CRESSON WHICH IS IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
I HAVE BEEN THERE FOR TEN YEARS DOING REMOVAL DEFENSE WITH THE
SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT LEGAL DEFENSE COLLABORATIVE, ALSO
KNOWN AS SFI LDC. SO I'M HERE TO TALK IN SUPPORT
OF THE $3.5 MILLION SUPPLEMENTAL THAT IS GOING TO
BE CRUCIAL GOING FORWARD IN THIS ENVIRONMENT WHICH WE
SAW REALLY PLAY OUT THIS WEEK. I ALSO WANT TO MENTION THAT I
AM A LONG TIME RESIDENT OF THE MARINA DISTRICT.
I ALSO WENT TO HIGH SCHOOL HERE IN THIS IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND HAVE A LOT OF CONNECTIONS THAT AND FRIENDS AND FAMILY
THAT ARE STILL IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THAT CARE A LOT ABOUT THIS
ISSUE. SO AGAIN I'M PART OF THE RAPID
RESPONSE NETWORK WHERE WHEN TERRIFIED FAMILY MEMBERS CALL A
DISPATCHER AND THEY SAY MY LOVED ONE HAS BEEN TAKEN OR
THEY DIDN'T COME BACK FROM THIS CHECK IN WITH ICE, I GET THE
CALL. AND SO MY COLLEAGUES HAVE
ALREADY SPOKEN AS WELL AND WE IMMEDIATELY DISPATCH TO TRY TO
FIGURE OUT WHERE WE CAN INTERVENE AT LEAST COLLECT
INFORMATION AND THEN SO THE PERSON THAT THE PERSON'S DUE
PROCESS IS NOT COMPLETELY LOST. THEY DON'T COMPLETELY FALL
THROUGH THE CRACKS. AND I CAN TELL YOU IN THIS LAST
WEEK I'VE HAD A LONG TIME SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS FAMILIES
THAT MAYBE HAD THIS HASN'T ALWAYS BEEN ON THEIR RADAR BUT
THEY'RE NOW VERY CONCERNED FROM THE MARINA, FROM THE PRESIDIO,
FROM LAUREL HEIGHTS, FROM MANY MORE NEIGHBORHOODS.
BUT I'LL JUST SAY THAT THEY HAVE CALLED ME TO SAY THANK YOU
SO MUCH FOR THE WORK THAT YOU'RE DOING.
WE'RE REALLY CONCERNED. WHAT CAN OUR CITY YOU KNOW,
WHAT MORE CAN WE DO AND JUST THANK YOU.
SO I WANT TO CONVEY THAT SENTIMENT FROM ALL OVER THE
CITY THAT NOW IS THE TIME TO REALLY LEAN INTO DUE PROCESS
AND WE'D LOVE TO SEE UNANIMOUS SUPPORT FOR THIS SUPPLEMENTAL
TODAY. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS PETER HABIB. I AM AN ATTORNEY AT THE CENTER
FOR GENDER AND REFUGEE STUDIES WERE A CURRENT MEMBER AND ONE
OF THE FOUNDING MEMBERS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT LEGAL
DEFENSE COLLABORATIVE SFR DC I'M OUR OFFICES RIGHT DOWN THE
STREET AT U.C. LAW SAN FRANCISCO SO I'M HERE TO ALSO
URGE YOU TO APPROVE THE BUDGET SUPPLEMENT FOR FOR CRITICAL
IMMIGRATION IMMIGRANT DEFENSE SUPPORT SERVICES AS ONE OF THE
LEGAL AS ONE OF THE LEADING RATHER AUTHORITIES ON ASYLUM
IN THE COUNTRY WE PROVIDE CRITICAL SUPPORT TO SEVERAL DC
COLLABORATIVE AND EVEN THOUGH WE HAVE A NATIONAL PROFILE OUR
PRIORITY IS AND ALWAYS HAS BEEN OUR WORK HERE WITH THE
COLLABORATIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO .
SAN FRANCISCO IS OUR HOME AND IT'S OUR COMMUNITY.
IT'S ALSO BECAUSE OVER THE COURSE THE LAST 25 YEARS SINCE
WE WERE FOUNDED AND THE LAST 11 WHICH WERE THROUGH THE
COLLABORATIVE WE'VE PIONEERED ADVANCES IN ASYLUM LAW BY
LITIGATING KEY CASES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, SETTING
CRITICAL PRECEDENT AND CREATING A MODEL FOR THE REST OF THE
COUNTRY. AND THIS HAS BEEN ESPECIALLY
TRUE IN THE CASE OF SECURING ASYLUM PROTECTIONS FOR
SURVIVORS OF SEXUAL AND GENDER BASED VIOLENCE AND DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE WHICH IS SOMETHING THAT IN PARTICULAR THE TRUMP
ADMINISTRATION HAS SET ITS SIGHTS ON OBLITERATING
INVESTING IN THIS COLLABORATIVE OF LEGAL TALENT REALLY COULDN'T
BE MORE CRITICAL THAN AT THIS MOMENT AS I'VE HEARD FROM
OTHERS IN THE FACE OF FEDERAL CUTS AND AGGRESSION FEAR
MONGERING UNCONSTITUTIONAL RAIDS, DEPRIVATIONS OF RIGHTS,
FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS AND UNMITIGATED CAMPAIGNS OF
DISINFORMATION AND MAL INFORMATION COMING FROM THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT AND HIS CRONIES AS WELL AS THE YET TO
BE FULLY REALIZED SURGE OF MASK AGENTS ARBITRARILY ABDUCTING
OUR NEIGHBORS OFF OUR STREETS. IT'S ESSENTIAL THAT WE FORTIFY
OUR CORE OF TRAINED AND COMMITTED ADVOCATES TO
SUPPORT AND DEFEND THE RIGHTS OF THE MOST VULNERABLE MEMBERS
OF OUR COMMUNITY. >> THANKS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
THANK YOU. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS YESENIA LACAYO AND I'M HERE WITH MISSION
ACTION AS I FILE AND RAPID RESPONSE NETWORK.
AND I'M ALSO A CONSTITUENT OF DISTRICT NINE.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR CONTINUOUSLY HOLDING SPACE
FOR US HERE. I'M HERE TO SUPPORT FOR THE 3.5
MILLION SUPPLEMENT OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO IS UNDER PRESSURE RIGHT NOW AND WE NEED THIS
BOARD TO ACTIVELY STAND WITH US NOT JUST IN WORDS BUT IN ACTION
WHEN SOMETHING HAPPENS AN ICE PICK UP A FAMILY IN CRISIS
SOMEONE NEWLY ARRIVED WITH NOWHERE TO NOWHERE SAFE TO
SLEEP. IT IS COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS
WHO ANSWER THE PHONE AT TWO IN THE MORNING, FIND EMERGENCY
HOUSING, SEND LEGAL HELP AND KEEP FAMILIES TOGETHER.
WE DO THAT WORK EVERY SINGLE DAY.
WE'RE ASKING THE CITY TO MEET THE SAME LEVEL OF URGENCY.
SOME COMMITMENTS WE NEED CONTINUE TO PUBLICLY
AND CONSISTENTLY DEFEND SAN FRANCISCO'S SANCTUARY VALUES
THAT THIS BOARD WILL NOT COLLABORATE WITH ICE AND THAT
IMMIGRANT FAMILIES SHOULD NOT BE AFRAID TO ACCESS SERVICES,
GO TO COURT OR ASK FOR HELP PROTECT AND EXPAND FUNDING FOR
IMMIGRANT RESPONSE, LEGAL DEFENSE, RAPID RESPONSE
LANGUAGE ACCESS AND EMERGENCY HOUSING.
PLEASE DO NOT CUT THOSE DOLLARS.
INVEST IN THEM. TREAT IMMIGRANT HOUSING AS PART
OF PUBLIC SAFETY. PEOPLE ARE ARRIVING HERE
AND SLEEPING IN CRISIS CONDITIONS.
WE SHOULD BE OFFERING SAFE PLACEMENTS ROOTED IN DIGNITY
NOT SWEEPS. IF YOU CALL THIS A SANCTUARY
CITY PEOPLE SHOULD ACTUALLY BE ABLE TO FIND SANCTUARY HERE.
I ALSO WANT TO REMIND YOU THAT THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS
HAVE ALREADY TAKEN TO THE STREETS IN THE MISSION THIS
YEAR TO SAY WE WILL DEFEND OUR IMMIGRANT NEIGHBORS AND WE
EXPECT OUR CITY TO DO THE SAME. OUR MESSAGE TO YOU IS SIMPLE NO
COLLABORATION WITH THIS ONE COMMUNITY DEFENSE HOUSE
AND PROTECT IMMIGRANT FAMILIES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I'LL CLOSE WITH THIS. IMMIGRANTS ARE NOT A TALKING
POINT IN SAN FRANCISCO. WE ARE THE WORKERS KEEPING THE
CITY RUNNING, THE PARENTS KEEPING THE SCHOOLS ALIVE
AND THE TENANTS HOLDING NEIGHBORHOODS TOGETHER.
WE'RE ASKING YOU TO SHOW UP FOR US THE WAY WE SHOW UP FOR THIS
CITY. >> LACK OF MONEY THAT
IMMIGRANTS AND OF SOLAR AND WE EXPECT THE CITY TO STAND WITH
US. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
HI. A SUPERVISOR THIS IS JOSE.
I'M THE IMMIGRANT RIGHT PROGRAM MANAGER AT CHINESE FOR
PROTECTION S.A. AND I SERVE ON THE IMMIGRANT RIGHTS
COMMISSION. THANK YOU EARLIER FOR YOUR
APPOINTMENT TO THE COMMISSION'S HERE TODAY.
>> I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF CIA CHINESE FOR INDUCTION
AND YOU KNOW WE ARE ALSO PART OF THE CENSUS OF IMMIGRANT
LEGAL EDUCATION NETWORK OF IRELAND AND SERVICES ARE RAPID
RESPONSE NETWORK. FIRST OF ALL I WOULD LIKE TO
THANK THE BOARD ESPECIALLY SUPERVISOR FUTURE BUDGET CHAIR
SOME OF HER CHAN'S THE LEADERSHIP IN SECURING THE
BUDGET SUPPLEMENTARY TO FUND OUR CITY'S IMMIGRANT RIGHT
COLLABORATIVE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT LEGAL EDUCATION
NETWORK S.F. ROTC. SO THIS IS OUR WEAPON RESPONSE
NETWORK FOR THE MUCH NEEDED FUNDING TO EXPAND OUR CAPACITY
TO SERVE OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY ACROSS THE CITY.
THIS ADDITIONAL FUNDING ALLOW US TO STRENGTHEN PROTECTION FOR
IMMIGRANTS INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO INCREASING SUPPORT
FOR COMMUNITY FRIENDS. I WORK THROUGH THE LOCAL RAPID
RESPONSE NETWORK TO FUND OUR IMMIGRATION LEGAL SERVICE AS
ARTICULATED BY MY COLLEAGUES PREVIOUSLY AND ALSO OUR
COMMUNITY EDUCATION. NORIA RIGHT WORKSHOP
AND EDUCATION ARE WHICH JUST PAST WEEK YOU KNOW I WAS
WALKING CHINATOWN WITH OUR SUPERVISOR, YOU KNOW SO AS A
STARTER HERE IN CHINATOWN COMMUNICATE WITH OUR COMMUNITY
ABOUT OUR RIGHTS IN CASE OF IMMIGRATION RAIDS HAPPENING
IN OUR CITY. SO WE'VE ARE CONSISTENTLY
CHANGING IMMIGRATION LAW AND THE LANDSCAPE AND HYPHEN
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT. THE NEED IS ONGOING BECAUSE THE
FEDERAL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT AND DETENTION OF OUR CENSUS OR
RESIDENT WERE KNOCK STOP WITHIN A SIX MONTHS.
SO THAT'S WHY WE URGE SUPPORT TO CONTINUE TO ENSURE OUR CITY
IS FULLY EQUIPPED AND HAVE THE INFRASTRUCTURE TO PROVIDE
URGENTLY NEEDED SERVICES TO OUR RESIDENTS.
>> THANK YOU FOR HER SUPPORT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS MOLLY ATKINSON.
I'M WITH THE JUSTICE AND DIVERSITY CENTER OF THE BAR
ASSOCIATION OF SAN FRANCISCO AND WE ARE THE LEGAL LEAD FOR
THE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT LEGAL DEFENSE COLLABORATIVE.
I WANT TO THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR SUPPORT OF THIS BUDGET
SUPPLEMENTAL TO INCREASE LEGAL SERVICES AND AND IMMIGRATION
FOR SAN FRANCISCANS AND JUST LIKE OUR CLIENTS ARE AFRAID TO
GO TO SCHOOL, AFRAID TO LEAVE THE HOUSE, AFRAID TO GO TO
WORK, THEY'RE AFRAID TO COME HERE AND MAKE PUBLIC COMMENT.
SO I'D LIKE TO READ A MESSAGE FROM ONE OF OUR CLIENTS WHO WAS
DETAINED AT THE IMMIGRATION COURT IN SEPTEMBER.
I WANT TO EXPRESS MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE FOR THE DEDICATION
PROFESSIONALISM AND COMMITMENT WITH WHICH YOU HANDLED MY LEGAL
DEFENSE. YOUR WORK WAS CRUCIAL
IN ACHIEVING MY RELEASE, WHICH REPRESENTS NOT ONLY THE
RECOVERY OF MY FREEDOM BUT ALSO THE POSSIBILITY OF BEING WITH
MY FAMILY AGAIN AFTER AN EXTREMELY PAINFUL PERIOD IT WAS
VERY DIFFICULT FOR ME TO HAVE BEEN DETAINED IN IMMIGRATION
COURT AS I HAVE ALWAYS SOUGHT TO LIVE RIGHTEOUSLY AND COMPLY
WITH THE LAW. THIS SITUATION AFFECTED ME
DEEPLY ON AN EMOTIONAL LEVEL AS BEING AWAY FROM MY FAMILY
ESPECIALLY FOR MY SON WITHOUT KNOWING HOW HE WAS OR BEING
ABLE TO ACCOMPANY HIM IN HIS DAILY LIFE WAS A VERY HEAVY
BURDEN TO BEAR. I CAME TO THE UNITED STATES
HOPING TO FIND THE FREEDOM TO FULLY LIVE MY SEXUAL
ORIENTATION AS A LESBIAN WOMAN IN AN ENVIRONMENT WHERE I COULD
BE RESPECTED AND AUTHENTIC. THANKS TO YOUR COMMITMENT
AND STEADFAST FASTNESS TO DEFEND MY RIGHTS TODAY I HAVE
THE OPPORTUNITY TO REUNITE WITH MY LOVED ONES AND TO CONTINUE
MY LIFE WITH THE DIGNITY AND FREEDOM I HAVE ALWAYS
LONGED FOR. I'M AWARE THAT THERE WILL STILL
BE MORE LEGAL PROCEEDINGS AHEAD.
HOWEVER, I HAVE FULL CONFIDENCE IN YOUR ABILITY AND IN THE
PROFESSIONALISM WITH WHICH YOU WILL CONTINUE TO REPRESENT ME.
KNOWING THAT I HAVE YOUR SUPPORT GIVES ME PEACE OF MIND
AND STRENGTH TO FACE WHAT COMES AHEAD.
I DO NOT HAVE ENOUGH WORDS TO EXPRESS THE RELIEF
AND GRATITUDE I FEEL FOR WHAT YOU HAVE DONE FOR ME.
I WILL ALWAYS REMEMBER WITH RESPECT AND ADMIRATION YOUR
WORK AS WELL AS THE TRUST YOU GAVE ME IN THE MOST DIFFICULT
MOMENTS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> I'M DISTRICT 11. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS STEPHANIE MOONEY AND I'M AN ATTORNEY WITH THE
UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRATION DEPORTATION DEFENSE
CLINIC. WE ARE ALSO PART OF THE SFO DC
COLLABORATIVE. WE PARTICIPATE IN ATTORNEY OF
THE DAY PROGRAMS AND WE REPRESENT MANY FAMILIES HERE
IN THE BAY. LIKE MY COLLEAGUES TODAY, WE
STRONGLY URGE YOU TO INCREASE FUNDING FOR IMMIGRANT LEGAL
SERVICES AT THIS TIME OF HEIGHTENED ICE ENFORCEMENT.
THE DEMANDS ON OUR CLINIC HAVE INCREASED ON A DAILY BASIS
GIVEN THE NEW ADMINISTRATION SO AGAIN WE JUST ASK YOU TO
INCREASE OUR FUNDING SO THAT WE CAN CONTINUE TO PROVIDE LEGAL
SERVICES TO THE IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
BEFORE THE LAST SPEAKER IN LINE SPEAKS IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO'D LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT, NOW IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO GET
UP AND GET IN LINE OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST SPEAKER
WELCOME SIR OR THE SUPERVISORS AND MAYOR OFFICE OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THE TITLE OF MY SPEECH IS
BEAUTY IS IN THE EYES OF THE BEHOLDER.
MY MOM WAS BORN IN 1942. SHE WAS AMONG THE SIX KIDS OF
HER PARENTS. AS A RESULT I HAVE THREE UNCLES
AND TWO AUNT. BUT MY MOM BEING THE OLDEST.
WHEN MOM WAS TEN MY GRANDPA DIED OF OPIATE ADDICTION.
SHE CRIED FOR A YEAR BECAUSE MY GRANDMA WAS ILLITERATE.
I SAW HER DUTIES AS A HOUSEWIFE.
SHE OFFERED NO SENSE OF CONTROL TO BRING HER CAUSE UP.
MY MOM HAD TO CARRY THE WEIGHT OF CARING THREE UNCLES AND TWO
OF MY AUNT. I WAS BORN IN 1972 IN THE
VIETNAM WAR WHICH HAS CLIMAXED THE VIETNAMESE AS AN ALL FLED
THEIR LIVES. ALONG WITH TWO SIBLINGS AND ONE
COUSIN GAIL WERE THE YOUNGEST OF LONG BOAT PEOPLE WHO ESCAPED
FROM VIETNAM TO MALAYSIA AS REFUGEES.
HOW IS THAT POSSIBLE? ALTHOUGH MY UNCLE AND MY DAD
WERE ALWAYS HIDING DUE TO WAR CONSTRICTION, MY DAD INVENTED
MACHINES TO MAKE BUTTONS. EVERY DAY MY MOM WOULD GO TO A
FLEA MARKET AND SELL BAGS AND BAGS A BUTTON.
EVENTUALLY MY MOM MY DAD INVENTED MACHINES TO MAKE
CHRISTMAS LIGHTS. MY MOM BECAME ONE OF THE MOST
WEALTHIEST AND MALE POWERFUL WOMEN FIGURES IN VIETNAM.
SHE SINGLE HANDEDLY BROUGHT 100 PEOPLE IN A BOAT ESCAPE TO
CHINA TO THE SHORES OF MALAYSIA.
WHAT DROVE HER TO LEAVE THE ANSWERS TO PAIN OF STAYING
OUTSTRIP THE PAIN OF LIVING. SO THAT'S WHY SHE MADE THE
DIFFICULT CHOICE. ALL HER CHOICE BOILS DOWN TO ME
BEING THE OLDEST KID. SHE KNEW I HAVE NO VIABLE
FUTURE IN A WAR TORN COUNTRY. WHEN ASKED IN 2005 WHEN SHE HAD
MADE THE SAME DECISION YOU HAD TO KNOW THE PEARLS OF THE SEA.
WE'VE ALL SINCE SHE SAYS NO. IT WAS DUMB MISCALCULATE IDEA
THE ODDS WERE THE ANSWER. SO IN 2021, THREE MONTHS AFTER
MY MOM'S PASSING I HAVE LUNCH OF MAGGIE AND THAT SHE WAS NOT
READY TO GET MARRIED. HOWEVER SHE OPENS IDEA TO WAY
OF CARING MISSED CHINESE INTERNATIONAL.
SO I SO I SAID I WAS AFRAID TO BE WRONG THINK BIGGER.
THE LEVERAGE IS TOP UBER DRIVER.
I'M HERE TO CLAIM A STAKE AS I'M HERE TO DELIVER THE
WORLDWIDE CONSTITUTION TO JOE BIDEN ANNOUNCED ALLIANCE 22
AND IT'S NATIONAL. >> WHY THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO'D LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD? ALL RIGHT.
MR. PRESIDENT. >> >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> UH, MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE
WILL SKIP OVER THE CLOSED SESSION FOR NOW.
TAKE THAT AT THE END OF THE MEETING.
PLEASE CALL HOUR FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
AGENDA ITEMS 36 THROUGH 47. >> YES THESE ITEMS WERE
INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY CAN I SUPPER ITEM 38 38.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN 38. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT I LIKE TO SEVEN ITEM 4640 SIX.
ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE BALANCE OF
THE ITEMS? >> YES.
THAT WOULD BE ITEMS 36 WE HAVE 737 AND 38 ONLY 3638 WITH
SEVEN. OKAY SO THEN 36, 37, 39 THROUGH
45 -46 I BELIEVE THAT'S 247. >> YEP.
OKAY. SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MARK MODE MONUMENT I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MANAGEMENT
I SUPERVISOR MILKER MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SORTER SORTER I
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EITHER ARE TONIGHT WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 38 38 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE MONTH OF OCTOBER 2025 AS
FILIPINO AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH AND TO CELEBRATE THE HISTORY
AND CULTURE OF FILIPINO AMERICANS AND THEIR IMMENSE
CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I AND BEFORE I CALL ON SUPERVISOR DORSEY I SHOULD HAVE
SAID THAT THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. OKAY AND NOW SUPERVISOR DORSEY
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELSON AND THANKS TO MY COLLEAGUES FOR
YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THIS RESOLUTION.
EACH OCTOBER WE HAVE THE HONOR OF CELEBRATING THE HISTORY
AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF OUR FILIPINO COMMUNITY AND I'M
PROUD TO REPRESENT THE FILIPINO CULTURAL HERITAGE DISTRICT AS
WELL AS MANY FILIPINO COMMUNITY SERVING ORGANIZATIONS
AND BUSINESSES IN DISTRICT SIX. WE'VE OFTEN HEARD IT SAID
PREVIOUSLY BY OUR FORMER COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR ARTHUR
SAFAI AND NOW BY SUPERVISOR CHEYENNE CHEN THAT DISTRICT SIX
AND DISTRICT 11 HAVE A SPECIAL CONNECTION THROUGH OUR FILIPINO
COMMUNITY. I REPRESENT THE CULTURAL HOME
OF SAN FRANCISCO'S FILIPINO COMMUNITY AND AS THE DISTRICT
SIX SUPERVISOR AND DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR REPRESENTS BY FAR
THE LARGEST POPULATION OF SAN FRANCISCO'S FILIPINO COMMUNITY.
AS ANY OF US WILL TELL YOU, THIS IS AN EXTRAORDINARILY
EXTRAORDINARY AND RESILIENT COMMUNITY WITH A DEEP HISTORY
IN OUR CITY, STATE AND NATION. FROM FILIPINO AMERICANS
ACTIVISM LOCALLY IN THE 1970S TO SAVE THE EYE HOTEL AND THEIR
CONTINUED ACTIVISM HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO EVER SINCE TO
FILIPINO AMERICANS FOUNDATIONAL ROLE IN CALIFORNIA'S FARM LABOR
MOVEMENT FOR BETTER WAGES AND WORKING CONDITIONS FORGING
CROSS-RACIAL SOLIDARY ITY IN THE LABOR MOVEMENT THAT
STILL ENDURES TO THE EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE FILIPINO
AMERICANS BRAVELY EXTENDED TO THE U.S. MILITARY MOST FAMOUSLY
IN WORLD WAR TWO. BUT HISTORICALLY AS FAR BACK AS
THE CIVIL WAR UP TO AND INCLUDING TODAY OUR
FILIPINO-AMERICAN COMMUNITY CARRIES A SPIRIT OF SERVICE
AND CARE FOR OTHERS WHICH SHINES THROUGH ITS PRESENCE
IN SO MANY PROFESSIONS FROM LEADERS WHO INCLUDE
CALIFORNIA'S ATTORNEY GENERAL AND ITS FORMER CHIEF JUSTICE TO
HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONALS AND CLERGY AND PEOPLE OF FAITH
ARTISTS, ADVOCATES, COMMUNITY STEWARDS.
I WANT TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION FOR THE WORK THAT
NONPROFIT PARTNERS ESPECIALLY DO TO SERVE AND UPLIFT OUR
FILIPINO COMMUNITY BUT IN PARTICULAR THOSE
ORGANIZATIONS SERVING FILIPINO IMMIGRANTS IN OUR CITY.
AND I KNOW WE HEARD A LOT OF THAT FROM FOLKS IN PUBLIC
COMMENT. THAT WORK HAS NEVER BEEN MORE
CRUCIAL THAN IT IS RIGHT NOW WITH IMMIGRANTS UNDER ATTACK
AND LIVING IN FEAR AS THEY NEVER HAVE BEFORE IN OUR
HISTORY. EARLIER TODAY SUPERVISORS CHEN
SORTER, CHERYL AND MYSELF HOSTED A RECEPTION THAT
FEATURED FOOD FROM DISTRICT SIX HIS OWN JT RESTAURANT, ONE OF
THE MANY INCREDIBLE FILIPINO OWNED BUSINESSES IN OUR CITY.
OUR THANKS TO JT AND TESS. THANK YOU TO MY CO-SPONSORS FOR
TAKING PART IN THIS ANNUAL CELEBRATION.
AND THANKS TO THE FILIPINO AMERICAN COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR ALL THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS THAT CONTINUE TO
ENRICH OUR CITY. >> MY BOY, THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU.
PRESS AMENDMENT FOR THE FILIPINO AMERICAN HISTORY MONTH
IS A TIME FOR US TO HONOR THE RICH CULTURE, VIBRANT
TRADITIONS AND LONGSTANDING RESILIENCE OF OUR COMMUNITY.
DISTRICT 11 HAS A VIBRANT FILIPINO COMMUNITY THRIVING
WITH CULTURALLY AND HISTORICALLY RELEVANT
EDUCATION PROGRAMS FILIPINO OWNED SMALL BUSINESS
AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATION LIKE THE FILIPINO COMMUNITY CENTER
FCC. >> THEY ARE DOING GREAT WORK TO
INVEST IN SUPPORT AND UPLIFT OUR FILIPINO YOUTH AND I'M SO
PROUD TO RECOGNIZE AND UPLIFT THE CONTRIBUTIONS FILIPINO
AMERICANS HAVE MADE TO THE CITY AND RECOGNIZED THE LEGACY OF
RESISTANCE, COMPASSION AND COMMUNITY CONNECTIVITY.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, I WOULD LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A
CO-SPONSOR. >> ALL RIGHT.
MADAM CLERK, YOU CAN NOTE THAT AND I BELIEVE THAT WE CAN TAKE
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION THE RESOLUTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 46.
>> ITEM 36. 4046.
EXCUSE ME, MR. PRESIDENT. YES?
THIS ITEM IS A RESOLUTION THAT URGES THE SAN FRANCISCO
MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT TO ENFORCE THE PROHIBITIONS OF RIDING ELECTRIC
AND GAS POWERED SCOOTERS ON SIDEWALKS IN ORDER TO PROTECT
PEDESTRIANS AND ADVANCE VISION ZERO GOALS.
SEE AS WELL. THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM
AND COLLEAGUES. I JUST WANT TO SAY ONE THANK
YOU TO EVERYONE WHO CO-SPONSORED THIS RESOLUTION
CALLING FOR MOTORIZED SCOOTER ENFORCEMENT ON SIDEWALKS
IN ORDER TO PROTECT PROTECT PEDESTRIANS AND KEEP PEOPLE
SAFE. >> OUR SIDEWALKS ARE WHERE
EVERYONE WALKS WHETHER THEY'RE SENIORS, CHILDREN, FAMILIES,
PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES INCLUDING THOSE WHO USE
WHEELCHAIRS NEED TO FEEL SAFE TO MOVE ABOUT.
>> ALSO JUST WANT TO CLEAR SOMETHING UP.
THIS RESOLUTION IS SPECIFIC TO MOTORIZED SCOOTERS AND GAS
POWERED SCOOTERS BUT THERE'S ALREADY LAWS ON THE BOOKS THAT
PROHIBIT CYCLING ON SIDEWALKS AND OTHER FORMS OF
TRANSPORTATION THAT HAVE BEEN BANNED ON OUR SIDEWALKS.
>> AND SO THOSE LAWS ALREADY EXIST.
SO I WANT PEOPLE TO KNOW THAT WE'RE FOCUSED ON ENFORCING LAWS
ALREADY ON THE BOOKS. WE ARE CURRENTLY WORKING WITH
THE CITY ATTORNEY TO EXPLORE POTENTIAL LEGISLATIVE OPTIONS
TO IMPROVE ENFORCEMENT. CURRENTLY STATE LAW BANS
SCOOTERS ON SIDEWALKS AND AT PRESENT THESE VIOLATIONS ARE
CLASSIFIED AS MOVING VIOLATIONS WHICH MEANS ONLY S.F. PD IS
AUTHORIZED TO ISSUE CITATIONS. WE ARE REVIEWING WHETHER THERE
ARE WAYS TO EXPAND ENFORCEMENT AUTHORITY OR OTHERWISE
STRENGTHEN COMPLIANCE MECHANISMS TO ADDRESS THIS
CONCERN. EVERYONE RIDERS, DRIVERS
AND PEDESTRIANS DOES SHARE RESPONSIBILITY FOR KEEPING OUR
CITY SAFE. WE CAN SUPPORT NEW FORMS OF
MOBILITY BUT NEVER AT THE EXPENSE OF THOSE WHO WALK OR
USE THEIR WHEELCHAIRS OR OTHER DEVICES THAT ARE LEGITIMATE ON
OUR SIDEWALKS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. ROSA WALTON.
LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK. COULD YOU PLEASE TAKE US TO THE
CLOSED SESSION MATTER ITEM 35. >> YES.
GIVEN THAT ITEM 47 HAS BEEN APPROVED THE MOTION THAT THE
BOARD CONVENE IN CLOSED SESSION ON OCTOBER 28TH.
WE ARE NOW GOING TO READ THE TITLE OF THE CLOSED SESSION
IN ITS ENTIRETY MOSTLY THE CLOSED SESSION FOR THE BOARD TO
CONVENE TODAY OCTOBER 28TH FOR THE PURPOSE OF CONFERRING WITH
OR RECEIVING ADVICE FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY REGARDING THE
FOLLOWING EXISTING LITIGATION MATTERS THERE ARE VARIOUS
MATTERS AGAINST DONALD TRUMP IN WHICH THE CITY IS A PARTY.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
AND WE WILL NOW ASK THAT MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC PUBLIC
EXIT THE CHAMBER WHILE WE GO INTO CLOSED SESSION.
WE'RE GOING TO RESUME THE MEETING IN OPEN SESSION AFTER
WE CONCLUDE MADAM CLERK, PLEASE LET US KNOW WHEN THE CHAMBER IS
READY. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT
. S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO
GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
AMAZON CISCO FOR YOUR WATCHING GOLDEN GATE ADVENTURES WITH
LIGHTWEIGHT HORSES ALL IN THIS EPISODE IS EXPLORING GOLDEN
GATE PARK. >> HI I'M MICHAEL BALTHAZAR
AND YOU'RE WATCHING GOLDEN GATE ADVENTURES, A SHOW THAT
HIGHLIGHTS SAN FRANCISCO'S URBAN OUTDOORS.
TODAY WE'RE IN GOLDEN GATE PARKF .
WE'RE GOING TO HIGHLIGHT A FEW OF THE ACTIVITIES THEY HAVE
HERE. OFFIRST UP ARCHERY.
>> LET'S SHOOT SOME ROMERO ARROWS.
WE'RE HERE ATAD 47TH AND FULTON THE ARCHERY RANGE HERE GOLDEN
GATE PARK AND I'M HERE WITH MY FRIEND AAR JIM WHO IS AN EXPERTT
ARCHERY. HE'S GOING TO GIVE US A FEW
TIPS. FIRST OFF, LET'S SEE.
I THINK SAFETY IS REALLY IMPORTANT.
THAT'SYAN AN EXCELLENT IDEA. SO NUMBER ONE, JUSTSO WITH
ANYTHING LIKE ARCHERY, YOU WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT EVERYTHING IS
POINTED AT THE TARGETE. SO ONCE WE
HAVE AN ARROW ON THE BOW WE WOULDN'T WANT TO POINT
IT AT SOMEBODY. WE WOULD ALWAYS WANT TO MAKE
SURE THAT WHAT WE'RE DOING IS POINTED DOWNRANGE TOWARD THE
TARGET. >>HA SO NUMBER TWO IS THE NUMBER
ONE IS FOR MOSTLY FOR PROTECTING OTHER PEOPLE.
PROTECTING YOURSELF IS IMPORTANT TOO.
SO F YOU ALWAYS WANT TO USE A TAB
OR A GLOVE LIKE THE ONE YOU'RE WEARING FOR FINGER PROTECTION
WHEN DRAWING AND RELEASING THE STRING.
ALSO OUR ARMED GUARDS KEEP THE STRING FROM HITTING OUR ARMS ON
THE RELEASE. WHAT WE'RE USING TODAY IS A
VERY MODERN AND CONTEMPORARY RECURVE BOW.
SO COMPOUND LONG BOWS RE CURVES ARE ASIAN ASIATIC BOWS
MONGOLIAN JAPANESE. TURKISH.
SYRIAN. . VERY DISTINCTIVE SHAPES TOTALLY
DIFFERENTT FLAVORS OF ARCHERY JUST BASED ON LET'S TRY THIS.
ALLLE RIGHT. >> SO ARCHERY ISS ALL ABOUT
ACCURACY AS YOU TRY TO HIT THE TARGETO.
THEPO SPORTS ROOTS GO WAY BACK O HUNTING IN BATTLEFIELDS BUT
TODAY IT'S EVOLVED IUT INTO SOMETHING RECREATIONAL
AND COMPETITIVE. THIS RANGESORE IS IN A CHILL SPT
TUCKED INTO A PEACEFUL WOODED AREA ON THE WEST ENDCK OF THE
PARK T. >> THIS IS A LOT OF FUN GUYS
WHETHER YOU'RE JUST STARTING OUT OR ARE ALREADY A PRO IT'S
THE PERFECT PLACE TO PRACTICE. THERE ARE WELL-MAINTAINEDED
TARGET BALES AT DIFFERENT DISTANCES ALL SURROUNDED BY
TALL TREES AND LUSH GREENERYESES CREATING A CALM ATMOSPHERE.
THAT WAS A AWESOME .
I THINK WE'RE GONNAET GET BETTER THAN THAT, RIGHT?
WHY DON'T YOU GOHT TO THE RANGE IS RUN BY VOLUNTEERS AND IT'S
TOTALLY FREE TO USE BUT YOU'LL NEED TO BRING YOUR OWN GEAR OR
RENT SOME NEARBY. LOCALS AND TOURISTS LOVE IT
WHETHER THEY'RE HONING THEIR SKILLS OR JUST WANTING TO TRY
SOMETHING DIFFERENT OUTDOORS IN THE CITY T.
OH THAT WAS A BAD ONE. ARCHERY CAN BE VERY HUMBLING
AND NOT TOO BADAD. THISIT ONE'S A LITTLE HIGH
BECAUSE THAT WAS MY SECOND SHOT.
I COULDN'T REALLY I DIDN'T
REALLY FEEL THAT ONE AS WELL. BUT ONCE I GOT IT HONEDEDEL IN I
THINK I GOT ONE IN THE TEN. LET'S GOOT THAT WAY.
OH WOW.
FARTHER BACK. LEFTFT AGAIN.
JUST LEFT. OH, JUST TO THE T LEFT.
THAT'S THE RIGHT ELEVATION. I SAW THAT.
YOU GOT IT.T. OKAY.
LAUGHS SARAHAH YEAH, I VISUALIZE IT.
YEAH, YOU'RE RIGHT. >> THE LAST I GET OH, I WAS SO
CLOSE I LOOKED SO GOOD IN THE AIR.
>> ALL RIGHT, NEXT TIME. THAT'S I
WHY I GET TO COME OUT HERE TO PRACTICE.
THATAT WAS VERY EXHILARATING. I LOVE ARCHERY, MANG. TIM, WHY O
YOU LOVE ARCHERY? WHAT'S NOT TO LIKE?
YOU CAN DO WHAT WE JUST DID WHICH WAS SPEND TIME TOGETHER
EXPLORING IT AND WORKING ON IT. YOU CAN ALSO HAVEND A BLAST GOIG
OFF INTO THE WOODS BY YOURSELF. YOU KNOW THIS
RANGE ANY RANGE YOU CAN DO IT WITH FRIENDS YOU CAN DOO IT BY
YOURSELF. >> YOU CAN GET THE EXPERIENCE
YOU WANT FROM IT. THERE'S A LOT OF FUN AND I
THINK YOU Y GRORO FOR BEING MY N THIS ARCHERY.
THAT'S MY PLEASURE. IT'S GOODDHEMY TO SEE HIM LIKE Y
NOW WE'RE GOING TO GOO REALLY? >> NOW WE'RE AT THE BLUE HERON
BOATHOUSE. WE CAN GET A TWO DIFFERENT KINDS
OF BOATS. THERE'S ACTUALLY A PEDAL BOAT
AND A ROWBOAT .
I THINK WE'RE GOING TO GO GET A ROWBOAT.
LET'S GO GET ON THE LAKE. >> TIME TO ROW A BOAT.
BOATS. BOAT.
BOAT SURROUNDED BY GREENERY. >> THIS MANMADE LAKE IS A NICE
LITTLE ESCAPE FROM THE BUSY CITY.
TO GET INTO AIS RHYTHM AND MOVE IN SYNC WITH
THE WATER AND YOUR BOAT. IT CAN HAVEE A CALMING
MEDITATIVE FEEL WHILE STILL GIVING YOU A SERIOUSIO WORKOUT.
ALL RIGHT. >> HOW COOL IS THIS POOL?
LOOK HOW BIG THAT TREE IS. IT'S LIKE NICE AND PEACEFUL OUT
HERE. I'M THE O O ONLY ONE THAT MEANSI
THINK PEOPLE REALLY NEED TO COME OUT HEREEO C.
ACTUALLY, THEY REALLY COME OUTER HERE.
AS YOUAK NAVIGATE THE LAKE. YOU'LL PASS BYWB STRAWBERRY HILL
,AN ISLAND IN THE MIDDLE OF THE LAKE WITH A WATERFALL
TRAILS AND TONS OF WILDLIFE LIKE DUCKS, TURTLES AND BIRDS.
>> STRAWBERRY HILL IS CONNECTED BY TWO BRIDGES TO THE PARK.
AND IT'S THE HIGHEST POINT IN GOLDEN GATE PARK TS.
IT INCLUDES HUNTINGTON FALLS, A 110 FOOT TALL ARTIFICIAL
WATERFALL THAT FEEDS INTO THE
LAKEKE. THERE'S ALSO THE CHINESE
PAVILION, A GIFT FROM SAN FRANCISCO'S SISTER CITY.
TAIPEI, TAIWAN. IT'S A CHARMING PLACE TO REST
AND TAKE IN THE VIEWS I. OOH, THAT WAS A WORKOUT FOR THE
ARMS. I LOVE BOATING.
THAT'S A LOT OF FUN GETTING OUT ON THE LAKE.
'SBUT NOW I GOT TO LOOK AT THE LEGS.
LET'S GO. SKATETE WHERE THIS GAME PLAYS ON
STICKS AND FOAM. IT'S BEAUTIFUL DAY.
I THINK I'M GOING TO RENT SOME ROLLERBLADES.
ILET'S GET ROLLING. >> GET YOUR SKATES ON SKATES.
>> IF Y YOU'RE LOOKING FOR A FUN WAY TO SPEND A SUNNY AFTERNOON.
CHECK OUT THE GAMEPLAYEN HERE. IT'S NEAR SIXTH AVENUE
IN KENNEDY DRIVE AND HAS A GREAT SURFACE THAT'S PERFECT
FOR PRACTICING OR HANGING OUT WITH FELLOW SKATERSE
. OH MAN, THIS IS, UH THIS IS
VERY NOSTALGIC FOR THE MILLENNIAL AND ME 90S.
PLAYING WITH MY BOYS SOME STREET HOCKEY.
I HAVEN'T RIDDEN BLADES IN A WHILEID BUT IT'S TO BE LIKE
RIDING A BIKE. I LYEAH, RIGHT.
>> LET'S GO. HERE.
>> I'M HERE AT THE FREE SUNDAY ROLLER DISCO PARTY FROM
NOON TO 5 P.M..
THE GODFATHER ESCAPE BRINGSGS HS MOBILE DEEJAY UNIT AND PLAYS
GROOVY TUNES FOR YOU TO SKATE HERETE.
AND IF YOU NEED SKATES NO WORRIES.
NEARBY ARE AVAILABLE FROM 11 A.M. TO 6 P.M. ON THE
WEEKENDS STARTING IN JUST $12 AN HOUR FOR KIDS AND 20 FOR
EVERYONE ELSE. ALL RIGHT.
I'M A DANGEROUS MAN. THE SKATING PLACE HAS BEEN HERE
SINCE 1986 AND IT GOT A A FRESH IN 2022 WITH NEW
PAVEMENT AND A STUNNING MURAL BY LOCAL ARTIST AMYNN L DEVLIN.
>> THE MURAL CALLED PSYCHEDELIC GOLDEN GATE SKATE FEATURES A
COLORFUL DESIGN THAT CELEBRATES THE PARK'S ROLLER SKATING
HISTORYS. >> PLUS IT WAS CREATED
IN COLLABORATION WITH THE CHURCH OF EIGHT WHEELS, WHICH
IS ALL ABOUT KEEPING THE SKATING SPIRIT ALIVEVEL.
>> THIS IS FUN. I HAD NO IDEA THIS WAS OVER
HERE. SANNHE FRANCISCO HAS EVERYTHING
ALL RIGHT. >> SOME 2000 GETTING BACK ON
SOME ROLLER BLADES. IT'S LIKE BEING A LITTLE KID.
DTHIS IS GOLDEN GATE ADVENTURES. AND I'M MICHAEL BALTAZAR FROM
S.F. TV. I ITHANKS FOR WATCHING AND ANDR
TO TV DISTRICT TEN AND THE PLACE TO BE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY
TO REPRESENT THE LAST REAL BLACK COMMUNITY HEREE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WAS VERY IMPORTANT TO ME NOT ONLY JUSTAC THE BLACK
COMMUNITY BUT ALL THE COMMUNITIES OF COLOR THAT WE
HAVE IN DISTRICTCT TEN FROM BAYVIEW ON THIS POINT TO PATROL
HILL TO VISITATIONON IN VALLEY O DOGPATCH TO LITTLE HOLLYWOOD
AND SO MY FAMILY ORIGINALLY MIGRATED FROM LOUISIANAMI
AND THEY CAME AND SETTLED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
MY GRANDFATHER WORKED ON THE SHIPYARD.
I HAD GREAT UNCLES AND AUNTS WHO EITHER WORKED IN THE
SHIPYARD OR THEY DID SOME DOMESTIC WORK FOR OTHER
FAMILIES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO MOST OF MY ENTIRE LIFE IT WAS
JUST MY MOTHER AND I AND SO I WAS RAISED BY A SINGLE MOM,
SINGLE PARENT FAMILY. MY MOM AND I LIVED IN WEST
POINT WITH MY GRANDMOTHER.
WE ALSO STAY WITH MY AUNT AND PATROL HERE AND THAT'S
WHERE I SPENT MY EARLY YEARS IN SAN FRANCISCO AS WELL AS
ALSO SPENDINGANME SOME TIME LIVG IN THE HEAT.
WELL, IT WAS IMPORTANT TO METO F BECOME THE SUPERVISOR OF
DISTRICT TEN FOR SO MANY DIFFERENT REASONS.
ONE IS THE PLACE WHERE I'M ORIGINALLY FROM.
IT'S THE PLACE WHEREWH I ACTUALY HAD MY BIGGEST OPPORTUNITY
AFTER GRADUATING FROM COLLEGE COMING AND WORKING AS THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF YOUNG COMMUNITY DEVELOPERSS AND HAVING
THE OPPORTUNITY TO RUN FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORSRS AND BE
ABLE TO AFFECT POLICY, AFFECT CHANGE IN THE VERY COMMUNITY
WHERE MY FAMILY IS FROM. >> MY NAME ISS KELLY MCCORD
AND I AM THE OWNER MANAGER ALONG WITH MY HUSBAND KEN OF
MISSION BLUE MISSION BLUE REALLYUE WE'RE NEIGHBORS FIRST
AND SO WHEN WE FIRST CAME TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD WE ENTERED THEE
STORY, WE GOT INVOLVED AND WE LEARNED THAT THERE WAS AN
OPPORTUNITY TO GETTO IT PLUGGED IN TO THE MERCHANT CORRIDOR
AND SO WE SEE MISSION BLUE IS KIND OF SETTING THE TABLE FOR
THE COMMUNITY TO COME TOGETHER AROUND GOOD COFFEE, GOOD
PASTRIES AND ARTISAN GIFTS. >> SO WHEN WE MOVED TO THE
NEIGHBORHOOD WE WERE VOLUNTEERING IN THE THE GARDENS
HERE THE BEAUTIFUL GREENWAYS AND THEREHO WAS JUST SO MANY
BUTTERFLIES AND I JUST ASKED WHAT'S THE BUTTERFLY OF THIS
AREA? AND FRAN MARTIN SAYS THE
MISSION BLUE AND WE SAID WELL IF WE EVER OPEN ANYTHING WE'RE
GOING TO CALL IT MISSION BLUE SOMETHING BECAUSE I WAS IN A
CHRYSALIS PHASE AND BECAUSE THE NEIGHBORHOOD WAS ALREADY SO
BEAUTIFUL AND WE WANTED TO BE A PART OF THE BECOMING ALONGNG WIH
THE NEIGHBORHOOD SOMETHING BEAUTIFUL AND WE WANTED TO ADD
VALUE TOAD TH THAT BEAUTY.
ONE OF THE GREAT GREAT HIDDEN SECRETS OF THE VALLEY IS THAT
WE'RE WHERE THE CROSSTOWN TRAIL STARTS.
IF YOU'RE NOT FAMILIAR WITH CROSSTOWN TRAIL IT'S A 17 MILE
TRAIL THAT RUNS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO AND IT CUTS THROUGH
NOT ONLY OUR COMMERCIAL CORRIDOROR BUT THE GREENWAYS
AND THERE ARE SIX STACKED GARDENSS THAT WERE BUILT BY THE
NEIGHBORS FOR THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND THEY'VE BEEN HERE FOR OVER
THREE DECADES AND THEY'RE AN INCREDIBLE TREASURE.
THE ROLLING ROUTES FARMERS MARKETS ARRIVES IN OUR TRUCK
EVERY SATURDAY MORNINGNG AT 10 A.M. IN THE PLAZA AND THERE'S
FRUITS AND VEGETABLES AND THEY TAKE EB TEA.
IT'S ACCESSIBLE TOVE EVERY ONE F OUR NEIGHBORS.
SO WE HAVE OUR WHOLE NEIGHBORHOOD MEETING AND THE
GREENWAY FOR FRESH FRUITS AND VEGETABLES AND AROUND THAT
WE LOVE TO ASK OUR LOCAL MUSICIANS TO COME SO IT'S
REALLY LIKE A ECOSYSTEM OVER THERE ON SATURDAY MORNING WHICH
ISWH ONE OF OUR GOALS AND JUST WHAT A NEIGHBORHOOD IS ALL
ABOUT . >> MY NAME IS LISA RUSSELL
AND I TOLD HER OF SEFTON FOR WE'VE BEENE HERE GOING ON NINE
YEARS BEING THAT IT'S HERE IN VISITATION VALLEY WHERE I
LIVE IT'S A QUICKCK WALK TO WOR. >> IT'S VERY DIVERSE
AND EVERYONE IS FRIENDLY AND IT'S REWARDING GETTING TO
MEET A LOT OF NEW PEOPLE, A LOT OF DIFFERENT DOGS.
THEY LOVE ASKING HER SO THAT'S A GOOD THING.
WE'VE DONE A LOTOT HERE SINCE I'VEFF BEEN IN OFFICE.
WE OPEN ANOTHER GROCERY OUTLET, WE HAVE A NEW LUCKY STORE RIGHT
IN THE BAYVIEW PLAZA WHICH IS FACILITY THAT
WE'RE IN RIGHT NOW. 1550 EVANS THE BRAND NEW
SOUTHEAST COMMUNITY CENTER IS ANOTHER AMAZINGCE ACCOMPLISHMENT
FOR DISTRICT TEN IF YOU COME FROM VISITATION
VALLEY CROSS BAYSHORE AND COME INTO THIRD
STREET YOU'LL SEE A NICE BABY SIGN THAT DEMONSTRATES
AND REFLECTIVEFL OF ONE THAT YOU ARE COMING IN TO BABY ON THIS
POINT BUT ALSOT IT'S A IT'S AN ART PROJECT TO MAKE IT MORE
VISUALLY APPEALING WHEN YOU ENTER INTO OUR COMMUNITY I'M
BARBARA GRATATA AND I'M THE WINEMAKER AND OWNER OF GROTTO
WINES HERE IN BAYVIEW WE STARTED WINEMAKING AS A HOBBY
ACTUALLY AND IN OUR GARAGE HERE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD IN 2006
AND 2015 WE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO OPEN A TASTING ROOM WHICH WE
HAVE DONE IN THIS SPACECE AND HERE WE ARE WE'VE EXPANDED
A LITTLE BIT TO ADD IN FOOD OPTIONS AND CAFE LIKE
EXPERIENCE. I OPENED UP TO BUSINESS
IN BAYVIEW AND WAS INSPIRED BY THE COMMUNITY HAVING DONE A LOTY
OF POP UPS AND EVENTS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND WE HAD AMAZING
SUPPORT AND FELT LET'S TRY TO
TAKE THIS TO THE NEXT LEVEL AND THAT WAS REALLY WHAT SORT
OF DROVE US WAS THE SUPPORT THAT WE GOTTHTH FROM THE BAYVIEW
COMMUNITY. YOU CAN EXPECT TO GET A LOCAL
BAYVIEW HOSPITAL QUALITY AND WELCOME YOU'LL EXPERIENCE
WINE TASTING WITHOUT GOING TO THE WINE COUNTRY BECAUSE WE ARE
A SMALL PRODUCER AND WE HAVE NOTHA ONLY OUR WINES BUT WE'VE
INTRODUCED SOME ITALIAN VARIETIES AS WELL SO YOU CAN
SITSO AND ENJOY ALL OF THAT PLUS SOME COMFORT STYLE FOOD.
WELL MY NAME IS ANTHONY WOMACK, 24 YEARSC OLD AND THE OWNER OF
WESTERN SCOOP ICE CREAM HERE LOCATED IN THE BABY OF THE ME
AND MY SIBLINGS WERE YOUNGER. MY AUNT USED TORE TAKE US OUT TO
EAT ICE CREAM ALL THE TIME AND I WAS JUST LIKE OUR BONDING
TIME. WE SPEND HOURS JUST EATING ICE
CREAM AND TALKING AND CATCHING UP.
ONE DAY MY AUNT CAME TO ME WITH AN IDEA WHY DON'T YOU BRING ANN
SHOP BACK HERE TO THE BAYVIEW?
HASN'T BEEN ONE HERE IN SOME TIME SOMEWO I THOUGHT IT WOULD A
GOOD IDEA TO BRING SOMETHING BACK TO THE COMMUNITY WHERE I
GREW UP AT AND SOMETHING I HAVEN'T SEEN RECENTLY AS A NEW
BUSINESS COME BACK TO THE COMMUNITY I REALLY WANT TO
CREATE THAT ENVIRONMENT A SIT DOWN ENVIRONMENT WHERE YOU CAN
ENJOY A BANANA SPLITIT A ROOT BEER FLOW MILKSHAKE ETC. JUST
CREATING THAT ENVIRONMENT FOR PEOPLE TO COME IN AND ENJOY
PRETTY MUCH GOTOP THE PASSION TO DO IT FROM BEING HERE IN THE
COMMUNITY AND FROM MY FAMILY. THIS PAST BLACK HISTORY MONTH
WE CELEBRATE IT WITH THE PARADE THAT STARTED AT THE OPERA HOUSE
THAT CAME DOWN TO 15 50. EVANS SO AS WE TALK ABOUT
BEAUTIFICATION, AS WE TALK ABOUT PROMOTING THE ARTS, AS WE
TALK ABOUT THE CULTURE OF BAYVIEW FROM THIS POINT AND THE
THINGS THAT WE'VE BEEN DOING TO MAKE SURE THAT WE PRESERVE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR COMMUNITIES TO COME TOGETHER.
AND IT'S ALSOOAL A LARGER AMOUNT OF PEOPLE IN COMMUNITY THAT
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITYOU TO COME OUT AND SEE WHAT IS GOING ON
AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO DO THAT EVERY BLACK HISTORY MONTH TO
PROMOTE NOT ONLY OUR CORRIDOR HERE IN THE SOUTHEAST SECTOR TO
PROMOTE BLACK PEOPLE COMING TOGETHER DURING BLACK HISTORY
MONTH BUT ALSO TO JUST PUT ONER DISPLAY ALL OF THE TALENT, ALL
OF THE GREAT AND AMAZING RESIDENTSDE THAT WE HAVE HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT COME OUT TO SUPPORT AND PROMOTE BLACK
HISTORY DURING BLACK HISTORY MONTH THOUSAND FIVE MY NAME IS
LENA MILLS AND I'M THE OWNER OF CREATIVE IDEAS CATERING COFFEE
WHAT REALLYAT INSPIRED ME TO OPN MY OWN COMPANY IS BECAUSE I WAS
TIRED OF WORKING FOR SOMEBODY ELSE.
>> WE HAD COLUMBIA AND MEXICAN FOOD AND WITH OUR KID
IN BUSINESS WE HAVE ALL DIVERSE MENU FOR ANY OCCASION.
THE MENU ARMSTRONG EVERYTHING I LEARNED WHEN I WAS A KID
AND GROWING UP WITH MY FAMILY THEY ALWAYS WANTED TO COOK ALL
DIFFERENT THINGS AND SO I LEARNED HOW TO DO A LOT OF
THINGS THAT WE NOW DO HERE AT THE COFFEE DIVIDING DISTRICT
AND IT'S IT'S AMAZING BECAUSE WE'RE IN COMMUNICATION WITH
SUPERVISOR JAMAL WALTON ESPECIALLY WHEN HE DOES LIKE
COFFEEES. HE TALKS WITH EVERYBODY IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. YOU KNOW THATTTA WANTS TO TALK O
HIM AND ASK ABOUT HOW THINGS ARE GOING WITH OUR COMMUNITY.
RIGHT. AND WEHE WE GET TOGETHER WITH
OTHER BUSINESSES THAT HAS LIKE CLEANING THAT
IN DOING THATTH IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD YOU KNOW ON ON ON
OUR STREET IN PEOPLE SEE THAT THATTH ALL THE BUSINESSES GET
TOGETHER AND THEY KNOW WHAT WE WERE DOING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
WE OPEN FOR BREAKFAST WE OPEN FOR LUNCH WE HAVE A CONVENIENT
WE DO LOCAL EVENTS YOU KNOW WITHTH THE CHURCHES, WITH THE
SCHOOLS AT THE PARK AND AND ALSO WITH OTHER BUSINESSES
IN THE AREA. MY NAME IS TIM MINE AND I AM
THE OWNER OF CHRISTOPHER'S BOOKS IN SAN FRANCISCO TARHEELS
INDEPENDENT BOOKSTORE. WE'VE BEEN
HERE FOR 33 YEARS THAT BOOKSTORES HOUSED IN THE
VICTORIAN OWNED BY PETER LILIENTHAL WHO ALSO RUNS THE
PICTURE ARCHIVES PROJECT. THIS SPACE HAS BEEN USED FOR A
NUMBER OF DIFFERENT THINGS OVER OF THE PHARMACY BEING
ONE OF THEM. WHAT MAKES US UNIQUE IS THAT
THAT WE MAINTAIN THE ORIGINAL CHARACTER OF THE SPACE.
IF YOU LOOK UP HERE YOU SEE THE YOU KNOW, ANCIENT RETROFITTING
SO THESE LITTLE DRAWERS AND EVERYTHING THESE ARE THE
ORIGINAL FIXTURES OF WHAT WAS HERE IN THE EARLY 1920S OR SO.
ONE OF MY FAVORITE PARTS IS IS SITTING IN THAT CHAIR OUT FRONT
AND SAYING HELLO TO PEOPLE WHENO THEY COME IN.
AND ONE OF MY FAVORITE PARTS IS WHEN SOMEONE ASKED ME TO
RECOMMEND THE BOOK YOU HAVE HOME YOUOU HAVE WORK WELL A THID
PLACE IS A PLACE WHERE YOU LOOK FOR COMMUNITY AND YOU BUILD
COMMUNITYCO AND I THINK OF CHRISTOPHER'S AND OTHER
BUSINESSES LIKE THAT AS A THIRD PLACE.
YOU KNOW I'VE HAD KIDS WHO WHO COME IN THAT I KNEW WHEN THEY
WERE BORN AND THEY'VE COME IN AND INTRODUCED ME TO THEIR
KIDS. THAT'S HOW LONG I'VE BEEN HERER
. AND THAT FEELING OF OF HISTORY
AND CONNECTION AND FAMILY AND JUST BEING A SOLE
PROPRIETOR AND ONE OF THE MOST AMAZING CITIES IN THE WORLD YOU
KNOW I STILL ENJOY COMING TO WORK EVERY DAY.
YOU KNOW WE DEFINITELY HAVE A LOT OF AMAZING PLACES TO GO
HERE IN DISTRICT TEN WHETHER IT BE SOME OF THE BARS THAT HAVE
BEEN AROUND FOR10 DECADES IL PIRATA AND PETRO HILL BOTTOM OF
THE HILLOF CONNECTICUT YANKEE NW WE HAVE NEWER SPOTS
LIKE GUMBO SOCIAL CAFE OF THAT IS LOCATED
IN THE INDIA BASIN. I'M JUST SO EXCITED ABOUT ALLLL
OF THE THINGS THAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO DO BUT I WANTED TO MAKE
SURE THAT ASSO SUPERVISOR I REALLY ADDRESS THE CONCERNS
AND ISSUES THAT COMMUNITY HAD AND LEFT WITH TANGIBLE ASSETS
ON THE WAY OUT BUT ALSO WITH POLICIES IN PLACE THAT WILL
OUTLIVE ME AS A SUPERVISOR
IN SOME OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS IN DISTRICT EIGHT ARE THE
CASTRO GLEN PARK SNOWY VALLEY, DIAMOND HEIGHTS MISSION,
DOLORES AND POLE VALLEY. >> HELLO.
I AM RAFAEL MANDOLIN. I AMER THE SUPERVISOR
REPRESENTING DISTRICT EIGHT ON THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. I HAD ALWAYS BEEN INTERESTED
IN POLITICS AND PUBLIC LIFE AND I GREW UP IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND WHEN I WAS IN HIGH SCHOOL I HAD AN INTERNSHIP WORKING FOR A
SUPERVISOR I ON THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND AS I GOT
INVOLVED IN IN LOCAL AFFAIRS WHEN I WAS GROWING UP AT SOME
POINT IT SEEMED LIKE IT MADE SENSE TO TO RUN AND SO I DID.
SO WHEN I WAS RUNNING IN 2018 WE FOCUSED A LOT ON
HOMELESSNESS AND MENTAL HEALTH ISSUES AS PRIORITIES FOR ME
AND PRIORITIES FOR THE DISTRICTT IN THE CITY.
MY MOM SUFFERED FROM MENTAL ILLNESS FOR A BIG CHUNK OF HER
ADULT LIFE AND SHE STARTED GETTING SICKTY WHEN I WAS MORE
VERY SICK WHEN I WAS 10 OR 11 YEARS OLD I MOVED UP TO SAN 1
FRANCISCO BECAUSE SHE WASN'T ABLE O TO TAKE CARE OF ME ANYMOE
AND I HAD A GRANDMOTHER UP HERE BUT I YOU KNOW OF COURSE
CONTINUED TO FOLLOW HER LIFE AND AS I COULD TRY TO HELP HERAN
OUTLO BUT SHE SHE HAD A ROUGH SECOND HALF TO HER LIFE.
SHETI LIVED IN INSTITUTIONS AND BOARD CARES.
SHE WAS IN A HOMELESS SHELTER FOR A PERIOD
NSRD OF TIME AND I SAW, YOU KNOW, THAT THERE ARE FOLKS
WITH THESE SIGNIFICANT NEEDS AND I THINK THAT HAS INFORMED
MY APPROACH TO GOVERNANCE AND MY PRIORITIES AS A AS AN
ELECTED OFFICIAL LAST YEAR THE GOVERNOR NEWSOM AND SENATOR
EGGMAN AND THE STATE SENATE AND ASSEMBLY ONE WOMAN IRWIN
WORK TO PUT PROPOSITION ONE ON THE BALLOT IN MARCH AND THAT'S
A BIGE INVESTMENT IN IN HOUSING AND TREATMENT FOR PEOPLE WITH
SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESS. PROPOSITION ONE DOES A COUPLE
OF BIG THINGSS. ONE IS IT IS A VERY LARGE BOND
$6.5 BILLION FOR HOUSING BEDS,S, PLACEMENT LOCKED AND UNLOCKED
FACILITIES FOR PEOPLE WITH SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESSAC.
THAT'S IMPORTANT BECAUSE WE HAVEN'T HAD THOSE KINDS OF
FUNDSS AVAILABLE FOR THAT AND OF COURSE WE USED TO HAVE STATE
MENTAL HOSPITALS. WE'VE LARGELY CLOSED THOSE.
WE HAVE NOT REPLACE THOSE. SO THIS IS THE MOST SIGNIFICANT
INVESTMENT CALIFORNIA WILL HAVE MADE IN REPLACING THE STATE
HOSPITALS WITH SOMETHING BETTER AND MORE COMMUNITY BASEDRE S.
I THINK ANYONE WHO GOES OUT ON THE STREETS IN SAN FRANCISCO
CAN SEE THAT THERE ARE FOLKS WITH REAL NEEDS WHO ARE NOT
HAVING THEM RIGHT NOW. AND I'M HOPING THAT PROP ONE
AND WHAT WE DO WITH IMPLEMENTING IT IN SAN
FRANCISCO WILL HELP US TO BETTER MEET THE NEEDS OF SOME
PRETTY SICK FOLKS. I THINK THE COUNTRY CLUB IS A
VERY SPECIAL PLACE. THE CASTRO IS KNOWN FOR A
NUMBER OF THINGS. IT'S THE PLACE WHERE YOU KNOW
HARVEY MILK HAD HIS CAMERA SHOP AND WHERE THE CIVIL RIGHTS
MOVEMENT AND POLITICAL MOVEMENT OF THE LAST W 4 OR 5 DECADES
STARTED. IT'S ALSO KNOWN FOR AS A GREAT
DESTINATION FOR PEOPLE. A LOT OF THAT IS ABOUT BARS THE
GREAT NIGHTLIFE AND AND THAT'S GREAT.
THERE'S ALSO A DARKER SIDE TO THAT WHICH IS THERE IS A LOT OF
ADDICTION IN THE COMMUNITYOF. ORIGINALLY WHEN WE WERE FOUNDED
IN 1983 WE WERE A COFFEEHOUSE HOUSE THAT WAS HELPING FOLKS
RECOVER FROM THE EPIDEMIC OF THE AIDS CRISIS OVER TIME OVER
THE LAST 41 YEARS THAT HAS CHANGED AND NOW WHAT WE ARE 4 IS
WE ARE A NONPROFIT THAT HAS A FOCUS ON THE RECOVERY
COMMUNITY. THAT'S OUR FOCUS.
BUT THE CENTER ISSIT OPEN TO EVERYBODY.
WE HOST 46 IN-PERSON SUPPORT GROUPS A WEEK RANGING FROM
CRYSTAL METH ANONYMOUS ALCOHOLICS ANONYMOUS NARCOTICS
ANONYMOUS OVERREAD AS ANONYMOUS ADULT CHILDREN OF ALCOHOLICS
DHAMMA SMART RECOVERY. SO WE REALLY R TRY AND CATER TO
THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY AND ALL THE THINGS THATT THEY MIGHT NEED
HEALTH AND WELLNESS FROM FOLKS NEED A COMMUNITY OF SUPPORT TO
HEAL FROM SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER.
GIVEN THE CURRENT CIRCUMSTANCES HERE IN THE CITY THAT FOLKS ARE
GOING TO NEED A PLACE WHERE THEY CAN GOS MEET THEIR FRIENDS,
HANG OUT, GET SUPPORTIVE SERVICES AROUND THE THINGS THAT
ARE HURTING THEM AND THEN JUST HAVE A PLACE WHERE THEY CAN
THEY CAN JUST BE THAT'S THE MAGIC THAT HAPPENS HERE.
THAT'S THE MAGIC OF SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS SMALL AND MIGHTY THAT ARE DOING REALLY GOOD WORK
TO HELP PEOPLE MOVE FORWARDON. I BENEFIT FROM THIS ENTITY
BECAUSE WHEN I HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER
ABOUT HOW TO TACKLE THE CHALLENGES IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
OR IN THE CITY OVERALLIS I CAN TURN TO THE FOLKS AT THE
COUNTRY CLUB WHO HAVE LIVEDTU EXPERIENCE WITH MOST OF THE
ADDICTIONS THERE ARE AND CAN TELL ME YOU KNOW WHAT'S GOING
TO WORK OR WHAT'S LIKELY TO WORK, WHAT'S NOT LIKELY TO WORK
LESS VARIETY IS ANOTHER JUST GREAT CASTRO INSTITUTION I SUPER
COMMITTED TO THE NEIGHBORHOODS AT A TIME WHEN RETAIL IS
STRUGGLING NOT JUST IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT AROUND THE
COUNTRY. >> THIS IS A BELOVED STORECI THY
PROVIDE JOBS FOR LOTS OF FOLKS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S A FAMILY THAT HAS SEEN THE TRANSITION IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
. THEY WERE HERE WHEN IT WAS, YOU
KNOW, MORE IRISH WORKING CLASS KIND OF NEIGHBORHOOD AND THEN
THEY THEY SAW AND WELCOMED YOU KNOW, ALL THESE FOLKS COMING
INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND REALLY CHANGINGMI THE
NEIGHBORHOOD AND THEY EMBRACE THAT.
>> WOW. ALL RIGHT.
>> THAT'S EASY. OKAY.
AND HOW MUCH DOES THAT STORE WAS STARTED BY MY GREAT GREAT
GRANDFATHER IN 1936. IT STARTED AS YOU USE GREETING
CARDS AND MAGAZINE STAND AND EVOLVED WITH WITH THE
NEIGHBORHOOD NEEDED OVER THE YEARSN.
MY GREAT GRANDFATHER WAS A FIXOV IT MAN IN THE TENDERLOIN
AND WAS IN A MOTORCYCLEY ACCIDENT WHILE HE WAS
RECOVERING HE WAS FIXING THINGS IN THE BACK OF HIS PARENTS
STORE AND THAT'S HOW WE STARTED CARRYING HARDWARE ITEMS
AND LITERALLYTH HE COULD FIX ANYTHING.
WHEN YOU WALK INTO MY STORE YOU'RE WALKING INTO THE MOST
FANTASTIC PLACE YOU'VE EVER BEEN WALKING IN THE MAIN STORETH
YOU'RE GOING TOEV BE GREETED BY ROWS OF BOARD GAMES AND TOYS
AND THEN ALL OF A SUDDEN YOU'RE IN HARDWARE, LAND AND HOUSE WAS
LINEN PARTY AND PAINT AND IF YOU WALK INTO MY ANNEX YOU'RE
IMMEDIATELY GREETED BY DRAG QUEEN EYELASHES AND SHOES
AND FABRIC AND ALL EVERY GIFT ITEM YOU COULD IMAGINE AND IT
IS KIND OF A THROWBACK TO A TIME OF THE GENERAL STORE WHEN
YOU WOULD GO TO ONE STORE FOR ANYTHING YOU MIGHT NEEDOR RANGIG
FROM YOUR AT YOUR DRAG OUTFIT THAT YOU MIGHT NEEDNG FOR YOU
KNOW, SOME PARTY OR PERFORMANCE TOTY SOMETHING YOU NEED TO LIKE
FIX YOUR SEWERS OR YOUR WALLS OR TO REPAINT ORLL MAYBE JUST,
YOU KNOW, A GIFT TO TAKE TO SOMEONE FOR A HOLIDAY OR A
BIRTHDAY. >> SO THEY GOT ALL THE STUFF
WE LIKE TO SAY IF WE DON'T HAVE IT YOU DON'T NEED IT
LITERALLY WE HAVE EVERYTHING EXCEPT FOR FOOD AND CLOTHES.
EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN FRANCISCO IS STRUGGLING
BO IMPACTS OF THE OUR FAILURE TO SUCCESSFULLY
ADDRESS THE MENTAL HEALTH NEEDS OF OUR MENTALLY ILL POPULATION.
AND SO AS I LOOK 10 OR 20 YEARS INTO THE FUTURE, I THINK IT
WILL BE BRIGHT, IT WILL BE BRIGHTER TO THE EXTENT THAT WE
HAVE FOUND A WAY TO MEET THE NEEDS OF PEOPLE WITH
ADDICTIONS, WITH WITH MENTAL HEALTH CHALLENGES THAT IMPACTS
EACH STOREFRONT, EACH STORE OWNER, THE EMPLOYEES IN THOSE
STORES AND PEOPLE JUST WALKING AROUND THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND I'M
HOPING THAT YOU KNOW, TODAY I THINK WALKING AROUND IN MANY OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S NEIGHBORHOODS PEOPLE HAVE TO THINK ABOUT YOU
KNOW, WHY ARE WE NOT DOING A BETTER JOB OF CARING FOR THESE
PEOPLE? AND MY HOPE IS THAT 10 OR 20
YEARS FROM NOW BECAUSE THE WORK I DO AND THE WORK OTHER PEOPLE
DORO THAT PEOPLE WON'T HAVE TO CONSTANTLY ASK THAT QUESTION
THAT WILL JUST KEEP DOING IT AND I THINK THAT WILL NOWOW ALLW
FOR A FLOURISHING OF THESE NEIGHBORHOODS.
THESE ARE BEAUTIFUL NEIGHBORHOODS A WITH BEAUTIFUL
BUILDINGS AND VIEWS AND WEOR JUT WE JUST HAVE TO MEET THE NEEDS
OF THE HUMAN BEINGS WHO ARE KIND OF KIND OF BEEN LEFT
BEHIND AND ARE ON OUR SIDEWALKS AND IN OUR GIVEAWAYS B
I AM SUPERVISOR MIRANDA MELGAR. I AM THE SUPERVISOR FOR
DISTRICT SEVEN. >> I AM AN IMMIGRANT TO SAN
FRANCISCO. MY FAMILY CAMEI WHEN I WAS 12
FROM EL SALVADOR DURING THE CIVIL WAR A BUNCHOM OF WAR
REFUGEES AT THIS PLACE GAVE US SECURITY, SAFETY AND AN
OPPORTUNITY TO THRIVE. SO I LOVE THE CITY DEEPLY
AND AS A MOTHER OF THREE KIDS WHO HAVE GROWN UP ADS CITY KIDS
YOU KNOW I AM GRATEFUL FOR EVERYTHING THE CITY HAS TO'M
OFFER TO PEOPLE LIKE ME AND O FAMILIES I HAVE BEENN
POLITICALLY INVOLVED MY WHOLE LIFE EITHER IN GOVERNMENT OR AS
A NONPROFIT WORKER AND I CARE ABOUT THE COMMUNITY.
I CARE ABOUT PEOPLE AROUND ME AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT AS
THE WORLD CHANGES AROUND US OTHER PEOPLE HAVE THE
OPPORTUNITIES THAT MY FAMILY DID.
WE ARE BACK IN SAN FRANCISCO POST PANDEMIC SO IMPORTANT TO
BE OUT THEND PORT AND OUR BUSINESSES SUPPORTING OUR
NEIGHBORS. THMAI'M THE FIRST WOMAN TO
REPRESENT THIS DISTRICT BELIEVE IT OR NOTOTNO I'M THE FIRST LATA
ELECTED TO THE BOARD OFSU SUPERVISORS WITHOUT AN
APPOINTMENT FIRST EVER. SO I DO THINK THAT DIVERSITY IS
IMPORTANT. I WANT IMMIGRANTS TO BE
REPRESENTED WOMEN MOMS, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE THAT HAVE
DIFFERENT EXPERIENCESCE BECAUSE THAT BRINGS RICHNESS TO OUR
DECISION MAKING AND I THINKNGK THAT IT MAKES FOR A BETTER
DECISION. >> SO THAT'S WHAT INSPIRED ME
TO RUN FOR DISTRICTS. EVAN IS ONE OF THE MOST DIVERSE
DISTRICTS IN SAN FRANCISCO BOTH IN TERMS OF ECONOMICS AND ALSO
ETHNICITY. IT SPANS NOWOM ALL THE WAY NORTH
FROM GOLDEN GATE PARK. IT INCLUDESK. ALL OF THE
INSTITUTIONS IN THE PARK THE FERRIS WHEEL, THE MUSIC
CONCOURSE, THE MUSEUMS TO THE SOUTH TO THE DALY CITY BORDER
AND WEST TO THE OCEAN INCLUDES THE ZOO, FORT FUNSTON ALL OF
THOSE FUN THINGS AND THEN TO 280 ON THE EAST SO INCLUDES A
CITY COLLEGE SAN FRANCISCO STATE IT HAS UCSF PARNASSUS SO
IT'S VERY LARGE GEOGRAPHICALLY IT IS MOSTLY SINGLE FAMILY
HOMES SO IT IS THE PLACE WHERE FOR GENERATIONS FAMILY SET
ROOTS SEND THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL.
WE HAVE NICE PARKS, LAKE MARE SAIDSC MOUNT DAVIDSON.
THIS IS LIKE AIS VILLAGE WITHIN THE CITY SO WE'RE VERY CLOSE
KNIT COMMUNITY. WESE TEND TO BAND TOGETHER
AND TRY TO SUPPORT ONE ANOTHER AND AND ALSO IS JUST A FRIENDLY
PLACE FOR FAMILIES AND PEOPLE TO HAVE A CUP OF COFFEE
AND CHECK OUT THE PARK OCEAN AVENUE WHICH IS AT THE SOUTHERN
END OF OUR DISTRICT IS A VERY VIBRANT COMMERCIAL CORRIDOR
THAT MOSTLY CATERS TO OUR LOCALR NEIGHBORHOODS BUT ALSO TO THE
STUDENTS IN AS YOU GO FURTHERUD WEST
YOU KNOW YOU HAVE THIS TOWN MALL WHICH HAS SOME OF THE
BEST PAN-ASIAN FOOD OFFERINGS I THINK IN THE CITY IF YOUFEY.
HAVEN'T BEEN THERE, IT'S REALLY FUN AS YOU GO UP A LITTLE BIT
FURTHER, THERE'S WEST PORTOLA AVENUE WHICH IS A VERY OLD
SCHOOL YOU KNOW, A COMMERCIAL DISTRICT WHERE YOU CAN STILL
FIND ANTIQUE SHOPS AND COBBLER SHOPS AND YOU KNOW AS WELL AS
LIKE MORE MODERN RESTAURANTS. IT IS DEFINITELY HOPPING
AND FULL OF FAMILIES ON ANY WEEKEND.
>> I'M MATT ROGERS .
>> I'M THE CO-OWNER OF POP AND HOUSING HARDWARE ON WEST
WESTPORT AVENUE. AND CARL, I KNOW OUR OTHER
CO-OWNER OF HAVING DOESN'T HARDWARE IN WESTHE PALM AND WE'E
A NEIGHBORHOOD HARDWARE STORE AND IT'S BEEN A COMMUNITY
INSTITUTION SINCE IT WAS FOUNDED IN 1936.
WE HAVE A LITTLE BIT OF EVERYTHING FOR DO YOURSELF HOME
REPAIRS TO GARDENING OR GIFTT BUYING.
LIKE MY ENTIRE EXPERIENCE WITH SERVICE, CISCO HAS BEEN TO THIS
COMMUNITY. IT'S A VERY SMALL TOWN FEEL R
A BIG CITY THAT THE COMMUNITY IS REALLY CARING AND CONNECTED
AND I LIKE THAT. WHAT MAKES>> ME EXCITED ABOUT
DOING BUSINESS IN DISTRICT SEVEN IS JUST THAT I KNOW IT SO
WELL. I GREW UP HERE.
I KNOW A LOT OF THE CUSTOMERS I THEIR CHILDHOOD FRIENDS OR
PARENTS OF CHILDHOOD FRIENDS AND THIS IS A VERY COMFORTABLE
PLACE AND IT FEELS LIKE HOME IF YOU GO UP NORTH WE HAVE THEE
INNER SUNSET COMMERCIAL CORRIDOR WHICH HAS AN AWESOME
FARMER'S MARKET ON WEEKENDS AND A PLETHORA OF RESTAURANTS.
>> THERE'S IRANIAN, THERE'S ETHIOPIA, THERE'S THE
EVERYTHING YOU NEED IS REALLY FRIENDLYNE AND THERE YOU STOP
AND TALK TO YOU ABOUT YOU KNOW, THE DAILY BASE AND AND I LOVE
THEY THEY BRING THEIR KIDS WITHH THEM.
THEY TEACH THEM HOW TO USE THEIR MONEY IN CHANGEEI AND IT'S
SOMETHING THAT YOU DON'T SEE IN TOO MANY MARKETS DO AND THEN
ANOTHERINVE COMMUNITY BUT I LOVO SEE THE KIDS COMING AND TALKING
TO YOU YOU KNOW I'VE HAD SOMETHING DIFFERENT THAN I SEE
FROM OTHER MARKETS. WHAT I LOVED ABOUT THIS
DISTRICT WAS THE EASY ACCESS TO TRANSIT AND THE INNER SUNSET
AND THE ABILITY TO DO A LOT OF OUR SHOPPING AND FOOTOT AND NOW
THE IMPROVED BIKING WITH JFK BEING CLOSEDD TO CARS BECAUSE WE
HAVE A FOUR AND A HALF YEAR OLD WHO RIDES HER BIKE, YOU KNOW WE
NOW HAVE A SAFE PLACE TOSA GO RIDE BIKES OR WE DON'T HAVE TO
WORRY ABOUT TRAFFIC. SO GRAFFITI CONTINUES TO BE ONE
OF THE THINGS THAT DURING THE PANDEMIC JUST GOTEM OUT OF
CONTROL EVERYWHERE IN THE CITY. AND AND I DO THINK THAT IT IS
HAMPERING OUR RECOVERY OF COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS.
SO SOME OF THE VOLUNTEERS ON WEST PORTAL AVENUE SOME OF THE
MERCHANTS GOT TOGETHER WITH OUR INTERNS AT OUR OFFICE TO DO
SOME JUST HANDS ONN ABATEMENT AND WE'VE BEEN DOING IT
REGULARLY EVER SINCE. WE'RE DOING IT ONCE A WEEKK.
BUT WE HAVE A WONDERFUL NEIGHBOR, CARRIE SYKES, WHO HAS
BEEN ORGANIZINGFHB AND STORING E PAINT AND THE SUPPLIES IN HER
OFFICE ON WEST PORTAL. BUT THIS OBVIOUSLY NEEDS MORE
THAN JUST A VOLUNTEERJU EFFORT. I'M REALLY GRATEFUL FOR THAT
COLLABORATION. WE PASSED LEGISLATION AT THE
BOARD AND PUT $4 MILLION IN THE BUDGET OVER THE NEXTOV 24 MONTHS
TO HELP THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKSPU HIRE LABORERS
AND LABORER APPRENTICES TO ABATE THE GRAFFITI ON PRIVATETE
PROPERTY ON COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS.
I THINK THAT FOR A COUPLE OF YEARSA THIS IS A GOOD RECOVERY
STRATEGY UNTILO WE CAN GET BACK UP AS NORMAL AFTER THIS AWFUL
PANDEMIC. PARTICIPATORY BUDGETING IS A
POT OF MONEY THAT IS AVAILABLE EVERY YEAR FOR DISTRICT SEVEN
NEIGHBORS TO PROPOSE PROJECTS THAT IMPROVE THE NEIGHBORHOOD
AND THE DISTRICT. AND SO ANYONE ANY ORGANIZATION
IN THE DISTRICT CAN PROPOSE A A PROJECT AND THEN IT'S A VOTE
IT'S A POPULAR VOTE. SO WE HAVE 14 PROJECTS THAT
WERE JUST APPROVED AND THEY SPAN FROM, YOU KNOW, A
VEGETABLE GARDEN AT APTOS MIDDLE SCHOOLOL TO A YOU KNOW,
PEDESTRIAN SAFETY PROJECT ON SLOW HURST AVENUE.
IT JUST RUNS THE GAMUT. BUT IT'S REALLY WONDERFUL
BECAUSE IT ALLOWS PEOPLE TO BE ENGAGED IN A REAL WAY AND THEN
TO SEE THE OUTCOME OF THEIR, YOU KNOW, ENERGY AND WORK
BECAUSE THE THINGS YOU KNOW, GET IMPROVED RIGHT IN FRONT OF
THEM. I THINK I REALLY LIKE THAT IT'S
REALLY CLOSE TO THE BOTH PARKS AND LIKE A BUNCH OF BUSINESSES
ASASBU WAS JUST LIKE A VERY CALM FEELS LIKE IT FEELS VERY
PEACEFUL STILL EVEN THOUGH IT'S CLOSE TO A LOT OF THINGS WHICH
MAKES IT FEEL JUST VERY SERENE BUT THEN ALSO NOT BORING YOU
KNOW JUSTTER LIKE THERE'S ALWAYS STUFF TO DO TO SO THERE'S LOTS
TO SEE TASTE AND EXPERIENCE AT DISTRICT SEVEN
DISCOVER THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO AND DISTRICT FIVE A
TAPESTRY OF NEIGHBORHOODS EACH RICH IN HISTORY AND UNIQUE
CHARACTER AND FROM THE ICONIC HAIGHT-ASHBURY AND THE CULTURAL
VIBRANCE OF THE FILLMORE AND JAPANTOWN TO THE CHARM OF
HAYES VALLEY THE NORTH, THE PANHANDLE WESTERN ADDITION
AND THE TENDERLOIN THIS DISTRICT SHOWCASES THE CITY'S
DIVERSITY AT ITS FINEST AND I'M KRISTEN EVANS.
I'M A RESIDENT AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNER HERE IN THE
HISTORIC HAIGHT-ASHBURY NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> I OWN THE BOOK SMITH AND THE OLYMPICN HAIGHT-ASHBURY IS A
UNIQUE PLACE. IT WAS THE MOST COLORFUL PART
OF THE CITY WHEN IN WAS A KID. I ENDED UP MOVING HERE
AND OWNING A BOOKSTORE HERE WHICH WAS THE DREAM WEPE HAVE
PEOPLE OFE ALL WALKS OF VISITOS AND TOURISTS FROM AROUND THE
WORLD THAT COME TO THE HAIGHT-ASHBURY.
THEY'RE COMING SOMETIMES TO SEE OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD
THE ROCK STARS JANIS JOPLIN'S HOUSE GRATEFUL DEAD HOUSE
PEOPLE ARE VERY MUCH FREE SPIRITED HERE WE HAVE MANY
SECONDHAND CLOTHING STORES. PEOPLE ARE REALLY ECO CONSCIOUS
AND SO WE HAVE PEOPLE THAT ARE ENJOYING THE VIBRANCY OF THE
STREET AND IT'S AS MUCH A PLACE TO SHOP AS IT IS AST PLACE TO
ALSO PEOPLE WATCH. >> SO WHILE YOU'RE DOING THAT
STOP HAVE SOME LUNCH. WE HAVE DRAGON EATS WHICH IS
FUN BANH MI RESTAURANT CHA CHA CHA IS A NEIGHBORHOOD CLASSIC.
THEY HAVEE A PLACE RIGHT NEXT DOOR THAT IS CUBAN PUERTO RICAN
STYLE FOOD CALLED PRODUCTS TOO. >> THAT'S REALLY I MEAN I COULD
GO ON ABOUT ALL THE REALLY GREAT DELICIOUS PLACES TO TRY
AND HEY, I'M PART OF THE HAIGHT-ASHBURY MERCHANTS
ASSOCIATION AND WE WORK ON REALLY PROMOTINGN OUR CORRIDOR
AS A DESTINATION. PEOPLE DON'T JUST COME TO HATE
STREET TO ONE DESTINATION. THEY COME AND THEY VISIT 3 OR 4
DIFFERENT PLACES WHEN THEY WHEN THEY COME TO VISIT.
SO IF WE HAVE VACANCIES WE HAVE FEWER REASONS WHY PEOPLE ARE
COMING TO THE STREET. WE HAD 21 VACANCIES GOING INTO
THE PANDEMIC THAT INCREASED TO 32 DURING THE PANDEMIC.
AND SOD ONE OF THE THINGS THAT WE HAD BEEN ADVOCATING FOR WAS
A STOREFRONT VACANCY TAX. SO VOTERS PASSED PROPERTY
AND THAT HAS REALLY REDUCED THE NUMBER OF AGENCIES.
>> WE'VE GONE FROM 32 DOWN TO 14 .
YOU SHOULD DEFINITELY COME TO THE HAIGHT-ASHBURY JOY OUR
BEAUTIFUL WEATHER GET A MEAL ON HAIGHT STREET SHOP AT OUR OUR
BEAUTIFUL BOUTIQUES. DISTRICT S FIVE IS PROUD TO
FEATURE A NETWORK OF SLOW AND SAFE STREETS THAT CONNECT
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS .
PAGE STREET STANDS OUT AS A SHINING EXAMPLE NOW BUSTLING
WITH BIKERS AND PEDESTRIANS AND RECOGNIZED AS THE CITY'S
MOST SUCCESSFULL SLOW STREET INITIATIVES LIKE THE GOLDEN
GATE GREENWAY AND CAR FREE DAYS
HAVE ALSO TURNED PREVIOUSLY TRAFFIC HEAVY AREAS INTO SAFE
WELCOMING SPACES FOR WALKING
AND BIKING AFTER HAVING LIVED ALL OVER THE CITY I WANTED
SOMEWHERE WHERE I NEVER NEEDED TO USE A CAR AND I ALSO WANTED
SOMEWHERE WHERE I HAD A LITTLE BIT OF SEPARATION FROM MY JOB
WHICH WAS DOWNTOWN. SO I KIND OF DREW A 25 MINUTE
RADIUS AROUND DOWNTOWNN AND HAYS VALLEY SEEMED TO FIT THE BILL.
I FOUND THIS NEIGHBORHOOD REALLY FELT LIKE KIND OF THE
MOST COMMUNITY I'VE EXPERIENCED .
YOU KNOW, PEOPLE TEND TO LINGER REMINDS ME A LITTLE BIT OF A
EUROPEAN CITYA A . I SEE A LOT OF PEOPLE JUST
HANGING OUT OUTSIDE AND YOU KIND OF PASSEDGEPE PEOPLE AND YU
GET TO KNOW PEOPLE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S A PRETTY, PRETTY SPECIAL ENVIRONMENTTY..
ONE OF MY FAVORITE LANDMARKS IS WHERE WE'RE STANDING PATRICIA'S
GREEN YOU KNOW, IT'S THE FORMER SITE OF THE FREEWAY.
IT'S NAMED AFTER PATRICIA WALKUP.
SHE WAS PART OF A GROUP OF PEOPLE THAT LED THEAT MOVEMENT O
GET THE FREEWAY TAKEN DOWN AND THIS WITH THE EMBARCADERO
IS ONE OFWH THE BEST EXAMPLES OF OF WHAT HAPPENS WHEN YOU REMOVE
A FREEWAY AND GIVE SPACE BACK TO PEOPLEE.
THERE'S TONS OF PLACES TO TO SHOP AND EAT PRETTY MUCH
SOMETHING FOR EVERYBODY HERE. MY FRIEND'S KID HAD THEIR FIRST
BIRTHDAY PARTY LAST WEEK AND I WALKED INTO FIDDLESTICKS
AND GOT A PRESENT FOR THEM. IF IT'S WARMLIY LIKE TODAY YOUN
POP OVER TO HOMETOWN CREAMERY AND GET SOME ICE CREAM.
>> ANOTHER FAVORITE IS MERCURY CAFE WHICH IS A FEW BLOCKS DOWN
OCTAVIA AND ANOTHER FAVORITE IS HAYES VALLEY BAKERYY WHERE THEY
NOT ONLY HAVE LIKE INCREDIBLE BAKED GOODS AND BREAKFAST
AND SANDWICHES BUT THEY EMPLOYD AND TRAIN AT RISK AND DISABLED
PEOPLE. SO THERE'S A REAL LARGE SOCIAL
ANGLE TO WHAT THEY DO EVERY FRIDAY SATURDAY SINCE COVID,
THE 400 BLOCK OF HAY STREET BETWEEN OCTAVIA AND GOUGH IS
PEDESTRIANIZED SO WE WE OPEN IT UP FOR PEOPLEED SOMETIMES WE HAE
BANDS IT ESSENTIALLY DOUBLES THE SIZE OF OUR TOWN SQUARESQ.
SO FORAR ANYBODY IN D FIVE OR ANYWHERE AROUND THE CITY IT'S
REALLY A GREAT GATHERING SPACE TO JUST KIND OFTO LINGER.
>> YOU DON'TCO EVEN NECESSARILY NEED A PLAN JUST KIND OF COME
AND HANG OUT AT THE FILLMORE. AT THE HEART OF DISTRICT FIVE
REMAINS ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORIC BLACKSA NEIGHBORHOODS
AFTER ENDURING CHALLENGES LIKE REDEVELOPMENT AND DISPLACEMENTNT
,THE COMMUNITY IS EXPERIENCING A RESURGENCE WITH NEW
BUSINESSES BRINGING FRESH LIFE AND VIBRANCY TO THE AREA.
>> IN RECENT YEARSIN. I'M ERIC SCOTT AND WE ARE HERE
AT HONEY ART STUDIO. I GREW UP HERE IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD AND I FEEL REALLY FORTUNATE TO HAVE MY BUSINESS
HERE. WESI ARE A MULTIPURPOSE PLACE.
CLASSES AND WE ALSO HAVE LIVE ENTERTAINMENT
AND COMMUNITY MEETINGS AS A PRIVATE EVENT SPACE.
>> THE HISTORY OF THE FILLMORE DATES BACK GENERATIONS BEFORE
ME. >> WELL THAT'S A BIG PART OF
OUR STUDIO HERE. THERE'S A BOOK THE HARLEM OF
THE WEST AND THAT BOOK DEPICTS WHAT THE HARLEM OF THE WEST WAS
WHICH IS THE FILLMORE AND PEOPLE REALLY FROM ALL OVER
THE WORLD WOULD COME HERE. IT WAS A HUGE JAZZ SCENE.
>> IIE MEAN JUST EVERYTHING THIS WAS THE PLACE TO BE TO
EXPERIENCE BLACK CULTURERE AND JUST TO LIVE, YOU KNOW?
>> I DEFINITELY WANT TO GIVE THAT CLOSER TO TO MY
GENERATION, THEIR NEW BUSINESSES.
WE HAVE SOMETHING REALLY SPECIAL AND REALLY UNIQUE WHICH
IS IN THE BLACK SITS ON THE CORNER OF GARY AND FILLMORE.
>> IT IS A HOME TO I BELIEVE 30 ENTREPRENEURS.
IT'S LIKE A MARKETPLACE. >> IT'S SUPER COOL.
A LOT OFR THE THINGS ARE EITHER CUSTOM OR JUST REALLY UNIQUE
JAZZ THESE HAIR SALON AND JAZZY HAIR SALON I BELIEVE THEY'RE
APPLYING FOR A LEGACY BUSINESS OWNERSHIP BECAUSE THEY'VE BEEN
IN BUSINESSBU I BELIEVE FOR OVER 25 YEARS.
THERE'S LOTS OF COTTAGE AND HOME BASED BUSINESSES
UMBRELLA MARKETS MUHAMMAD KNOWNN AS BROTHER MUHAMMAD HERE IN THE
FILLMORE FOR SINCE 1999 BEEN ESTABLISHED HERE SINCE 1999
SELLING MY PRODUCTS AS YOU SEE IN MY BYLAWS AND UH COSMETIC
ITEMS CLOTHING CETERA. SO HOW'S IT GOING?
GOOD, GOOD, GOOD. GOOD TO SEE YOU.
GOOD. I STILL HAVE MY OLD CUSTOMERS
THAT STILL COME AND SUPPORTRT SO THEIR SALES, THEIR SALES FROM
THEM A SENSE OF COMMUNITY. WE HAVE LITTLE REMNANTS OF THAT
OLD I CALL IT THE OLD VIBE HERE .
>> SO KIND OF IS IT THE
FILLMORE IS THE FAMOUS JAZZ DISTRICT AND WE STILL HAVE
ELEMENTS OF THAT YOU WANT TO COME AND EXPERIENCED IT
FRIENDLY, FRIENDLY PEOPLE AND THIS IS A PLACE WHERE
YOU'LLU A SA TAKE A PIECE OF SAN FRANCISCO, A PIECE OF THE
FILLMORE RIGHT BACK WITH YOU. SINCE THE REDISTRICTING
IN 2022, THE TENDERLOIN HAS BECOME PART OF DISTRICTC FIVE
INTRODUCING A VIBRANT NEW COMMUNITY TO THE DISTRICT.
THE TENDERLOIN IS RICH IN HISTORY WITH UNIQUE
LANDMARKS LIKE VETERANS ALLEY WHICH WAS RENAMED FROM SHANNON
STREET TO HONOR THE MURAL PROJECT STARTED BY AMOS GREGORY
. >> WHAT BEGAN AS A BLIGHTED
ALLEY IS NOW A MEANINGFUL GATHERING PLACE WHERE VETERANS
EXPRESS THEMSELVES THROUGH ART AND CONNECT WITH ONE ANOTHER.
>> THE NEIGHBORHOOD ALSO BOASTS THE TENDERLOIN MUSEUM OFFERING
INCREDIBLE PROGRAMS THAT HIGHLIGHT THE AREA'S CULTURALTH
AND HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE SO THAT SOUTHERN MUSEUM HAS A
PERMANENTT COLLECTION ABOUT THE HISTORY OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD
AND WE ALSO HAVE A COMMUNITY ART GALLERY FEATURING
TENDERLOIN ARTISTS AND OTHER ARTISTS LIKE WORKING
ON PROJECTS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE'VE REALLY BECOME KNOWNODOD FR HAVING HISTORICALLY INSPIRED
ARTS PROGRAMS AND THAT'S SOMETHING THAT MAKES US VERY
UNIQUE. WE'RE CURRENTLY PRODUCING A
PLAY ABOUT THE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA AREA AND WE STRIVE TO
WORK WITH AS MANY LIKE NEIGHBORS AND NEIGHBORING
ORGANIZATIONS AS POSSIBLE TO CREATE REALLY DIVERSEEA
PROGRAMING FOR A DIVERSE NEIGHBORHOOD.
TEN REALLY IS LIKE AN INCREDIBLY CLOSE KNIT COMMUNITY
AND JUST LIKE THE ALMOST DECADE I'VE BEEN WORKING HERE, YOU'RE
ABLE TO REALLY MAKE SO MANY CONNECTIONS WITH PEOPLE
AND CHARLIE'S IS AN INCREDIBLE NEIGHBORHOOD WORKING CLASS DRAG
BAR AND IT'S THE LAST BAR IN THE TOWN REALLY NEIGHBORHOOD
WHICH WAS THE FIRST NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN FRANCISCO
CATAPULTS USIG AN INCREDIBLE ORGANIZATION THAT SHOWS
EXPERIMENTAL PERFORMING ARTS AND THEY HAVE BEEN GREAT
PARTNERS AND DO A LOT FOR THEHE NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE HAVE A LITTLE SAIGON AND SAIGON SANDWICHES.
THE VIETNAMESE SANDWICHES I THINK ARE ONE OF THE CLASSIC
STAPLES OF TENDERLOIN CUISINE AND YEMEN KITCHEN IS A
RESTAURANTAT THAT OPENED IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD ACTUALLY THAT I
HIGHLY RECOMMEND THE PHENIXE HOTEL IS LIKE SUCH A TENDERLOIN
LEGACY BUSINESS. YEAH, THAT BRINGS IN LIKE
PEOPLE INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD THAT MIGHT NOT NORMALLY STAY
HERE. THERE'S SO MUCH MORE TO THAT
CENTER LINE THAN WHAT YOU READ ABOUT IN THE NEWS.
COME VISIT. THAT'S ONE MUSEUM AND HEAR MORE
OF THE STORY FROM THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE HEREE THEMSELVES.
PROBABLY THEOB MOST UNIQUE FEATURE IN JAPANTOWN IS THE
PEACE PAGODAA WHICH WAS BUILT AS PART OF THE JAPAN TRADE CENTER.
THE OTHER IS THE JAPAN CENTER ITSELF.
YOU KNOW, THE OLDEST INDOOR SHOPPING MALL IN SAN FRANCISCO
WAS BUILT IN THE LATE 1960S. DESPITE ALL THE CHANGES JAPAN
HASNT BEEN THROUGH, IT'S REALLY STILL AN AUTHENTIC JAPAN TOWN.
IT'S STILL A JAPANESE-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
SO YOU COULD STILL FIND A LOT
OF JAPANESE JAPANESE AMERICAN FOODCA HERE JAPANESE ICE CREAM
STORES THAT ARE REALLY POPULAR .
WE HAVE WHAT'S CALLED MATCHA DRINKS HEREA .
THE OTHER THING THAT BECOME REALLY POPULAR HERE
IS ALL OF THE NEW RAMEN SHOPS THAT HAVE OPENED UP
. YOU KNOW, BEFORE EVERY JAPANESE
RESTAURANT HAD RAMEN IT WAS D ANYTHING YOU COULD
ORDER. BUT NOW IT'S ALL SPECIALIZED
RAMENLILI. SO THEY COME FROM DIFFERENT
PARTS OF JAPAN AND THEY FEATURE THEIR HOMETOWN STYLE OF RAMEN.
YOU KNOW, IT'S A REALLY SAFE
PLACE TO HANG OUT BUT YOU KNOW, YOU COME DOWN HERE AND YOU'LL
GET A SENSE OF THE JAPANESE AMERICAN HISTORY AND CULTURE
JUST BYAN BEING DOWN HERE. >> IT'S JUST ONE OF THE GREAT
PLACES TO VISIT IN SAN FRANCISCO.
DISTRICT FIVE IS A VIBRANT AND DIVERSE AREA WITH SO MUCH
TO OFFER BOTH RESIDENTS AND VISITORS.
IT'S A PLACE WHERE PEOPLE CAN EXPERIENCE THE AMAZING
COMMUNITY SPIRIT AND EXPLORE THE MANY UNIQUE SMALL
BUSINESSES THAT MAKE THIS DISTRICT TRULY SPECIALL
DISTRICT TWO IS ONE OF THE MOST BEAUTIFUL PARTS OF THE CITY.
THE MOST BEAUTIFUL WE HAVE THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE
IN THEG THE CITY RIGHT H PRESIDIO WHICH IN AND OF ITSELF
IS AN ABSOLUTE GEMHIHI. BUT THIS DISTRICT IS INCREDIBLE
BECAUSE IT'S MADE UP OF ALL I THESE DIVERSE LITTLE POCKETS
DOWN TOWARDS CITY HALL AND CATHEDRALIV HILL.
WE HAVE LARGER APARTMENT BUILDINGS AROUND JEFFERSON
SQUARE PARKBU ON FILLMORE STREE. WE HAVE A DIVERSE MERCHANT
CORRIDOR RIGHT NEXTWECO TO APARTMENT BUILDINGS AND SINGLE
FAMILY HOMES JUST HERE IN LAFAYETTE PARK.
WE HAVE INCREDIBLE VIEWS BOTH PE TO THE NORTH AND TO THE SOUTH.
I'M STEVE AND CHERYL, DISTRICT TO SUPERVISOR HERE IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCODI. I AM INCREDIBLY PROUD TO LIVE
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO IN A FABULOUS NEIGHBORHOOD
IN PRESIDIO HEIGHTS WITH MY WIFE AND OUR YOUNGOOH KIDS.
SO I I MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO IN THE FIRST APARTMENT I LIVEDIR
IN WAS ON BROADWAY AND LAGUNAN DISTRICT TWO ISDI THE ONLY PLACT
THAT I'VE LIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THIS IS A HISTORIC PART OF THE CITY BUT IT'S ALSO A LIVELY
PART OF THE CITY THAT'S GOT SMALL MERCHANT CORRIDORS ONT'
UNION ON CHESTNUT AND IT'S
INCREDIBLY LIVELY PLACE NOT ONLY TO LIVE BUT ALSOL TO WORK.
HI MY NAME IS JESSICA ANN AND I'M THE OWNER OF NICO.
>> NICO>> GETS WE ENDED UP IN SN FRANCISCO AND MY PARTNER AND I
DECIDED TO MOVE FROM LOSFR ANGELES ABOUT TWO AND A HALF
YEARS AGO AND WE WANTED TO EXPERIENCE A NEW PLACE AN
ENVIRONMENT THAT HAD A LOT OFPE WALKABILITY AND GOOD CLIMATE
BECAUSE WE DIDN'T REALLY LIKE THE HEAT IN L.A. CI AND ALSO ALL
THE PARKS AND GREEN SPACE BECAUSE AE WE HAVE TWO DOGS.
SO THAT'S HOW WE DECIDED TO MOVE HEREID.
I THINK MY FAVORITE THINGS ABOUT THIS IS THAT IT'S ONE OF
THE MOST BEAUTIFUL DISTRICTS IN SAN FRANCISCOCT.
I THINK IT'S VERY HISTORIC. IT'S GOTTO LIKE A BAY THE VIEWS
IT'S GOT THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE
SOGE I THINK WHEN YOU LOOK AT SN FRANCISCO ALL TOGETHER FOR MEO I
THINK IT'S THE MOST SCENIC I GUESS I DIDN'T KNOW MUCH ABOUT
THE DIFFERENT NEIGHBORHOODS K IN SAN FRANCISCO WHEN WE FIRST
MOVED HERE. WE WERE JUST DRIVING BY AND I
HAPPENEDWH TO SEE THIS SPACE AND I ABSOLUTELY FELL IN LOVE
WITH IT. SO NICO NICO ACTUALLY NEEDS TO
SMILE OR BE SMILINGNG AND JAPANESE AND IF YOU LOOK AT
THE BRANDING ON THE TOP IT'LL SAY NICO NICO IN JAPANESE
AND THEN ON THE BOTTOM IN KOREAN.
SO I WANTED TO REPRESENT MY DUAL HERITAGE IN ONE SPACE
AND OFFER A GIFT SHOP THAT HAS CULTURAL LIKE ENGAGEMENT LIKE
REPRESENTATION OF AAPI COMMUNITIES BUT ALSO OF MYSELF
. WHEN I HAVE FAMILY AND FRIENDS
VISITING SAN FRANCISCO I HAVE A FULL ITINERARY FOR THEM HERE
IN THE DISTRICT. >>E FIRST OF ALL WE'VE GOT TO GO
SEE THE BRIDGE NOW FOR LUNCH. >> I WANT TO MAKE A MOVE AND GO
TO ROSE'S CAFE ON UNION STREET .
WE'RE GOING TO HAVEZA A LITTLE BIT OF PIZZA.
THEN AFTER THAT WE'RE GOING TO GO TO CRISSY FIELD.
WE'RE GOING TO GET ON THE BEACH.
OF COURSE IT'S A SUNNY DAY SO WE'RE GOING TO RELAXAX A LITTLE
BIT THEN WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A DIP MORE OF A COLD PLUNGE BUT
THEN WE'LL TOWELN OFF AND WE'RE GOING TO MAKE OUR WAY TO
CHESTNUT. >> MAYBE WE'LL DO A LITTLE
ORIGINAL JOE'S MAYBE WE'LL DO IS IS A LOT I OF GREAT OPTIONS
FOR DINNER AND THEN LATE NIGHT MAYBE WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A
COCKTAIL AT PRISON HEADYB COURTHOUSE DISTRICT TWO IS AN
INCREDIBLE MIX OFRIOT FABULOUS PEOPLE AND FABULOUS GEOGRAPHY
AND WHEN THOSE TWO THINGS COME TOGETHER YOU GET A LOT OF
BEAUTY. WE
HAVE SOME OF THE BEST NEIGHBORHOOD MERCHANT CORRIDORS
WITH SOME FANTASTIC
RESTAURANTS. WE HAVE SOME OF THE BEST HIKINGA
HERE IN THE CITY IN THE PRESIDIO.
WE HAVE SOME OF THE BEST IN THE CITY. C
>> WE'VE GOT A HARBOR. I MEAN THERE IS>> SO MUCH TO DO
HERE. IT IS INCREDIBLE.
BUT MOST OF ALL I THINK THE GREATEST T PART ABOUT DISTRICT O
IS OUR PARKS WHETHER IT'S ATT THEE PLAZA PARK, WHETHER IT'S
RIGHT HERE IN LAFAYETTE PARK WE HAVE SOME INCREDIBLE PARKS THAT
I'M INCREDIBLY PROUD TO BE ABLE TO VISIT ALL THE TIME.
>> THERE'S NOTHING BETTER THAN BEING IN DISTRICT TWO AS PARKS
. I LIVE IN PRESIDIO HEIGHTS.
WE'RE REALLY CLOSE TO SACRAMENTO STREET.
THERE ARE SOMEEI FABULOUS RETAIL STORES.
IT'S A LIVELY, GREAT PLACE WITH FANTASTIC CREATORS AND I'M SO
EXCITED TO HAVE THAT IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD I.
>> WE'VE BEEN TRYING TO OPEN A STORE IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR A
VERY LONG TIME. WE'VE CHECKED OUT LOTS OF
NEIGHBORHOODS. SO IN ONE OF THE WONDERFUL
TWIST OF FATE I HAVE A NEW BOYFRIEND WHO LIVES DOWN THE
STREET. SO WE WOULD WALK UP AND DOWN
THE STREETT ALL THE TIME AND WE SAW THIS SPACE AND WE SAID THIS
IS WHERE WE WANT TO BE. I THINK THE AMAZING THING ABOUT
ITS VARIETY.IS WE HAVE LOTS OF AMAZING STORES
ON A SACRAMENTO STREET. I THINK THERE'S A REAL SENSE OF
COMMUNITY HERE THAT I FEEL IS QUITE STRONG.
>> SO FROM A RETAIL PERSPECTIVE WEWE JUST REALLY FEEL LIKE
THERE'S A LOT OF AMAZING ENERGY .
THE STREET IS PARTICULARLY IS KINDL WHICH I THINK
OF A BONUS. WE WERE VERY HAPPY WHEN THE
STORE WAS AVAILABLE. NOW THAT I'VE BEEN LIVING HERE
FOR A WHILE OF COURSE THE CITY IS INCREDIBLE BUT YOU HAVE ONE
OF THE MOST AMAZING GIFTS, RIGHT?
WHICH IS THE PRESIDIONE A THAT U ACTUALLY HAVE THIS INCREDIBLE
OPEN SPACE THAT'S UTILIZEDHIHI THAT'S CLOSED FOR THE
NEIGHBORHOOD AND ACTUALLY I THINK QUITE CLOSE FOR THE
A WHOLE CITY.
I THINK THIS NEIGHBORHOOD HAS FOR LACK OF A BETTER WAY TO
DESCRIBE IT'S GOT A GREAT VIBE. WE LOVE IT PARTICULARLY BECAUSE
WE>> HAVE A LOT OF GALS WHO COME IN THEY KNOW OUR STORE IN MARING
BUT THEY LIVE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND THEY'RE HAPPY
THAT WE'RE HERE I. AMELIA MILLS IS A WOMEN OWNED
BUSINESS. >> WE'VE BEEN IN BUSINESS FOR
33 YEARS. SI3SISTER AND I ARE PARTNERS
AND WE MAKE BEAUTIFUL BRA SIZE SWIMWEAR AND BEAUTIFUL READY TO
WEAR IT ALL STARTED IN SAN FRANCISCO SO MY SISTER WORKEDTA
FOR JESSICA MCCLINTOCK. FRIEND OFCALL FROM A
HERS WHO WORKED FOR THE SPORTS ILLUSTRATED SWIMSUIT ISSUE
AND SHE SAID I KNOW YOU ALWAYS LOVE MAKING SWIMSUITS WHEN YOU
GROW UP IN HAWAII WERE VERY SWIMSUITIT CENTRIC AND SHE
LITERALLY ONCE SHE GOT THE CALL AND THEY SAID WE WOULD C LIKE TO
PUT SOME OF YOUR SUITS IN OUR SPORTS ILLUSTRATED ISSUE SHEOUME
LITERALLY WENT TO ALL THE STORES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND SHE
CHECKED OUT THE WHOLE SWIMSH F DEPARTMENT AND SHE SAID THIS IS
INSANE THAT WOMEN HAVE T TO BUY SUITS AS A SET.
SHE SAID WOMEN ARE ALL SHAPES AND SIZES AND THEY ARE NOT THE
SAME SIZE TOP AND BOTTOM AND SHE SAID THIS IS WHAT I'M
GOING TO DO. SO FROM THAT MOMENT WORKING ATTA
JESSICAT MCCLINTOCK, SHE SAID I'M GOING TO START A BUSINESS
WHERE WOMEN CAN BUY TOPS AND BOTTOMS SOLD SEPARATELY.
NOW WE'VE BEEN DOING THATT 33 YEARS.
>> DISTRICT TWO IS AOI FANTASTIC TECH AREA WITH RESIDENTS WHO
LOVE THIS CITY WHEN YOU WALK DOWN THE STREET AND YOU KNOW
YOUR NEIGHBORS AND YOU CAN TALK TO THEMM, IT MAKES IT FEEL LIKE
HOME AND AT THE END OF THE DAY THAT'S THE MOST IMPORTANT THING
. SAN FRANCISCO IS HOME AND I
WANT IT TO FEELE SAFE AND WELCOMING FOR THE PEOPLE
WHO WANT TO BE HERE AND SUCCEED HERE.
O COMMUNITY.BOUT IT'S ABOUT NEIGHBORS.
IT'S ABOUT FEELING HOMET AND S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO
GOVERNMENT TELEVISION. WELL MY NAME IS CONNIE CHAN.
I'M DISTRICT ONENN SUPERVISOR AND WELCOME TO THE RICHMOND YOU
KNOW I'M A FIRST GENERATION IMMIGRANT.
I CAME HERE TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CHINATOWN IN FACT WHEN I WAS 13
YEARS OLD WITH MY MOM AND MY BROTHER.
NDMY FIRST JOB IS AS A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER FOR PUBLIC SAFETY.
WAS SAN FRANCISCO SAFE? I EVENTUALLY LANDED IN CITY
HALL AND BECAME ACA LEGISLATIVE AIDE TO FORMER SUPERVISOR
SOPHIE MAXWELL WHO WORK AT MANY DIFFERENT CITY DEPARTMENTS LIKE
THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S OFFICE. WHEN KAMALAWE HARRIS WAS OUR
DISTRICT ATTORNEY EVENTUALLY I RAN FOR OFFICE AND NOW I'M
REALLY PROUD TO BE REPRESENTING THE RICHMOND AS ITS DISTRICT
SUPERVISOR. >> WE HAVE GREAT NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS IN THE RICHMOND THAT REALLY NEED TO BE
PROTECTED AND IS THE REASON WHY WE LAUNCHED THE NEIGHBORHOOD
ANGERING BUSINESS SPECIFICALLY PRIORITIZE BUSINESS SUPPORTS
AND RESOURCES FOR BUSINESS. I'VE BEENPOIN AROUND FOR 15 YEAS
AND MORE WHERE TO HAVE THE LEGACY BUSINESS PROGRAM WHICH
IS WHERE BUSINESS HAS BEEN AROUND FOR 30 YEARS OR MORE BUT
WE THOUGHT YOU KNOW WE GOT IT LIKE MADE SURE THE NEXT
GENERATIONS OF SMALL BUSINESS CONTINUE TO STAY ON FOR
GENERATIONS TO COME F. >> MY NAME IS ROOS.
I'M THE OWNER OF HAMBURGER HAVEN.
WE JUST CAME BACK ON JULY 11TH. WE'RE HAPPY TO BE BACK.
HEY, RAVEN WAS OPENED IN 1968. AT THAT TIME I BELIEVE ONE OF
THE OWNERS OF MILLS HAD STARTED IT WENT THROUGH A GUY NAMED
ANDY IN THE EARLY 70S AND THEN MY FATHER TOOK IT OVER MID 70S
REGGIE FOLLOWED HIM ORIGINALLY IT WAS JUST THE BURGER JOINTS.
WE WERE OPEN LATE NIGHTS THEN IT SLOWLY CHANGED OVER THE
YEARS AND BECAME A BREAKFAST STAPLE.
SO WE SPECIALIZE IN BREAKFAST BRUNCH AND LUNCH RIGHT NOW I
ABSOLUTELY LOVE THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
I GREW UP HERED AND IT FEELS LIKE HOME.
I WALK DOWN THE BLOCK. I RECOGNIZE PEOPLE A.
PEOPLE SAY HELLO, YOU SAY HELLO BACK.
YOU KNOW YOU TALK TOAL JOE. SO IT HAS THAT FAMILIAL
ENVIRONMENT THAT IS REALLY ENJOYABLE AND I HAVEN'T
EXPERIENCED ANYWHERE ELSE. >> THERE ARE MANY THINGS I WILL
LOVE TO CONTINUE TO SEE IMPROVEMENTS BUT MOST
IMPORTANTLY ARE SOME OF THE THINGS THAT WE DON'T QUITE SEE
ARE MAKING SURE THAT OUR TENANTS STAYSU HOUSED OUR SMALL
BUSINESS TO STAY INTACT AND THRIVE IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. AND THOSE ARE THE POLICY
SOLUTIONS THAT I'M GOING TO CONTAIN A TO PUSH TO MAKE SURE
OUR COMMUNITYHA CAN TAKE ROOT AND STAY HERE AND THRIVE SO I'M
REALLY PROUD OF, YOU KNOW, WELCOMING FOLKS TO THE RICHMOND,
BECAUSE EVERYONE LOVES IT BECAUSE WE GOT FARMER'S MARKET
EVERY SUNDAY THERERERY BUT YOU O SEE SOME REALLY BUSINESS THAT
BEEN AROUND IT'SY ALWAYS ICE CREAM AT TOY BOAT AND GOING TO
SHOP FOR BAUXITE GREEN APPLE AND DEFINITELY LIKE GIORGIO IS
A PIZZA PLACE THAT ALL FAMILIES LOVE YOU WILL SEE A LOT OF
GREAT CHINESE GROCERY SHOPS THAT IS READILY AVAILABLE FOROR
EVERYONEER AND THAT IS JUST ENRICHMENT.
>> THERE'S SO MUCH MORE TO DO IN THE RICHMOND
WHAT IS LOVE IS THE BUBBLE THEATER.
>> MY NAME'S ADAM BERGERON AND ALONG WITH MY WIFE JAMIE
OWN LITTLE COMPANY CALLED CINEMA S.F. WE OPERATE THE
BALBOA THEATER ON BALBOA STREET, THE VOGUE THEATER ON
SACRAMENTO STREET AND SOON TOTH BE THE FOUR STAR THEATER ON
CLEMENT STREET. >> BALBOA THEATER OPENED ON
IN 1926 AND HAS BEEN SERVICING THIS OUTER RICHMOND
NEIGHBORHOOD CONTINUOUSLY SINCE THEN BO AND THEN CLOSE ON ITS
HEELS. >> THE FOUR STAR HAS BEEN OPEN
SINCE 1913. WHEN YOU COME IN TO A MOVIE
THEATER, THE REST OF THE WORLD KIND OF HAS TO BE LEFT BEHIND.
>> BUT YOU GET IMMERSED IN THIS WORLD THAT THE FILMMAKERS HAVE
MADE FOR YOU AND THAT'S A SPECIAL EXPERIENCE TO HAVE.
WE CAN ALL THINK OFWE MOVIES THT WE SAW ON THE BIG SCREEN WITH
EVERYBODY YOU KNOW, SCREAMING OR LAUGHING OR CRYING OR YOU
KNOWOW AND IT'S A SHARED HUMAN EXPERIENCE THAT YOU GET WHEN
YOU GO INTO PLACES THAT ARET GATHERINGS AND ART IS PRESENTED
TO YOU. I THINK THE SHARED EXPERIENCE
IS T IS THE MOST PRECIOUS OUT OF ALL OF THOSE AND THEU POPCORN
THAT WE HAVE TO AT THE BALBOA ESPECIALLY WE STRIVE TO HAVE
MOVIES FOR PEOPLE OF EVERY GENERATION FROM THE POPCORN
PALACE MOVIES THAT WE SHOW ON THE WEEKEND MORNINGS FOR
FAMILIES M M AND FOR LITTLE KID. >> THIS IS FOR EVERYBODY OF ALL
AGES. WHAT IS GREAT ABOUT THE
RICHMOND IT'S REALLY A NEIGHBORHOOD OF THE IMMIGRANTS
. ITIG BELONGS TO IMMIGRANTS BUT
NOT JUST API IMMIGRANTS. YOU WILL SEE THAT THERE'S ALSO
A HUGE POPULATION OF RUSSIAN AND UKRAINIAN IMMIGRANTS AT
THIS MOMENT EVEN IN THIS WORLD CLIMATE THEY REALLY STAND
UNITED IT TOGETHER. YOU WILL SEE THAT THE SUPPORT
THAT THEY LEND TO EACH OTHER AS A COMMUNITY AND A CINDERELLA
BAKERY IS ANOTHER LEGACY BUSINESS IN THE RICHMOND IF YOU
GO ON THEIR WEBSITE IT'SSS. KNON AS A RUSSIAN BAKERY BUT THE
FIRST THING YOU WILL SEE IS THEIR PLEDGE TO SUPPORT THE
UKRAINIAN COMMUNITY AND SO YOU WILL SEE THAT UNITY THROUGH
AND THROUGH IN THE RESTAURANT. AND SO I'M SO PROUD OF OUR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY IN THE RICHMONDNT.
MY DAD, HE IMMIGRATED FROM IRAN
AND THE REASON HE STAYED WAS BECAUSE OF THE RESTAURANT
AND SOMETHING THAT HAS MORE SENTIMENTAL VALUE FOR US JUST
BECAUSE IT'S V THE REASON THAT E ARE IN THIS COUNTRY.
WHEN HE HAD OPTION TO TAKE OVER THE RESTAURANT AND HE DECIDED
TO STAY AND THAT'S THE REASON WHY WHY WE'RE HERE AND IT'S
PART OFT OUR FAMILY LEGACY. IT'S PART OF SAN FRANCISCO
HISTORY AND WE LIKE TO KEEP IT GOING FOR YEARS TO COME.
>>G ANOTHER MOMENT THAT I'M REALLY PROUD TO BE REPRESENTING
TO RICHMOND BUT ALSO TO BE THE ONLY ASIAN AMERICAN WOMAN
ELECTED IN OFFICE AND ALSO AS AN IMMIGRANT FLUENT SPEAKING
IN MANDARIN AND CANTONESE AND THAT HAS NOT BEEN HAPPENING
IN THREE DECADES. YOU'RE GOING TO SEE THAT YOU
KNOW IT'SNOPP REALLY MY ABILITYO REPRESENT ESPECIALLY THE ASIAN
AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND IN MY CASE DEFINITELY ALSO THE
CHINESE SPEAKING ELDERS IN OUR COMMUNITY THAT REALLY CAN C ALLW
ME TO COMMUNICATE WITH THEM DIRECTLY.
MY NAME IS CALVIN USE AND THE PROGRAM ARE ABOUT THE CENTER I
HAVE BEEN LOOKING ATCT SELF-HELP FOR SEVEN YEAR SO I LOVE THIS
APPLICATION FOR HELPING
COMMUNITY HELPING WITH THE SENIOR AND ALSO THE PEOPLE WE
SPIRITY SO I DO HAVE A CONNECTION WITH THEM BECAUSE I
AM AN IMMIGRANT AND MY PARENTS ARE SENIORS.
I JUST LOVE TO HELPING OUR COMMUNITY AND HELPING PEOPLE OF
NEW IMMIGRANT THE AS MUCH AS SEEING THEM HAVE IMPROVEMENT
FOR THE FISCAL AND PSYCHOSOCIAL THAT IF YOU WANT NATURE
RICHMOND IS ALSO THE NEIGHBORHOOD TO GO BECAUSE
WE'RE SANDWICHED BETWEEN OCEAN BEACH, SUTRO HEIGHTS AND THE
GOLDEN GATE PARK. I LOVE THE OUTER RICHMOND.
FOR ME THIS IS THE SINGLE BEST NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN FRANCISCO.
EVERYBODY KNOWS EACH OTHER. PEOPLE HAVE BEEN LIVING HERE
FOREVER. IT'S IT'S YOUNG AND OLD.
THE OCEAN IS REALLY NEARBY AND SO THERE'S KIND OF THAT
OUTDOORSO OCEAN VIBE TO IT. THERE'S PLENTY OF PLACES WHERE
YOU CAN SEE THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE WHICH IS PRETTY AMAZING.
THE BUSINESSES ARE ALL SMALL MOM AND POPSI BUSINESSES.
HOUSES GET PASSED DOWN FROM GENERATION TO GENERATION D.
IT REALLY HAS KIND OF A SMALL TOWN FEEL BUT YOU KNOW YOU'RE
IN A BIG CITY AT THE SAME TIME. IT'S REALLY GOT THIS KIND OF A
UNIQUE FLAVOR TO IT THAT I DON'T SEE IN ANY OTHER
NEIGHBORHOOD AND IT IS ABOUT BEING INCLUSIVE WILL ALWAYS
INCLUSIVE AND WELCOMING THE COMMUNITY.
ANYBODY SHOULD BE FEELING WELCOMECO EMPTY THAT BELONG
IN THE RICHMOND AND THAT WAS SHOP LOCAL WE EAT LOCAL AND WE
BELIEVE THAT WITH THAT SUPPORT AND THAT NETWORK TND IT COMES FL
CIRCLE. IT IS PASSING ALL YOUR
KINDNESS. I THINK THAT'S PNG WHAT RICHMONS
ABOUT THAT WE'RE TOGETHER AS ONE.
SO WELCOME T TO THE RICHMOND
ALSO GO TO THE STAMP AND CISCO DOWNTOWN WELCOME TO POWER
STATION EVERYONE AND WELCOME TO THE SOPHIE MAXWELL BUILDING.
MY NAME IS TINA CHANG. I'M PARTNER HERE AT ASSOCIATE
CAPITAL SOON TO BE FIFTH SPACE YOU ALL WILL RECEIVE A MORE
FORMAL ANNOUNCEMENT ABOUT THAT STUDENTS SO STAY TUNED.
IT IS MY PRIVILEGE TO SERVE AS YOUR M.C. TODAY AND I PROMISE
TO KEEP THINGS BRIEF SO WE CAN GET TOPR THE MAIN EVENT.
BUT FIRST I'D LIKE TO SHARE A FEW WORDS ABOUT WHY TODAY IS SO
SPECIAL TO ME. THROUGHOUT MY CAREER I'VE HAD
THE GREAT T HONOR OF WORKING ON TRANSFORMATIVE PROJECTS FROMH
MASTER PLANNING NAVAL BASES ACROSS THE GLOBE TO ADVANCING
PUBLIC PRIVATE PARTNERSHIPS TO COMPLETE ONE OF THE MOST MIXED
USE CORNERS IN SAN FRANCISCO. BUT I HAVE TO SAY THAT TODAY AS
WE'RE ABOUT TO WELCOME OVER 100 FAMILIES TO POWER STATION
STANDS AMONGST MY PROUDEST MOMENTS WE SET OUT TO CREATE
MISSING MIDDLE HOUSING HOUSING FOR EVERYDAY HEROES WHO HELP
MAKE THE CITY FUNCTION BUT WHO CAN NO LONGER AFFORD TO BE HERE
. AND WE'RE ABLE TO DO THAT DUE
TO THE UNWAVERING RESOLVE OF OUR TEAMM.
AND AS ALV RESULT OF THAT RESOLE WE CAN WELCOME SIX FAMILIES
FROM THE HOMELESS PRENATAL PROGRAM TO POWER STATION.
THIS ORGANIZATION IS DEDICATED TO ENDING GENERATIONAL POVERTY
AND SO YES, TODAY'S STANDS IS A VERY PROUD MOMENT FOR ME
AND FOR ALL OF US. POWER STATION AND THE SOPHIE
MAXWELL BUILDING ARE THE RESULT OF SHARED DETERMINATION, GRIT
AND THE BELIEF THAT THE YOUTH 29 ACRES COULD ONE DAY BECOME A
THRIVING COMMUNITY NOT JUST FOR FAMILIES BUT ALSO FOR
BUSINESSES AND VISITORS ALIKE. AND WE'RE NOT ABLE THAT WE'RE
ABLE TO DO THAT NOT JUST BECAUSE OF THE TEAM AT
ASSOCIATE CAPITAL BUT BECAUSE OF EVERYONE HERE.
NONE OF THIS WAS ACHIEVED ALONE .
SO I HAVE TO SAY THANK YOU TO SOPHIE MAXWELL AND HER
LEADERSHIP M TO THE COMMUNITY WO WALK WITH US EVERY STEP OF THE
WAY OVER THESE PAST EIGHT YEARS.
THANK YOU TO THE DOGPATCH
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION TO THE POTRERO BOOSTERS, TO THE
DOGPATCH POTRERO MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION, THE GREEN BENEFITS
DISTRICT. THANK YOU TO THE INCREDIBLY
TALENTED ARCHITECTS AND DESIGNERS WHO CRAFTED EVERY
INCH OF THE BUILDING BEHIND ME B TWO ELEMENTS ARCHITECTS PALAZZO
PROJECTS JEFF SCHWABS AND CHEYENNE CONCEPCION.
THANK YOU TOIO ORGANIZED LABOR RUDY AT BUILDING TRADES
ASSOCIATION AND OUR PARTNERS AT SWINNERTON TO FILL THE GATES
AND THANK YOU OF COURSE TO OUR CITY PARTNERS TO THE TIRELESS
EFFORTS AND ALL OF YOU WHO WORKED QUIETLY WHEN YOU COULD
HAVE Y Y SAID NO THANK YOU TO RY ,TO OUR PARTNERS AT THE SAN
FRANCISCO PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO MOST CITY TO F THE S.F. MTA
TO SFP YOU SEE AND TO ALL OF YOUR TIRES TIRELESS EFFORTS AT
THE PORT. WE'RE SO GRATEFUL FOR YOU.
I WOULD BE F REMISS IF I DIDN'T RECOGNIZE OUR SUPERVISOR SHIMON
WALTON WHO DID TENS OF BIGGEST CHEERLEADER AND HE REMINDS USAD
EVERY DAY TO KEEP GOING AND OF COURSE THE FINANCIAL WIZARDS AT
JP>>WI MORGAN IT'S NO ACCIDENT T POWER STATIONS FIRST PROJECT IS
A WORKFORCE HOUSING BUILDING A SYMBOL OF INCLUSION A
AND OPPORTUNITY BECAUSE THIS IS WHAT WE'RE ALL ABOUT.
WE'RE ABOUTSS CREATING ATTAINABE YET ASPIRATIONAL FUTURES FOR
THE PEOPLE OF THENA FRANCISCO. AND WITH THAT I WANT TO WELCOME
ENRIQUE LANDA W MANAGING PARTNER TO OUR STAGE WHO'S TITLE SHOULD
ACTUALLY BE CHIEF OPTIMIST OFFICER NOT NOT JUST FOR POWER
STATION BUT FOR THE CITY. LADIES MANDELMAN, ENRIQUE LANDAA
. HEY, THANK YOU ALL FOR BEING
HERE. YOU KNOW, SOME OF YOU ASKED ME
WHY A MARCHING BAND? >> IT'S A HOMECOMING.
>> THAT'S IT. IN BURTON HIGH SCHOOL.
WELCOME. WESTERN STYLE.
BUT I'M GOING TO TELL YOUOU IT'S FOR US AFTER NINE YEARS OF
BEING HEREIN THAT FIRST MOMENT THAT PEOPLE ARE GOING TO WALK
INTO THIS HOUSE, THAT MOMENT YOU FEEL WHEN YOU'RE MOVING
SOMEWHERE NEW THAT MOMENT OF POSSIBILITY THAT'S WHAT, WE'RE
CELEBRATING. WE'RE CELEBRATING A MOMENT OF
OPPORTUNITY FOR PEOPLE THAT WE DON'T NORMALLY BUILD FOR.
YOU KNOW, WHEN WE SET OUT TO DO THIS PEOPLE SAID WE WERE NUTS
AND WE MIGHT HAVE BEEN. BUT IT'S THAT MISSING MIDDLE
THAT NOBODY BUILDS FOR THE PEOPLE M SAID IS IMPOSSIBLE THAT
WE JUST SAID WAIT, HOW CAN WE LIVE IN A CITY WHERED YOU CAN'T
BUILD FOR THE MIDDLE? THAT DOESN'T MAKE ANY SENSE.
DLAND SO WE TOOK KIND OF THE COURAGE FROM SOMEONE WHO'S
SITTING HERE TODAY WHO HAD THE COURAGE TO SAY, YOU KNOW, MAYBE
SAN FRANCISCO DOESN'T NEED A POWER PLANT.
MAYBE WE COULD DO SOMETHING BETTER WITH THIS LAND A UNION
ELECTRICIAN, A SINGLE MOM AND JUST AN ABSOLUTE LIGHTNING
BOLT OF A PERSON WHO STARTED THE COMMUNITY PROCESS THINKING
SOMETHING DIFFERENT HERE AND I CAN'T IMAGINE A BETTER PERSON
TO NAME THIS BUILDING FOUR THAN SUPERVISOR SOPHIE MAXWELL.
>> SOPHIE WHAT YOU DID WAS MORE THAN CLOSE A POWER PLANT.
YOU HELPED INSPIRE A COMMUNITY TO THINK WE COULD DOTY SOMETHING
BETTER. AND WHEN WE STEPPEDR. HERE NINE
YEARS AGO THE COMMUNITY WELCOMED US.
THERE WAS PEOPLE WHO SAIDEOM SUE COME, BUT WE'RE DOING THIS
TOGETHER. AND YOU KNOW WHAT WE DIDE, THAT
GOSH, WE DID SOMETHING LIKE 150 EVENTS.
WE HAD 82,000 PEOPLE HERE. BUT OF COURSE THE A PEOPLE WE
LISTENED WE THOUGHT MY FRIEND ALLISON HEATH IS HERE.
I LEARNED SOMETHINGNGER FOR HER. WE REALLY PROVED THAT IF YOU
ACTUALLY Y GET CONSENSUS WITH COMMUNITY THE COMMUNITY WILL
SUPPORT YOU AND THE THING ABOUT THAT IS THAT THAT WAS THE FIRST
STEP. THAT'S THEEHAAS FLYWHEEL SO YOUT
THE COMMUNITY MOVING BUT YOU
KNOW WHEN YOU GET THIS THING ENTITLED AND IT'S GLORIOUS DAY T
THE ONLY THING THAT HAPPENS AFTER THAT IS OOPS, THERE'S A T
PANDEMIC AND EVERYTHING WAS GOING TO STOPP.
BUTHE THAT'S WHEN THE CITY STEPPED UP AND IN NORMAL TIMES
THERE WAS THIS ADVERSARIAL RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN CITIES
AND DEVELOPERS THINKING T THAT E COULDN'T ALL HAVE NICE THINGS
AND NOW THAT CONVERSATION'S CHANGING'T.
THE CITY REALLY STEPPED UP STARTING WITH SUPERVISOR WALTONP
WHO WHEN WE TRIED TO QUIT BASICALLY SAID DON'T YOU DARE
YEAH YOU KNOW HE'S BECOME OUR LIFE COACH.
EVERY TIME YOU THINK IT'S IMPOSSIBLE HE REMINDS YOU IT'S
DIFFERENTURE T H AND THEY TELL E I TOLD YOU BE EASY.
IT'S NOT. BUT THAT STARTED BUT THEN THERE
WAS THOSE CITY AGENCIES EVERYONE WHO'S BEEN NAMED HERE
WHO TOOK THOSE SMALL ADJUSTMENTS THAT LITTLE CHANGED
THAT PIECE OF LEGISLATION THOSE THREE LITTLE FEET THAT WAY, AN
EXTRA DRIVEWAY, WHATEVER YOU CALLED IT.
BUT THOSE CITY PARTNERS MADE IT HAPPEN AT A VERY DIFFICULT
PERIOD. THE FLYWHEEL KEPT GOING
AND THEN WHEN YOU GET WELL TURNS OUT PEOPLE SAY YOU CAN'T
GET MONEY FOR MISSING MIDDLE HOUSING.
QUESTION WE ASKED IS WHYTI NOT SURE SAN FRANCISCO LOST TO
BANKS AND IT WAS ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE BUT THIS BRAVE
CHARACTER JPMORGAN WHO SAYS I DON'T SHOW UP AT THESE THINGS
SHOWED AND SAID AND SPENT 18 MONTHS FIGURING OUT TO FINANCE
THIS BUILDING AND THIS BUILDINGG WAS FINANCED AT A WAY T PEOPLE
DIDN'T THINK WAS POSSIBLE THANKS TO THAT WE GOT THIS.
>> SO THANK YOU. BUT IT'S PARTNERSHIPS WITH
OTHER CAPITAL TOO. >> YOU KNOW PGE WAS ON THIS
SITE FOR OVER 100 YEARS. THEY WERE FOUNDED HERE AND THEY
HAD A ROUGH COUPLE OF YEARS TOER AND THEY COULD HAVE QUIT BUT
THEY DIDN'T. THEY ACTUALLY KEPT CLEANINGLDT
PARTNERING WITH US TO REMOVE 150 YEARS OF INFRASTRUCTURE
AND BUILDING 150 YEARS OF INFRASTRUCTURE TO COME.
SOSO ONE DAY BUILDINGS LIKE THIS THE CANCER CENTER THAT'S BUILT
ACROSS THE STREETAN IN THIS AMAZING PARK THAT'S GOING TO
OPEN UP THERE WOULD HAPPEN SO I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO THEM
TO THANK YOU JEANNIE. SO THAT'S
WHAT IT TAKES. IT'S THAT FLYWHEEL OF CITY
COMMUNITY AND THEN CAPITAL WORKING TOGETHER TO KEEP MOVING
THAT COOPERATION THAT BETWEEN THE THREE OF YOU WHEN YOU DO
THAT CREATES THE MOMENTUM THAT MAKES PROJECTS LIKE THIS
POSSIBLE. YOU KNOW, A LOT OF PEOPLE SAY
THAT SAN FRANCISCO P PIB IS IN E MIDST OF RECOVERY.
WE'RE NOT WE'RE REINVENTINGOT AND WE'RE DOING STUFF LIKE THIS
AND WE'RE SHOWING PEOPLE THAT WHEN YOU BUILD FOR THE MIDDLE,
WHEN YOU BUILD FOR THE PEOPLE THAT PEOPLE SAY IS IMPOSSIBLE,
YOU CAN MOTIVATE THIS TO DOO THIS AGAIN AND AGAIN.
SO I AM THRILLED THAT IN ABOUT TWO WEEKS 105 SAN FRANCISCANS
WILL CALL THIS PLACE HOME AND WHAT I'LL BE MORE THRILLED
ABOUT IS THAT HOMECOMINGS LIKE THIS GET WELCOMED OVER AND OVER
AGAIN. SO THANK YOU TO EVERYONE WHO'S
HERE. THANK YOU TO MY TEAM THAT MADE
THIS POSSIBLE THE CAPITAL THAT BELIEVED IN US EVEN WHEN WE
SAID CRAZY THINGS LIKE MARCHING BANDS AND MISSING LITTLE
HOUSING AND ALL KINDS OF THINGS AND THE ALL OF YOU WHO SHOWED
UP TODAY O A TO SUPPORT A PROJET THAT REALLY SHOULD NOT HAVE
BEEN KEPT A GOING OVER THE PAST COUPLE OF YEARS.
BUT WHEN A CITY COMES TOGETHER AND YOU C GET THAT FLYWHEEL
MOVING, THINGS DON'T STOP. >> THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE
AND YOU KNOW I GET TO INTRODUCE A CHEERLEADER FOR THE CITY THAT
HAS REALLY PUSHED THIS MOMENT
AND IT'S BEEN A NICE THING TO SEE I SAN FRANCISCO GETTING
REINTRODUCED THE LAST COUPLE OF MONTHS AND WATCHING THE ENERGY
OF OUR MAYOR WHO'S SEEMINGLY EVERYWHERE AND THANKFULLY HERE
WITH US W TODAY, MAYOR LURIE. THANK YOU, ENRIQUE.
I APPRECIATE IT. SUPERVISE, A YOUR MAXWELL IT WAS
AN HONOR WALKING THROUGH THE BUILDING WITH YOU AND I LEARNED
A LOT FROM YOUOU IN THAT VERY MOMENT AND THAT IS ESSENTIAL
HOUSING NOT AFFORDABLE M HOUSING ESSENTIAL HOUSINGNG UNTIL 2011
2011 THIS AREA POWERED SAN FRANCISCO HOME TO THE TRO POWER
STATION. IT GENERATED A SIGNIFICANT
AMOUNT OF OUR CITY'S ENERGYIG O NEEDS AND FUELED DECADES OFED
INNOVATION. BUT AS WENO ALL KNOW, THAT ENERY
CAME AT A COST. THE POWER STATIONS AND THIS
POWER STATION POLLUTED THIS NEIGHBORHOODTE.
AND FOR OVER 150 YEARS THE WATERFRONT WE SEE TODAY HAS
BEEN INACCESSIBLE TO RESIDENTS THAT CHANGES TODAY ON BEHALF OF
THE CITYF AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, I AM PROUD TOCO
ANNOUNCERO THE OPENING OF THE SOPHIE MAXWELL BUILDING A 100%
ESSENTIAL WORKFORCE HOUSING COMMUNITY THAT BEGINS A NEW
CHAPTER FOR THIS DISTRICT. THEUI BUILDING IS DESIGNED WITH
INTENTION AND CARE. RESIDENTSKING FOR
FREE WI FI AND A F SHARED WORKSPACE.
ITS R ROOFTOP DECK OFFERS A FULL VIEW OF THE WATERFRONT FOR THE
FIRST TIME IN MORE THAN A A CENTURYY, THIS NEIGHBORHOOD CAN
STEP TO THE EDGE OF THE BAY AND CALL IT HOME.
THROUGH A PARTNERSHIP WITH THE DOGPATCH YMCA, THIS SPACE WILL
ALSO STAY CONNECTED TO THE COMMUNITY THAT SURROUNDS IT.
MOST IMPORTANTLY, YEAH WE CAN CLAP FOR THAT TOO.
BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY EVERY HOME HERE ISRY AFFORDABLE.
EACH ONE REPRESENTS STABILITY FOR A FAMILY OR FOR A SAN
FRANCISCAN WHO MAY OTHERWISE HAVE BEEN PRICED OUT.
WHEN WEE OPEN DOORS LIKE THESE WE SEND A MESSAGE TO THE PEOPLE
WHO MAKE THIS CITY WORK THAT YOU BELONG HERE, THAT YOUR KIDS
CAN GROW UP HERE AND THAT THEY CAN BUILD A FUTURE AND A PLACE
AND A CITY THAT THEY LOVE. PROJECTS LIKE THIS ONE HERE
SHOW WHAT IS POSSIBLE BUT WE AS ENRIQUE SAY WE NEED MORE THAN
JUST A FEWNRNR PROJECTS. WE NEED A CITYWIDE STRATEGY
AND THAT IS WHY I HAVE INTRODUCED OUR FAMILY ZONING
PLAN SOURAN WE CAN MAKE SAN FRANCISCO AFFORDABLE NOW
AND FOR A GENERATIONOROR TO COM. I'M SORRY TO GETRY A LITTLE
POLITICAL BUT THIS IS A GOOD MOMENT TO DO IT.
WE WANT TO MAKE IT POSSIBLE TOO BUILD ENOUGH HOUSING SO THAT
KIDS GROWING UP HERE WILL BENG ABLE TO RAISE THEIR OWN
FAMILIES HERE. WE WANT FIREFIGHTERS O O, POLICE
OFFICERS, SOCIAL WORKERS, TEACHERS AND NURSESOF TO LIVE
IN THE COMMUNITIES IN WHICH THEY SERVEIN AND THAT IS WHAT WE
ARE DOING ACROSS THE CITY POSSIBLE TO BUILD
HOUSING AT ALL INCOME LEVELS WHILE MAINTAINING
LOCAL CONTROL OVER HOW WE GROW THIS BUILDING.
ENRIQUE THIS BUILDING STANDS AT THE BEGINNING OF A A LARGER
TRANSFORMATION OF THE POTRERO POWER STATION SITEMA.
OVER. TIME THIS AREA WILL GROW INTO AL NEIGHBORHOOD FILLED WITH
HOMES, OPEN SPACES AND SMALL W BUSINESSES A PLACE FULL OF LIFE
THAT ONCEHA STOOD POLLUTED. IT'S FITTING THAT THIS NEW ERA
BEGINS WITHRA A BUILDING NAMED FOR SUPERVISOR SOPHIE MAXWELLG,
WHO SERVED DISTRICT TEN FOR A DECADE.
YOUR VISION SUPERVISOR, YOUR VISION AND YOUR DEDICATION TO
THIS DISTRICT HAVE INSPIRED SO MANY PEOPLE.
I WANT TO THANK YOU Y AND EVERYONE WHO WORKED TO
BRING THIS PROJECT TO LIFE. THIS IS JUST THEIF BEGINNING FOR
THIS NEIGHBORHOOD. WE WILL CONTINUE TO BUILD RIGHT
HERERE AND BRING THIS AREA TO LIFE.
LET'S KEEP BUILDING HOMES SO WORKING FAMILIES CAN STAY
AND THRIVE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND LET'S CONTINUE TO
MAKE THIS CORNER OF SAN FRANCISCO A PLACE OF RENEWAL
AND PRIDE. THANK YOU.
>>NC AND LET'S GO SAN FRANCISCO THANK YOU, MARY LARRY.
AND NOW I'D LIKE TO BRING ON STAGE FOUNDER OF THE HOMELESS
PRENATAL PROGRAMR MARTHA RYAN. GOOD MORNING, EVERYBODY.
I'M I'M HONORED TO BE HERE TODAY ON BEHALF OF THE HOMELESS
PRENATALES PROGRAM. FORGR OVER 30 YEARS WE HAVE
WORKED TO END GENERATIONAL POVERTY ONE FAMILY AT A TIME BY
SUPPORTING PARENTS ESPECIALLY MOTHERS AS THEY BUILD HEALTHY,
STABLE AND SELF-SUFFICIENT LIVES.
OUR MISSION IS GROUNDED IN A SIMPLE BUT POWERFUL BELIEF WHEN
PARENTS THRIVE, CHILDREN THRIVE WHEN CHILDRENIV THRIVE, ENTIRE
COMMUNITIES THRIVE. WE BRING LIFE TO THIS EVERY DAY
THROUGH HOUSING, EDUCATION, JOB TRAINING AND WRAPAROUND
SERVICES THAT EMPOWER FAMILIES W TO TAKE CHARGE OF THEIR FUTURE.
BUTHE FINDING SAFE, AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS ONE OF THE IS REALLY
THE MOST DIFFICULT PART OF THE EQUATION TO ATTAIN.
BUT TODAY IS TRULY AN EXCITING DAYXC.
THE SOPHIE MAXWELL BUILDING IS A PERFECT EXAMPLE OF WHAT'S
POSSIBLE WHEN PUBLIC, PRIVATE AND COMMUNITY PARTNERS COME
TOGETHER WITH A SHARED GOAL AND SHAREDED VALUES.
>> BY SETTING ASIDE PERMANENT HOUSING FOR HOMELESS PRENATAL
PROGRAM FAMILIESEL, THIS PARTNER TAKES OUR MISSION TO A NEW
LEVEL. BETHE HOMES WILL
PRIORITIZEDE FOR MOTHERS WHO ARE OBTAINING PURSUING EDUCATION OR
WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT WORKFORCE TRAINING.
WOMEN WHO ARE WORKING HARD TO INCREDIBLY HARD TO TRANSFORM
THEIR LIVES TO CREATE A BETTER FUTURE FORE THEIR CHILDREN
. ONE GAVEL OR TWO.
>> DO WE WANT TO DO ONCE OR TWICE JUST ONCE.
>> ALL RIGHT. ALL RIGHT, EVERYBODY.
WE ARE BACK IN OPEN SESSION. I WOULD REQUEST A MOTION THAT
THE BOARD FINDS THAT THAT IS IN THE BEST INTEREST OF THE
PUBLIC THAT THE BOARD ELECT NOT TO DISCLOSED ITS CLOSED SESSION
DELIBERATIONS. >> MOVE, MOVE BACK.
>> CHERYL. IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
WALTON? MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION ON THE MOTION NOT TO DISCLOSE
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDEL THEN I MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EITHER ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION WE WILL NOT DISCLOSE
OUR CLOSED SESSION DELIBERATIONS AND I SEE NO
OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER OF THE CLOSED SESSION HAS BEEN
HELD AND IS NOW FILED. >> MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? >> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT,
MR. PRESIDENT. THEN COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON AND ESTABLISHED BY THE BOARD
PRESIDENT TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD FOR MS. BELVA
DAVIS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THE LATE RETIRED SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT FORMER ASSISTANT CHIEF FRANK
BLACKBURN ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR THE LATE
MR. DANIEL CASANOVA ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR THE
LATE FATHER TONY LATORRE AND MR. JOHN J.
>> BOUVIER, THE THIRD AND I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END
OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS
BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK WE
ARE ADJOURNED